<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>condensō [en]</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Giacomo Mantani</name>
        <email>name.surname on gmail</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2021-02-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Davening (Schachter-Shalomi, Rabbi Zalman)</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2021-02-18-davening.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2021-02-18-davening.html</id>
    <published>2021-02-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#davening">Davening</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1355843320l/15893573.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="davening">Davening</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>We need that skepticism for quality assurance, because fooling oneself is easy. This is why I so love the statement in Psalm 34:9, “Taste and see that God is good.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if an insight emerges for you, take a few quiet moments to daven it in. And may you, too, as so many holy ones have before, experience the vision of prayer in your mind’s eye, the living taste of prayer in your heart, and the deep and gentle glow of prayer in your soul.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Deuteronomy 26:17–18, which speak of a reciprocal relationship between us and God. The verb used to capture this relationship is aleph-mem-resh. In the simple form this means “to say,” but here—uniquely in Torah—it is used in a transitive form: he’emarta and he’emirkha. God “says” us, and we “say” God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Just as I heard it said to me in a whisper, so I told it to you in a whisper” (Genesis Rabbah 3:4).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The imaginal world is a real world. Real things happen in the imaginal world that affect this world in turn.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>prayer begins with kavanah. To daven with kavanah means to pray with focus, intention, meaning. It means praying from the heart, rather than prayer centered solely in the mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kavanah is not attained in a day. We start small and build patiently on every small success. But if we aim our actions and our davening toward a godly place, we will get there.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I can’t do this without Your help.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Dear God, please help me to let this thought go.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>), wisdom to yield ko’ach mah (), the power of “What?”—the wisdom of getting to know what a thing is. Wise Mind seeks to understand the mitzvah lifnai ve-lifnim, inside and out. He wants to do the mitzvah in a completely integrated and organic way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“duties of the heart,” in Bachya ibn Pakuda’s famous phrase,3 cannot be fulfilled without conscious and deliberate intention.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Saying the words without intent is clearly unsatisfactory; on the other hand, saying every word and syllable with full and true kavanah is close to impossible.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My entire life and everything I do are nothing but God Godding Godself as Zalman. The best thing I can do, then, is to make my life a good ride for God, to consciously devote my actions to that purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The awareness that we stand in the presence of the Living God is one of the most important realizations we can install in our operative consciousness. God is always present. The question is, how present are we? We want to stand in that Presence without opacity. Our work is to penetrate, in meditation and in action, to the very heart of being nokhach penei ha-Shem (Lamentations 2:19), of being truly present before God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Meister Eckhart was trying to express when he wrote, “The eye with which I see God is the same eye with which God sees me. My eye and God’s eye are one eye, one sight, one knowledge, and one love.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>meditating on the Tetragrammaton, the letters of God’s mysterious name, can open a channel to bring down the holy. As in Vipassana or pranayama, we can use our breathing to help us get there. Your lungs without breath are like the yud, the smallest letter, the vanishing point. Our inhalation forms the hey, letter of breath: hhhhhhh. At the top of the breath we form the vav, straight as an erect backbone. Then we breathe out—hhhhhhh—another hey. So we invite YHVH to come down and dwell within us. As Jews we are concerned about living in this world. Ours is not primarily an Ein Sof focus, a preoccupation with the world beyond the beyond, but a Gaia focus. Our fundamental kavanah is not to leave the world behind but to bring God into this world, to create the “Kingdom of heaven” in the life we live, right here and now.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Yir’ah, awe, is sometimes translated as fear, but neither completely captures the idea. The Hebrew root of yir’ah is yud-resh-aleph . The root of words meaning sight or to see is resh-aleph-hey . Yir’ah arises from the state of being seen for what we really are.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The awareness that we are being seen, that we do everything we do in the presence of that Witness—that is the true path to and meaning of yir’ah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The disciple says, “Master, I couldn’t find a place where no One can see me.” The awareness that we are being seen, that we do everything we do in the presence of that Witness—that is the true path to and meaning of yir’ah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If I ascend to heaven, there You are; if I make my bed in hell, You are there” (Psalm 139:8).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Proverbs 3:6, “Be-khol derakhekha da’eihu, Know God in all your ways.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>important forms of consciousness maintenance, of kavanah watching kavanah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If I knew it, I would be it; if I were it, I would know it.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>le-khaven el ha-matarah, to aim at the bull’s-eye. (Le-khaven is from the same root as kavanah, kaf-vav-nun.) This is a useful metaphor. When I finally embrace a matarah—a bull’s-eye, a target for my existence—and I say, “Yes, I will go with that, I will collaborate with that, I will invest myself in that,” then my embracing becomes a kavanah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>olam ha-ba—not “the world to come,” as the phrase is usually translated, but a world that is, at this very moment, becoming in us and around us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I come with a scroll-book on me,” says the psalmist, “in which there is one thing written”—like a journal, in which you declare its purpose on page one. This is what the scroll says: “My only desire is to do Your will. I want Your teaching in my very kishkes” (Psalm 40:8–9). This is my intent. This is what I want to do. I’m not there yet, but I’m on my way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>At the heart of kavanah lies the question: Why? Hebrew has two different words for why, madu’a and lamah, and each has a slightly different emphasis. Madu’a asks, “Mah yadu’a? What is known to us?” Philosophers might call this the what of etiology. It wants to know about origins and causes. Lamah asks, “Le-mah? What for?” This is the why of teleology. It asks: Where are we going with this? What is the goal? The why at the heart of kavanah is not only the madu’a of origins but the lamah of ultimate purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Every locksmith has a master key with which he can open many doors. Neginah is such a key, for it can unlock all doors.” Why? Because a niggun sung in the proper way is like doing teshuvah, like a moment of true repentance and turning to God. The wellsprings of niggun and teshuvah are the simple yearnings of the heart that we all share.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The word nusach can mean both text and melody.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>nusach can also mean the melody or musical mode of a given time and place, which is what I mean here. Nusach conveys information.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nusach also conveys emotion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The ga’agu’im or longing niggunim that raise up these unspoken questions can create a sacred space that all can share.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes the heart wants to daven, and the mind starts arguing. But, as the great cantor and educator Max Helfman said once, “you can’t argue with a song or a dance!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Maybe “the work is not upon you to finish” (Pirkei Avot 2:21). Someone else may complete your tune someday.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>with the emotions that you hear behind the words.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>emotional landscapes—sometimes within a single paragraph.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A niggun is a path to God, a “song of ascension.” But we must set out along that path! We must travel with that intention in mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>True prayer is like the iceberg: little that is visible on the surface, much that happens below.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the invitation to prayer says “come as you are.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>our souls accept only one outcome when it comes to prayer: transformation. We do not wish just to spin our mental wheels: We want to be changed. We want to be moved. We want to end in a better place than where we started. Our souls yearn for this. If we really mean the words we say, how can we help but be moved?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>prayers as a journey through four different landscapes, four distinct facets of human experience: physical, emotional, intellectual, and spiritual. Each facet has its own character; each communicates in its own language; each speaks to a different part of us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Asiyah is the realm of the practical and the sensible—the stuff we apprehend with our senses. We’re packing for our spiritual journey here, grounding ourselves in our physical bodies and in the here and now.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Yetzirah, on a human level, is the world of feelings, the world of passion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The language here is plural. In Yetzirah, the realm of emotions and love, the boundaries between ourselves and others begin to feel permeable</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I’m attracted to you in Asiyah! I love you in Yetzirah!” She’s saying, “Meet me in Beriyah.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In Beriyah, the language is no longer immanent but transcendent. Beriyah is the place of Wow, the place of wonder. We praise and give thanks for the constant and miraculous regeneration by a Creator who “renews, each day and always, the work of creation.” This is not the big bang understanding, in which a single event set the rest of the universe in motion. It is a mystical vision of the entire world being created anew in every instant. A person who sees the universe with such eyes can welcome each and every moment as a new opportunity for praise. In Beriyah, we are still in the group, but what the group does at this stage is to give you a matrix in which to do your individual work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>An important part of davening is to just sit be-nachat ru’ach, in serenity of spirit, and to allow for that to come in.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The word Atzilut refers to something that is noble, high, beyond. The world of Atzilut transcends our level of understanding. Boundaries are gone, definitions are gone. Individual words and thoughts are gone. We ourselves do not exist. Being as we know it has ceased.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kabbalistic tradition imagines us davening the Amidah in the world of Atzilut.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So never mind the achievements and attainments; just talk like a friend to God about what you are really concerned about. If a thought comes, turn it into a prayer. These heartfelt prayers are the ones that are really important; these are the prayers we save for Atzilut, sending them directly to the highest level. I start by saying the introductory verse: “Adonai sefatai tiftach u-fi yagid tehilatekha, Please God, open my lips and let my mouth declare Your praise.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When a concern comes up for anything, turn it into a bakashah, a request. Then set is aside and go back to stillness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Each dimension of ourselves—physical, emotional, intellectual, spiritual—has its own needs and speaks its own language. I don’t want to leave any part of me out. I want my davening, my spiritual life and practice, to integrate them all. How can this holy conversation be real unless my entire self is engaged?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We cannot think our way to God. We cannot reach God by a safe, step-by-step process.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we limit God to the ultimate abstraction, then whom are we praying to? But if instead we come at this from a Yetzirah heart space, that changes everything. If we attune ourselves to Yetzirah, the language of the davening makes sense, and all the stuff that we’re talking about here make sense. The feeling that we’re “doing the divine thing” makes sense—that’s why I like the term davening best, to describe what we’re doing at prayer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Where in this many-layered universe does compassion reside? Who is the You of God for you?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All we need are feelings that we want to share with the listening presence of the universe. If you are not yet used to praying, start by expressing yourself in your own words.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>how much time they had. I got some flak</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Voice arouses kavanah,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Daven so your heart can feel what your lips are saying!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Every breath will praise Yah” (Psalm 150:6). We can use this as a meditation with the YHVH, the Tetragrammaton. First empty your lungs and contemplate the yud, the smallest Hebrew letter, closest to emptiness. Then you breathe in, making a hhhhh sound; that’s the first hey. You hold the breath for a moment, sending it to all six directions in your body—that’s the vav, the sixth letter of the alphabet. Then you breathe out, hhhhh, to make the other hey. So we can use this prayer to scan our lung capacity and check in with our breath.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Barukh ha-Shem—thank God. At last! Now I am free just to sit and enjoy. I don’t need to run; I don’t need to make, do, fix, or change. For one day, I can just be.” If we pause from running through our day to offer a prayer, we find that we have created a little piece of Shabbos</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Throughout the centuries, the payyetanim—Jewish writers of spiritual poetry (piyyut, piyyutim)—have sought new ways of declaring their love for God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ashkenazi siddurim have “Ahavah rabbah ahavtanu” in the morning prayers and “Ahavat olam beit Yisrael amkha ahavtah” in the evening prayer. Chabad and some of the Sepharad siddurim, however, follow the Ari, who saw an important kavanah in the first letters of ahavat olam ahavtanu: aleph (1) + ayin (70) + aleph (1) add up to 72, a number the kabbalists saw as a permutation of YHVH: yud = 10; yud hey = 15; yud hey vav = 21; yud hey vav hey = 26. And 10 + 15 + 21 + 26 = 72.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we study Torah, may we see clearly what is meant for us to know. When we do Mitzvot, may all our feelings sit harmonious in our heart. Focus all our hearts’ longing on that moment, when we stand in Your Presence, in awe and adoration.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>harder to grasp than it sounds. The Tikkunei Zohar marvels, “You are One, but not in the sense of enumeration”—not “one” as an alternative to two, three, or four, but a Unity of infinite existence and infinite potential.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>asking for what we truly need is the hardest part of prayer. We throw up all sorts of obstacles.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whom am I praying to? I am praying to God, however I understand and experience that word right here and right now. I may not be praying to the God that is All, but simply sharing my tsuris with the face of God with which I am most intimate. Perhaps I am praying to whatever it is that listens in the universe. I don’t need to do any more than that. Who am I to ask for anything? I am a creation and manifestation of godliness. I am a wave in the ocean and a world unto myself. The infinite potential for creativity and love in the universe manifests in me and through me, as it does in every other creature. And will it help? We know some parents pray with all their hearts for a child to be cured of a life-threatening disease, and yet the little one dies. We pray daily for peace, yet we are still at war. Prayer is not a switch with which we can control the universe. But I do believe that we can, with our prayers, reach dimensions of existence that we do not otherwise have access to and that the openings in those higher worlds bring blessings down to us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A prayer truly prayed is the beginnings of its own answer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“O God, open up my lips, and let my mouth speak Your praise.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This first sentence reminds us that prayer begins with silence. Think back to the silence that follows the last, enlarged dalet of the Shema statement’s final ECHAD. This is not a silence of absence but a silence full of the presence of the One, a silence of infinite potential.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we want our prayers to be answered, we have to make sure not to hang up the phone too quickly.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>During the week, you can take a piece of notepaper and a pencil. Reflect for a few moments after your davening and see what comes down. “So what do I have to do today, Ribbono shel olam?” Write down what comes to you, and try to refer to it during the day or before you go to sleep at night.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I begin in Asiyah, putting on my tallis and tefillin first, creating the prayer space that I need. I check in with my body, and I say Asher Yatzar, acknowledging the miracle of the limbs and organs that sustain me. Then I look out of the window and see the world outside, the people and the buildings and the trees, the sun or the rain or the snow, and I say, “Thank You, Ribbono shel olam, all of these are wonderful, and I thank You.” I want to spend a little time in Yetzirah if I possibly can, giving my emotions a voice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I know that without help I’m not going to make it. I close with the Amidah’s final thought: “Oseh shalom, just as in the heavens everything works out as it should, so please, bring peace and tranquility upon us as well.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the first task before us is to empty ourselves of our expectations—to free ourselves of the hold they have over us. I always quote Swami Satchidananda, who would say, “Don’t make any appointments, you won’t have any dis-appointments!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Dear God, whatever jealousies and resentments I might harbor in my heart, please remove this judgment from me.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Reb Pinchas of Koretz, the great Hasidic master, wondered how we can pray for other people to become better. Are we not depriving that person of their choice and free will? The answer, he says, is that we are all part of each other. You are in me, and I am in you. Praying for the “you in me” to be better—the “you” that resides in my heart—somehow helps the “me in you” to do something good for you, and the “you in you” to become better. This is not a moral vision but an organismic vision. On a prayerful level, we are all part of each other and of the greater whole.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If I am not for myself, who will be? But if I am only for myself, what am I?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>aleph-mem-nun, meaning to be firm or trustworthy. Amen means “So be it. May your words come to pass.” It is prayer and affirmation in one.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Gods of the Word, Archetypes in the Consonants</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2019-07-04-gods-of-the-word.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2019-07-04-gods-of-the-word.html</id>
    <published>2019-07-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-07-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#gods-of-the-word-archetypes-in-the-consonants-magnus-margaret">Gods of the Word: Archetypes in the Consonants (Magnus, Margaret)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1359625340l/1760292.jpg" />

</div>
<h3 id="gods-of-the-word-archetypes-in-the-consonants-magnus-margaret">Gods of the Word: Archetypes in the Consonants (Magnus, Margaret)</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Jakobson, Jespersen, Bloomfield, Sapir, Firth – have written beautifully insightful articles on the relationship between sound and meaning, it has never reached the mainstream, and as far as I know, only Keith McCune and Amanuma have gone through all the major sound facts in any language.1 This very marginal field is called sound symbolism (though I prefer to call it phonosemantics, because I find the word ‘symbolism’ confusing).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Each word has an aspect of meaning which lies deeper than any of its senses, and it is fundamentally on this meaning that all the senses depend.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That problem arises because we are posing a question on the wrong level of abstraction – a question which therefore is meaningless.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The essential nature of a symbol is that it is first of all itself, and only secondarily is it its function.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>With the word as the mechanism of creation, everything that did not yet exist was named and all appeared.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Velar phonemes pronounced at the back of the mouth (/g/, /k/, /h/, /G/) are generally receptive. Labial phonemes pronounced at the lips (/b/, /p/, /v/, /f/, /m/, /w/) are rarely receptive and are often directed outward.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Socrates’ Hypothesis 1. That each phoneme has a meaning which it passes on to every word that contains it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“In truth language does not reside in man but man stands in language and speaks out of it.” We wander the earth, as the instruments of these peculiar sound beings.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I too am a true believer in the autonomy of the archetype. A /t/ or an /h/ is no less than a Zeus. The consonants are not essentially physical, but they live, evolve and influence human affairs. We overlook something essential if we deny that they can get up and walk around. This is not to say that their existence is independent of the human psyche. But then everything depends on everything.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are, so to speak, blinded to content by form. Reference does this by taking a possible context for a word very seriously, and freezing the word within a specific context into a ‘thing’ unto itself. It makes static what was fluid by limiting it to a context and claiming it to be a different thing in this context than in the next. The transition from process to thing is part and parcel to limitation within context.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Tao of Physics</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we are correct about the usefulness of drawing the distinction between inherent and referential semantics, then the mouth can be viewed as a system whose physics in part determines the meanings of words. Imagine that each phoneme has inherent physical properties.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>deduce the very general physical properties of the phonemes by how they interact in words, and this may or may not prove to correlate with muscle tension, air pressure in the mouth, etc. during articulation. Unfortunately there is probably no very reliable way to measure this muscle tension or air pressure. If there were a real physiological basis to this ‘wild idea’, one could imagine using word semantics to make educated guesses about muscle tension. This in turn could perhaps be used to make predictions about syllable structure and other phonological processes, as well as word semantics.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When an idea gets repeated often enough, it becomes common knowledge. When it becomes really convincing, then it starts sinking deeper and deeper into the unconscious recesses of the language. The sound meanings we are discussing and also metaphors are examples of this subconscious language - this background of invisible assumptions that we all share as speakers of English. The history of human thought lies buried in the phoneme meanings and other unconscious aspects of language.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Emerson says that the corruption of man is followed by the corruption of language.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The whole of nature is a metaphor of the human mind.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The mystic must first be an extremely good scientist, for science is the starting point and prerequisite of all higher endeavors. It is the discipline of stating truthfully and non-judgmentally what was observed – no more and no less.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>mystical and scientific thought systems are reconciled in the realization that mind gives rise to matter, and not the other way around. The material universe is a thought.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Language, as it turns out, is not dead, but a living being on whose health all of us depend. The fact that each consonant is an archetype is significant not because of what it can be used for, but because when one meets each god face to face, one cannot but realize that it is conscious, present, and alive. It looks upon the child who wanders into its dominion with a steady eye, and tolerates her only as long as her intentions are pure. One leaves with no doubt that this force, though patient, is silently recording every thought, and will have its way in the end. We may as well deal with the gods now, face to face, rather than be forced to eat our own garbage at some future period of time. There is linguistic ecology just as surely as there is planetary ecology.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All that matters is the act of speaking itself, the manner in which my relationship with him plays itself out. I dance with English, and our tale is only just beginning. Everything depends on my recognition of this.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>as children busy in our happy task, and with the door left ajar.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Essence of the Bhagavad Gita</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-11-01-essence-bhagavad.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-11-01-essence-bhagavad.html</id>
    <published>2017-11-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-11-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#the-essence-of-the-bhagavad-gita-explained-by-paramhansa-yogananda-as-remembered-by-his-disciple-swami-kriyananda-paramhansa-yogananda">The Essence of the Bhagavad Gita: Explained By Paramhansa Yogananda, As Remembered By His Disciple, Swami Kriyananda (Paramhansa Yogananda)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1387217298l/19502676.jpg" />

</div>
<h3 id="the-essence-of-the-bhagavad-gita-explained-by-paramhansa-yogananda-as-remembered-by-his-disciple-swami-kriyananda-paramhansa-yogananda">The Essence of the Bhagavad Gita: Explained By Paramhansa Yogananda, As Remembered By His Disciple, Swami Kriyananda (Paramhansa Yogananda)</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>One final thought: When you give people a choice of product or service tiers, you do something subtle but powerful. You shift the internal question for the customer from, “Should I buy this?” to “Which one should I buy?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it should be added that in this realm of appearances maya does have its own reality. Everything is a dream, but even dreams, as dreams, are real.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Self-realization and the knowledge of God, are synonymous.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the truths propounded in the Gita are applicable at all levels of life: material, mental, emotional, and spiritual. Paramhansa Yogananda makes the point that every great scripture is multi-leveled, addressing the vast variety of human needs from a standpoint of divine wisdom.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>there are several paths to God, according, not to people’s beliefs, but to each person’s own temperament. He delineates the right attitudes for the devotee, the various delusions that can prevent him from finding God, and the way to overcome them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A true scripture, Paramhansa Yogananda stated, addresses human needs in their entirety.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>three nadis, or subtle channels of life force, called</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Is the spiritual eye, one may ask, merely symbolic? No, it is actually beheld, and is, in fact, a reflection of the light in the medulla, through which the energy moves down the spine in three nadis, or subtle channels of life force, called the sushumna, the vajra, and the chitra.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Circumstances,” Paramhansa Yogananda commented, “are always neutral. They appear positive or negative according to the corresponding reactions of the heart.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every act, every thought, has its specific consequences.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This means we should not depend on our good habits alone to see us through psychological and spiritual tests. Habit born of past actions may give us good karma, but karma itself must be transcended in dedication to the truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you succeed in converting enough mental citizens to the side of goodness, they will outnumber the unruly ones and will gradually win them over, resulting in your rapid spiritual progress.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We must transform our faults into virtues.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every human trait begins as a simple thought. There is nothing man can achieve or even conceive that, as an idea, is inaccessible to any other human being.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The part played by the guru is not to make his disciples over in his own image, but, by sharing his magnetism with them, to uplift their consciousness</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>How is one to know what course in life is right or wrong? The first rule is, “Do what works.” That is why the question, “What was the outcome?” is more important than, “What are they doing?” Only from the outcome of a course of action can it be known with any certainty whether the act was justified or not. The maxim, “The end justifies the means,” is true only as long as the end is visualized in theory, in advance. Once it has been actually reached, however, it will show whether the means to it were right or not. Wrong means to an imaginary good end will produce, at last, disharmony and failure.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Judge your thoughts and actions by their effects—on yourself, first; then on others. Are they peace-inducing? Are they as universally beneficial as possible? Do they help to expand your understanding and sympathies? Have they brought greater harmony to your environment?—or have they produced disharmony? Do they inspire you and others? or have they brought less hope generally—even despair?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One should not wish harm to anything, but one may be obliged to kill harmful creatures.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Arjuna, nothing is ever lost. What you relinquish on the material plane you will rediscover a thousand times more wonderfully in God.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>sensations such as heat and cold, pleasure and pain are generated through the senses in (their) contact with the world. They are ideas only: transitory, each with its beginning and end. O Descendent of Bharata, bear with them patiently.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>one who is calm and even-minded, never ruffled during pain and pleasure: he alone gains consciousness of his eternal existence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Why lament that which cannot be avoided?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>stoicism</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One needs to know why it is necessary to seek truth, how best to go about it, and what one may expect (stated with as much intellectual clarity as possible, though emphasizing that direct experience alone conveys true understanding).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Renunciation of the world in thought as well as in deed is essential.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The mind itself is the battlefield. There is no other.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The true Self can be sustained only by spiritual states of consciousness, such as divine love, calmness, and bliss.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whether they are greeted with pleasure or distaste depends entirely on one’s mental conditioning. The human mind, unlike the minds of lower animals, can train itself to like anything.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“as if smiling.” This phrase, Yogananda said, is important, because it indicates that God is no stern judge of human behavior, but is “on our side.” He wants us to advance spiritually, and forever forgives us if we err.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To be “even-minded and cheerful” under all circumstances is the first duty of the yogi.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>even-mindedly toward his goal by performing ever calmly his karmically assigned duties. To be “even-minded and cheerful” under all circumstances is the first duty of the yogi. This</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To be “even-minded and cheerful” under all circumstances is the first duty of the yogi. This obviously does not mean being cheerful about other people’s suffering! One must respect, and even empathize with, their pains—as Krishna did. As regards one’s own pains, however, the aspiring yogi must firmly banish all thought of ego-identification with both pleasure and pain. Pain may in fact be “happening,” but he must not think of it as his own. The more he can resist the oppositional states of Nature—maya’s dualities (dwaita)—</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>good practice for the devotee is deliberately to submit himself to extreme opposites: heat and cold, pleasure and pain, etc. He should be careful not to test his powers too far beyond their proven ability so far. To do so would be fanaticism. Indeed, it might prove counter-productive: One could stand too long under a cold shower, and find himself hardly feeling warm again for months! One could even endanger his health. Along with the counsel to be even-minded and cheerful is an equally important one: Use common sense.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>For even-mindedness, an important practice is to give up likes and dislikes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nothing belongs to you—not even your own ego! Firmly to hold this attitude is the way to inner freedom</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Even the refusal to act is a kind of activity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What is the ego? Imagine the moon reflected in many vessels of water. Each vessel contains the same reflection, yet the reflection seems, in each of them, to be individual.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The decision not to act is like restraining a horse by the reins: It takes an effort of will, and therefore implies an act of some kind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>spiritual progress consists not in actually achieving anything, but in simply removing the distortions that obscure the nature of reality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Chapter Eleven</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In this yoga there is only that one direction (with no polar opposite).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To the sincere spiritual aspirant, little could seem more like hell than to be stuck for all eternity in an ego, even if the body in which one lives is forever healthy, supple, youthful, and full of energy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Heaven is usually offered as bait: a place where people spend eternity in a beautiful, idyllic environment of great natural beauty, surrounded by “angels.” To the sincere spiritual aspirant, little could seem more like hell than to be stuck for all eternity in an ego, even if the body in which one lives is forever healthy, supple, youthful, and full of energy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“center everywhere, circumference nowhere,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>only Hinduism (and I say this as one who was, himself, raised in orthodox Christianity) formally teaches moksha, or liberation from the very ego, in union with the Omnipresent, Divine Consciousness. Jesus Christ taught it. Few however, if any, of his self-declared followers believe that when he spoke of heaven he was referring to that same state of moksha: complete liberation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>most religious teachers offer a compromise of lower spiritual truths, they betray their own religion. Paramhansa Yogananda used to say, “Jesus Christ was crucified once, but his teachings have been crucified every day, throughout Christendom, since that time.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If only Hinduism declares this highest spiritual truth, surely it is because only Hinduism has not been confined in the “straitjacket” of a religious organization! It has grown naturally, rather, and has not been suffocated in the musty air of official decrees regarding what is, and what is not, the highest truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>its attachment to the results of action. Those results, because of that attachment, must return to their source.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Pray in this way: ‘I will reason, I will will, I will act, but guide Thou my reason, will, and activity to the right path in everything.’”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The way to this achievement is to remain ever calm in the Self, free from any thought of either acceptance or possession.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Pride goes before a fall.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Scripture itself is no substitute for self-effort.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>well when the land all around is in flood.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the Vedas are of no more use than a well when the land all around is in flood.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To the knower of Brahman (the Supreme Spirit) the Vedas are of no more use than a well when the land all around is in flood.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>wanting some sort of ego-payment for favors rendered. The Lord is no merchant</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Those who seek lesser favors from God are asking for a teaspoon of soil when they might have the whole kingdom. The problem in people’s minds is, of course, that they think to possess.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To attain God-consciousness, it is necessary to release all attachment to thoughts of “I” and “mine.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Some people—many hermits, for example—</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Perfect evenness of mind and feeling is itself the definition of yoga.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Affirmations of calmness in the midst of stress often have the contrary effect of creating more tension! In any case, calmness can be affirmed effectively only with inner calmness. Such calmness can hardly be established without also stilling the thoughts in meditation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“One can run nervously,” the Master replied, “or one can run calmly, but not to run when one needs to is to be lazy!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Pranayama is a condition, not a technique.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>withdrawal of the energy is the true meaning of pranayama: “yama (control) of the prana (energy).” Pranayama is a condition, not a technique. The practice of pranayama is to achieve energy control.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Breathlessness is deathlessness.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is helpful, when trying to develop emotional detachment, to concentrate one’s energy in the spine,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There are two requirements, above all, for the attainment of wisdom. One, to withdraw the mind not only from sense objects, but from the senses themselves; and, two, to remain merged in the consciousness of God as the most desirable of all goals.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>suffering diminishes when there is a decrease of self-interest. The discernment of this truth leads to the first faint stirrings of recollection that a reality exists that is more than the ego and the body. The fog of delusion begins to lift from the mind, and one no longer strikes out at the world in anger for not giving him what he wants. From acceptance of what is comes a gradual decrease of worldly attachment. From lessened attachment comes lessening interest in the objects of the senses, and an increase of longing for true wisdom—a longing which awakens devotion in the heart, love of truth, and intense aspiration to know true and everlasting bliss.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mistakes on the path are always possible. The devotee should acknowledge them sincerely and openly (at least to himself), and then simply forsake them. He should avoid the further mistake of becoming upset with himself. He should keep his mind focused steadfastly on the polestar of his true goal: union with God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Since the ego is a delusion, anything that tempts it to affirm its own separate reality is a delusion also. And so too, indeed, is any distress one may feel with oneself for having succumbed to delusion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whenever you feel pleasure, let it remind you of soul-bliss. Whenever you see beauty, take into yourself the joy you feel in it. Let every worldly happiness remind you of the much greater happiness of the Self. Some yogis recommend complete indifference to the world. What a dry outlook! Far better is it, my Guru taught, to enjoy with God the beauties and the pure delights of this world, by focusing on the inner joy you feel during experiences that uplift the heart’s feelings</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Spiritual progress is achieved not by the tense effort demanded for material success, but rather by a process of upward relaxation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In fact, the key to right meditation is relaxation—physically, emotionally, and mentally.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>High truths cannot be learned: they can only be remembered in the Self.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>doing harm to others never succeeded in bringing him happiness;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All who would unite their souls with God must follow that same path: yama and niyama (right action); asana (firmness of posture, and keeping the spine straight to enable the energy to flow freely through it); pranayama (control over the energy of the body); pratyahara (interiorization of the mind); dharana (one-pointed concentration); dhyana (absorption in deep meditation); and samadhi (oneness).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Actionlessness cannot be attained by mere inaction. One who forsakes work (in the name of divine aloofness from activity) cannot reach perfection.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My Guru explained that a liberated master, whatever his role on earth, never loses his inner awareness of freedom</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Can they cease from breathing by merely not breathing? Can they refrain from thinking by merely not thinking? Can they achieve silence by merely not speaking? One wonders how any aspirant to wisdom can conceive such absurdities! All creation exists in a vibratory state. The very atoms are constantly in movement. Prakriti (Nature) forces man to be active. Anyone who tries to be inactive becomes merely lazy. Anyone who pretends to be disinvolved in the world around him is being merely hypocritical. In order to achieve the actionless state it is utterly necessary to act consciously—not merely driven by Nature, but deliberately and intelligently, like a surfer going with the waves of circumstance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>any show of religiosity is acceptable only according to the depth of inner sincerity involved.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The wish to impress indicates a desire for results, rather than true sincerity of feeling.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The greater the will, the greater the flow of energy.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>No activity engaged in merely to impress others (or even God) will, in the end, bear divine fruit. Spiritual progress is achieved above all by desiring it intensely, and not by inflicting violent discipline on the body.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Perform those actions which your duty dictates, for action is better than inaction. Without action, in-deed, even the act of maintaining life in the body would not be possible.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it is often best to undertake first those battles which one can be more confident of winning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“One moment,” the saying goes, “in the company of a saint can be your raft over the ocean of delusion.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Very few human beings are ready for the highest spiritual blessing: the help of a true guru.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The work before him of achieving infinity is colossal! If he has any wisdom at all, he must surely see that he needs all the help he can get!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Life must be continuously progressive. If it tries to remain stationary, it is already living death. There are devas, or angels, to whom we can appeal, or with whose energies we can work in cooperation. As with other human beings, we gain much more by giving to them than by trying to snatch our gain from them. Even in the ashrams of great gurus, those disciples receive the most spiritually who, by their appreciation, give energy and don’t try to draw God’s blessings self-centeredly to themselves.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The age we now live in is an upward-moving age (not Kali Yuga, as people generally believe</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All things exist in a state of vibration. That is how the Supreme, ever-unmoving Spirit brought about the appearance of a reality separate from itself. As the blades of a fan, rotating rapidly, give the appearance of a solid circular disk, so Cosmic Vibration, in its infinite number of intensely rapid vibrations, gives the appearance of substance, variety, even of solidity. Thus we have, for example, the rocks, which to our senses appear very solid but which are now known to be only vibrations of energy, and which, even as material substance, are composed largely of space.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Without images, people’s devotion becomes dry.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>feel that the energy which enables him to move and breathe is not his own, personally.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To gorge one’s food gluttonously is to feed not only the body but the ego.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Vibration is action, which is to say, karma.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>AUM is properly written with three letters. The first letter signifies Brahma; the second one, Vishnu; and the third (properly pronounced as a slightly drawn-out hum), Shiva.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>AUM samadhi. His next perception is of Kutastha Chaitanya, or Tat, the Christ consciousness behind the vibrations of his body—and the center of every vibration of the body, reflecting the motionless Spirit beyond creation. Gradually his consciousness expands with the Christ consciousness, or Tat, until he perceives it as infinite. It is after reaching that stage, my Guru explained to me, that one may be called a master.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Suffering comes primarily from the thought,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The more things change, the more they remain unchanged.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What needs changing is no social system, but human consciousness. The best way to change society, surely, would be to create little societies that can inspire others to make the recommended changes, individually, in themselves, rather than forcing everyone to march in lock-step togetherness toward some general “good” that often ends in disaster. If an example works, others may be inspired by it, and may want to change. Without the desire to change, no one will ever do better at anything. The first responsibility the universe places on every person’s shoulders is this: “Change yourself.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>yet still I work on for the upliftment of others. There, where all uplifting work is done, am I.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Never should the wise condemn the ignorant for the ego-motivation they manifest. Instead, being themselves enlightened, they should seek only to inspire others in the direction of preferring to perform right, dutiful action.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>as foolish people, out of attachment to ego, act in hope of rewards, so should the wise also (even if wisdom has lifted them out of any personal need to be active), act with dispassion and non-attachment, glad to be of service to others as their guides</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Thoughts are universally and not individually rooted.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To drive a dark mood out of the mind, for example, try this simple method: Focus your energy and attention strongly at the point between the eyebrows. The magnetism you generate there will lift you out of the fogs of gloom to a higher, more spiritual atmosphere where peace, joy, and complete acceptance reign.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>He should not, however, allow anything to disturb his inner peace. Even if he sees wrong in the world, and accepts it as a manifestation of maya, he can remain inwardly undisturbed by it, and can work impersonally to improve matters in this world.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Work with what is, not with what you think should be.” All human suffering is due to the simple thought that things ought to be other than they are.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Don’t let others tell you what you, in their eyes, ought to be. On the other hand, never dismiss their advice arrogantly. Try at the same time, rather, to be always true to your own nature. You will never change yourself by suppression. Real change comes only by transcendence. If there is some quality in yourself that you don’t like, try to lift your awareness to a higher level.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Never let yourself become infatuated (infatuation is extreme attraction) with anything or anyone. Never let yourself hate anything or anyone. Develop an attitude, rather, of accepting the cosmic dream as it is, even when it becomes a nightmare!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“People are so skillful in their ignorance!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Time must simply pass, as nature takes its course, and brings that person gradually to the point where, after repeated disappointments and the slight glimmering of hope for greater understanding, the inner person finally emerges in the full dignity of a refined human being.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Desire is the sinful destroyer of wisdom and of Self-realization.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The senses are declared to be superior to the body (since they convey perception); the mind is superior to the senses (both inner and outer, since it is the perceiver); the discriminating intellect is superior to the mind (since it understands what it perceives); and the Self is superior to the discriminating intellect (since it is both perception and understanding).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it is difficult for man to perceive that every state of consciousness already contains its opposite: that, in happiness, suffering is already present; and that (fortunately) suffering already contains at its center the seeds of joy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>God is Infinite Consciousness. Only Kali Yuga consciousness could have visualized Him as uniquely possessing a human form—as people believed the Earth was the center of everything, and still believed as late as the end of the nineteenth century that our sun was the center. Once every soul encased in an ego prison realizes itself as the Infinite, and no longer one little “sliver of glass” individually reflecting the cosmic light, it becomes the Infinite—God Himself. There is no difference, in essence, between Krishna, Jesus Christ, Buddha, or any other great master. There is no difference—again, in essence—between them and the rest of us, once we realize ourselves as the one God who, for a time, thought himself encased in these human egos. Everything is God. In God, all comparisons and relativities cease. The soul of Everyman was never born; nor did it ever die. In Vedantic truth there was always only one reality, one Spirit: the Supreme Lord.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A few only, out of compassion for mankind, preserve that little “desireless desire” which brings them back to earth as avatars for the salvation of many. No avatar, however, in ultimate Reality, can be greater than any other.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>No avatar was ever created perfect. All of them were once like us, imperfect human beings who were finally washed clean in the realization of their own divinity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>God destroys evil-doers. God never destroys anyone! The only thing He destroys—the only thing He can destroy, since He cannot destroy Himself—is evil itself: never the evil-doer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Satchidananda: ever-existing, ever-conscious, ever-new Bliss.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>At the center of all movement, there is rest.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Though acting, I am without attachment; nor do I desire any particular outcome from (any) activity</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Digging a ditch—mere physical labor, in other words—can be either good, bad, or self-stultifying depending on one’s attitude while working.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The more whole-heartedly one can immerse himself in the feeling as well as the meaning of the ritual he performs, the more he will absorb divine inspiration into himself, until his very life becomes a ritual of self-offering, or yagya, to God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Watch yourself eating, walking, breathing, conversing, thinking. Stand mentally aside from your own body and mind. Become the silent observer of your own self. Gradually you will feel inwardly detached, and will accept that you are another reality altogether: the divine soul merely dreaming everything that happens to its individual-seeming consciousness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>incoming breath (prana) into the outgoing breath (apana),</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The slow, careful, conscious circulation of energy around the spine constitutes the ancient science known (since the time of Lahiri Mahasaya in the nineteenth century) as Kriya Yoga.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kriya Yoga, in order to be wholly effective, must be received not only intellectually (in written or spoken form), but vibrationally, in the form of initiation. A magnet is created either by electrical realignment of the molecules, or by close proximity to another magnet</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Spiritual mistakes can be costlier, in terms of long-range suffering.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>to take up Kriya Yoga signifies entering seriously onto the path to God. It is not a game, and should certainly be treated as a lifetime commitment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nevertheless, any yoga initiation, and especially into the ancient science of Kriya Yoga, should be looked upon as a very sacred step in one’s life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Truly, widespread literacy has had one unfortunate effect: the dissemination, not only of knowledge, but of ignorance! True understanding comes not by intellectual reasoning, but by intuition. Inner, intuitive attunement with the consciousness of the guru is what most surely and directly brings spiritual awakening.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ramanuja shouted the sacred mantra, “AUM namo Narayana!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>mahamantra (Haré Krishna, haré Krishna! Krishna, Krishna haré, haré! Haré Rama, haré Rama! Rama, Rama haré, haré!).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>From whatever direction one approaches a mountaintop, as long as he continues moving upward he will eventually reach the peak. What is all-important is the direction of one’s climb.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Paramhansa Yogananda encouraged people to add to the prayers they offer regularly to God and guru (and, perhaps, to a line of gurus) these words of invocation: “saints of all religions.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“God doesn’t mind your faults,” Yogananda used to say. “He only minds your indifference!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Karma can be national, communal, family, individual: anything that proceeds from a coherent center of intention, which attracts consequences back to that center. Karma is personal. A national leader who does evil on his people’s behalf, however, will not have to bear the entire weight of that bad karma on his own “shoulders”: The whole nation must accept the responsibility. Good people in that country must bear it also, though their own good karma may offset for themselves, and perhaps for a wider circle of people, any evil that must befall the nation as karmic retribution.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>purushakara and prarabdha. Purushakara karma is actions generated in this life under the influence, not of habit or desire, but of soul-guidance. Prarabdha karma, on the other hand, consists of present tendencies, and the results of past actions brought over from former lives.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>karma, which are being held in abeyance</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A powerful will can overcome, or can at least mitigate, virtually any misfortune that may await one. Bad karma can, for example, penetrate a weak aura, but be unable to penetrate a strong one.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>True, divine love is always expansive: from the little self to infinity. Its only motive is Bliss alone.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>free souls who live in this world often perform outward actions in order to set an example of right living for others. They do so because ordinary persons would find it all too easy, once they take up sannyas (the monastic path), to become mentally as well as physically inactive in the name of complete renunciation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To deprecate anyone is to affirm one’s own ego.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>please someone who may, in fact, be not at all enlightened is to shift the burden of responsibility to where it cannot ever belong: onto someone else’s shoulders.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our responsibility before God is our own. As Krishna says in the Gita, It is better to fail doing one’s own duty than to succeed doing the duty of another. Whatever may truly be one’s own duty (and it is no easy task to discern what that duty is), one cannot accomplish it by simply handing that decision over to someone else.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The yogi sees the body not as his body, but only as something he uses. He understands that his mind is not his own: It, too, is something he works through. He perceives the intellect as separate from his true, inner perception. And he cognizes the senses as cooperating with him, but independently from him. As the carpenter uses his hammer to drive nails into a board, so the yogi uses his very ego. He knows it is not his self, except in the sense that he, the infinite Self, must keep that little unit of reality going.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the yogi who is completely true to himself will never impose his will on other human beings.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“city of nine gates” is, of course, a reference to the body with its two eyes, two nostrils, two ears, two organs of excretion, and mouth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The greatest ‘sin’ is to call yourself a sinner.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“you must then act in such a way as not to commit that error again!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The best time for sowing the seeds of success,” Paramhansa Yogananda used to say, “is the season of failure!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The yogi should live mentally beyond time and space.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Everyone who is not you is simply your own deeper Self, manifested differently, in a different form, and even at different times. A sense of the oneness of all life helps the meditating yogi to approach God without fear or tension: to relax completely in divine love. Whatever happens in your life, you are one with the great ocean of Truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>True faith, it must be understood, is very different from blind belief.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>only way of showing his knowledge is by doing it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the physical act of breathing is intimately associated with—and is, indeed, caused by—the energy rising and descending in the spine through the ida and pingala nadis, or nerve channels. Ida begins on the left side; pingala, on the right. Breathing in the astral body takes place in these two nadis.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The ascending energy is called prana; the descending, apana.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kriya Yoga helps one (as we discussed earlier in this book) to equalize the incoming and outgoing breaths, and to absorb one’s energy in the spine, where one feels the currents as a cool (rising) and a slightly warm (descending) current.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The true renunciate and the true yogi are those who perform dutiful actions without desiring their fruits,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The fact that a person lives an ordinary life and has a normal job may make ego-renunciation more difficult, but it does not make it less obligatory.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The key to correct participation in “samsara,” then, is to “play one’s part” consciously non-identified with the ego.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Those who follow the renunciate path find it easier to direct all their energies to God. That very path, however, imposes also the broader responsibility of helping others spiritually: One should not live for himself alone.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Conditions are always neutral,” Yogananda said. “They only appear good or bad, joyful or sad, fortunate or unfortunate owing to the positive or negative attitudes [and expectations] of the mind.” The yogi must learn to gaze even-mindedly upon whatever happens to him.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When others treat you unkindly, unfairly, or even cruelly, make it a definite point never to react with emotion. Never strike back; never complain; never resist, out of ego-consciousness, either defensively or aggressively. Sometimes a wrong must be countered with a right, but even when duty calls you to such action, try always—as Krishna counseled Arjuna—to conduct yourself in such a way as to ensure that your own attitude is ever impersonal.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if they could spend some time—a week or two, or even longer—every year, and at least one day a week, in seclusion. Meditating for long hours, reading books that are spiritually uplifting, taking long walks “with God,” doing a little mental work such as writing in a spiritual diary: All these activities can provide a spiritually strengthening balance to constant outward activity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Yogananda mentioned also, in passing, another, symbolic reason for the above advice Krishna gave. The earth-grown grass, the animal skin, and the silken cloth symbolize the lower three chakras, above which the yogi’s energy should rise.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is best (but more difficult because of visual distractions) to meditate with open eyes, the gaze (as we’ve seen) slightly upward, and the lower eyelids slightly raised. Thus, closed eyes are naturally associated with sleep; wide open eyes, with wakefulness; and slightly raised, finally, with the lower lids in a “half open and half closed” position, is associated with superconsciousness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Those, in other words, who are unable to practice complete sexual abstinence are not debarred from the yoga path.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>O Arjuna! Yoga is not for him who eats too much or who fasts too much, who sleeps too much or who sleeps too little. (6:17) One who is temperate in eating, recreation, working, sleeping, and wakefulness attains yoga, which destroys all suffering.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Moderation means doing everything you can to advance spiritually, without pushing yourself too far.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The inmates, under obligation to follow a routine too monotonously regular, tend to become dull-minded. With too many rules, moreover, they tend to become excessively rigid, and lose any hint of the spontaneous creativity that is so essential for spirits who seek self-expansion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What really traps people in delusion is the thought, “I like this!”—or, “I dislike that!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Patanjali gave his definition of yoga as, “Yogas chitta vritti nirodha: Yoga is the neutralization of the eddies (whirlpools, great and small) of feeling.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The moon’s reflection on a lake is distorted by ripples in the water. Such are the ripples of feeling, which often grow and become waves of agitation, distorting the clarity of human perception. To calm the mind that it reflect the truth as it is, one must calm the waves of reaction in the heart.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a glass of water into which dirt particles have been stirred. One cannot command the water to become clear, but if one allows the glass to sit for awhile the impurities gradually settle to the bottom, or else rise to the surface of their own accord, to be skimmed off.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>them in their suffering, need only apply</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Yoga practice (yoga abhyasa) implies working both outwardly and inwardly, making repeated efforts to return to one’s calm center within. Dispassion (vairagya) means disengaging the mind (again, by repeated efforts) from all forms of sensory pleasure, subtle as well as gross.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nishkam karma—action without desire for the fruits of action—should be his motto all the way to and beyond the door of death.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Act as you should for the present, and leave the results in God’s hands.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>On should live more wholeheartedly right now, enjoying his yoga practices, thinking of this moment, not of the future, but simply loving God in the present and offering oneself up to the Lord without any expectation of reward. You should remind yourself, indeed, that there is no you to be rewarded! The chief reason people get discouraged is their expectation of specific results. Learn to expect nothing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>meditation advices these two pages</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>more important than chanting AUM is it to listen to AUM in the right ear in meditation. Closing the tragi of the ears with the thumbs (the elbows resting lightly on a crosspiece of wood), AUM is chanted mentally at the point between the eyebrows while the mind concentrates on the sounds appearing (as has been stated) in the right ear. One should concentrate on only one sound at a time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Habits,” Yogananda used to say, “can be changed in a day. They are simply the result of concentrated energy. Direct that energy in a new way, and the habit you want to overcome can be instantly dispelled.” The breath, when accompanied by strong mental affirmation, is the best medium for bringing into one’s nature the thoughts and qualities one wants, and for ridding oneself of those which one wants to dismiss. In this case, too, each exhaling breath can be a little death (of the discarded quality, anyway), and each inhalation can be a little rebirth into some new quality one desires to adopt.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Hold up a piece of paper in your hand. Will it shake on its own? Never! To shake it, you yourself must do the shaking.” The mind is influenced by physical awareness, but its response, always, comes from the awareness itself. Carnal desires originate not in the body, even though they obviously are influenced by the body. The origin of temptation, however, is in the mind. Nothing inert can influence the mind without the mind’s willing cooperation, whether consciously or subconsciously.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>disciplining the body is an indirect and incomplete way of freeing the mind from body-consciousness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Krishna emphasizes faith not as blind belief, but as the certainty born of complete intuitive understanding and acceptance. He emphasizes love because, without devotional love, the seeker cannot (as Swami Sri Yukteswar put it) set one foot before the other on the path to God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>[The master] was reminding me to love God more than meditation. ‘Do not mistake the technique for the Goal.’”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Earth, water, fire, air, ether, the perceiving mind (manas), discernment (buddhi), and causative self-awareness (ahankara): such are the Eightfold divisions of My manifested nature (Prakriti).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“ether,” or space, which Paramhansa Yogananda declared to be a distinct vibration, separating the astral from the physical universe.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nature (Prakriti) contains other “divisions”: mind (manas), which perceives all; intuitive intelligence (buddhi), which comprehends all; and the ego principle (ahankara) on a cosmic scale, which is the one Self in all outward manifestation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kutastha at the point between the eyebrows. This is still the ego, which even the enlightened man needs in order to keep his body functioning. The divine Self, as differentiated from the enlightened ego, has its center in the heart.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kundalini passes upward in reverse order from that of its descent. First it passes through, and awakens, the energy in muladhara, the coccyx (or “earth”) center. Next, it awakens the energy in swadisthana, the sacral (or “water”) center. Third, it enters and awakens the energy in manipura, the lumbar (or “fire”) center. The fourth center it awakens is anahata, the dorsal or heart center (“air”); then bishuddha, the cervical (“ether”) center.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Divine Mother: Paraprakriti, the pure aspect of the Cosmic Vibration.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Such is My lower nature (Aparaprakriti). Understand now, O Mighty-armed (Arjuna)! that My other and higher nature (Paraprakriti) sustains the soul (jiva), which is individual consciousness, and sustains also the life-principle of the universe.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The astral world contains both angels (devas) and demons (asuras). They are attracted to their own kind among human beings.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Thoughts,” Yogananda wrote in Autobiography of a Yogi, “are universally and not individually rooted.” Inspirations are not created: they must be invited.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>God also, Yogananda said, weeps for mankind: for man’s follies and sufferings. He weeps also for human wickedness, for though it produces grief for its recipients, it produces even more grief, in time, for the wicked themselves. Yet the Lord allows His show to go on. He created it without any sense of personal involvement. The drama of every individual’s life must work its slow way, by however winding a road, to its eventual, indeed inevitable, conclusion: reabsorption in the bliss of Satchidananda</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Time is an illusion. Once one awakens from it, it seems as though no time had passed at all!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Those, finally, who seek perfection in wisdom, spurning all other “attractions,” offer themselves up wholly to God. Such devotees are, among all the virtuous, the most pleasing to</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>seek perfection in wisdom, spurning all other “attractions,” offer themselves up wholly to God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Best it is, then, to pray to God for everything, always adding, “Fulfill this prayer, Lord, only if it is in keeping with Your will.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>even in prayer, he practices nishkam karma: non-attachment to the fruits.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>time is not an essential factor in self-upliftment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Habits can be changed in a day. They are the result of mental concentration. If one has been concentrating one way, he can simply concentrate a new way.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Never admit to yourself that you haven’t the power to overcome any defect. The more your mind resists a bad habit instead of embracing it gleefully, the more you will build up the inner strength eventually to overcome it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Await your opportunities calmly and dispassionately.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The important thing is not to concern oneself with theological niceties (think how many religious pedants waste time and effort in that preoccupation!), but to offer one’s energy upward, past the ego to a higher source.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is the story of a saint in India who lived long ago.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>God is all of these, but is so much more besides that He cannot, in His true essence, be either named or imagined.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What Krishna means in this sloka is not that it is erroneous to worship God with name and form, but only that it is wrong to try to confine God in doing so.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What Krishna means in this sloka is not that it is erroneous to worship God with name and form, but only that it is wrong to try to confine God in doing so. God is everything—and He is nothing: that is to say, no specific thing. He is both in and beyond everything, and, in truth, is not even the “things” He has manifested, since they are but dreams, “real” only as dreams are real.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Egoic will, which we have called whimsical, is in fact imposed upon man by his own past karma. It is whimsical only in the sense that, though an act may seem deliberate, in fact man is normally guided by his own past actions, and by the tendencies he built up in consequence of them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The will is free only when it is guided by superconscious inspiration. Even then, that inspiration must be filtered down through the mind’s prior conditioning: a poet, for example, will receive influence from the superconscious in the form of words, whereas a composer, under perhaps the same inspiration, will express it in melody, rhythm, and harmony.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Bhagavad Gita, amazingly, never wastes a word.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>He perceives God in all His eight aspects: Light, Sound, Peace, Calmness, Power, Wisdom, Love, and (above all) Bliss. (Peace and Calmness differ from one another only in that Peace is the soothing cessation of all agitation of feeling, whereas Calmness is dynamic, and is the silent, essential core of creativity, of impersonal love, and of divine wisdom.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Jyoti Mudra, the purpose of which is not only to see but to pass his life force and consciousness through the spiritual eye into infinity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>always bear in mind the goal (God) even while traveling the path.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Never go to bed at night before experiencing at least some aspect of the divine presence within—peace, love, upliftment of consciousness, or joy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>one moon gives more light than all the stars. One Self-realized soul accomplishes more by his simple presence in this world than all the “stars” of busy (but mostly either inept or frustrated) world changers.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Seize the day!” is an expression: this Day of Brahma; this yuga of Earth time; this season; this day; this very moment! Spiritual progress comes not with the passing of years, but with every moment of sincere effort. “The minutes,” Yogananda said, “are more important than the years.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>every step of the way is more rewarding, more joyful, and more utterly satisfying!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the raising of the Kundalini force must be accompanied by conscious purification of the heart’s feelings. The most important part of its awakening depends, indeed, on kindness, generosity, truthfulness, and all the basic virtues—recognized as such in every true religion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>yellow for muladhara; white for swadisthana; red for manipura; blue for anahata; smoke colored with little specks of light for bishuddha; and, in the spiritual eye (as has already been described), a ring of gold surrounding a field of deep blue-violet, with a silvery-white five-pointed star at the center.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is tempting to compare the colors of these six chakras, along with the seventh in the so-called crown chakra at the top of the head, with the colors of the rainbow. The rainbow is certainly comparable with the seven chakras, especially with their gradual change in hue from materialistic red to spiritual violet (red, orange, yellow, green, blue, indigo, and violet). This comparison must be written off, however, as more poetical than literal.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>one has to become aware of a limitation before he can transcend it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Indifference is the greatest spiritual disease.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Images—swirling, haunting, dream-like—come and go, changeless forever yet forever changing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We imagine that we, like little icebergs, are substantially different from Him,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Who made God?” is another question commonly asked. Yogananda’s reply was, “You ask this question because you are living in the realm of causation. God, however, is the Supreme Cause. He is self-existent.” To assume that a thing has been caused is, necessarily, to accept that it will, in time, be “uncaused”—that is to say, destroyed. God is neither living nor non-living: He simply is—without a cause, without a reason, beyond all inference or disproof, beyond either acceptance or rejection. Wise are they who, contemplating Him, simply marvel in silence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Hinduism itself was a name given only centuries later to the religion of India. The indigenous name, as we stated earlier, was Sanaatan Dharma: the “Eternal Religion.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Even stagnation is a kind of movement, implying as it does a kind of inward deterioration.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Those who worship the gods go to them; those who worship their ancestors go to the abode of ancestors; those who worship the nature spirits go to them; but those who are My devotees come to Me.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first snow that falls on the ground in wintertime does not immediately whiten the earth. Gradually the snowflakes cool the ground until it is cold enough to accept them. Whiteness then becomes visible, as if suddenly, everywhere.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Start wherever you are now on the way to the Infinite. The smallest step you take will bring you closer,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Garuda (“lord of the skies”; in classical symbology, the vehicle of Vishnu).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>No art is needed to feel inspiration, but to express that inspiration requires self-discipline and focused energy. These come only as a result of serious training and much effort. The true artist is never one who, feeling uplifted by what he sees, makes wild brush marks on his canvas that can have meaning for no one but himself</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Perseverance in pursuing Self-knowledge, and (sincere) aspiration to (experience) it through meditation, is better than the possession of theoretical knowledge. Offering up to Me the fruits of action, moreover, is better than one-sided but restless meditation. Action, coupled with renunciation of the fruits of action, brings inner peace, which makes it possible to meditate deeply.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>he gives energy, rather than waiting to receive it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>bodies: physical, astral, and causal, the first two of which are subject to birth and death—may be described even on the physical level as only ideas of the soul. All three bodies are unreal in eternity, and endure only as long as the idea of them is kept alive by desires. That idea is fueled in the astral and physical bodies by the concept of individuality. Ego-consciousness is, indeed, an “element” of the astral body.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“To know something is, in fact, to differentiate three distinct things: the knower, the thing known, and the act of knowing.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I’m not what I do. I’m a young man with many interests, including that of visiting this saint—though I do so for reasons I don’t fully understand.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>am that something within that remains unchanged—that simply observes change.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I am that something within that remains unchanged—that simply observes change.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>he, himself, was a point of inner perception from which he merely observed these changes, but didn’t define himself in terms of any of them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I am that something within that remains unchanged—that simply observes change. Thus, he came to identify himself more and more with his soul.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Knowledge is the possession of a mere catalogue of facts: Wisdom is the understanding of how to use facts in the quest for enlightenment in the Self.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whenever possible, he should seek seclusion—for one or two weeks a year, or for longer periods—to immerse himself in the thought of God. He should not dislike worldly company, since to dislike anything is to create a disturbance in his chitta, or feeling. He may not always find it convenient to avoid such society, but he should be conscious of, and accept as the right attitude for a devotee, an inner disinclination for it. Thus, if he must sometimes attend worldly gatherings, he should relate to people from a firm center of calmness within himself.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>in this world of duality, all victories are transient, and are necessarily balanced by defeats (owing to the universal sway of duality). Individual seekers of truth must, one by one, dive beneath the agitation caused by the storm at the surface, and find peace in the depths. Liberation is achieved singly, not by group effort. Though groups can at least provide a supportive environment for the individual aspirant, the exercise of conscience must be done personally—and often solitarily: It is ever a matter between the individual and his Maker.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the one who experiences (but doesn’t react with feelings of either pleasure or pain),</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>some seekers follow the path of meditation, some that of knowledge, and some the path of selfless activity (service). Described here briefly are the three main approaches to God (which is to say, to Self-realization).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>some seekers follow the path of meditation, some that of knowledge, and some the path of selfless activity (service).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A true guru’s teaching is, above all, by a transferral of consciousness. His main “job” is to uplift the disciple by his spiritual magnetism. The disciple’s role is to listen, not to argue.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The spiritual path is twenty-five percent the disciple’s effort; twenty-five percent the guru’s effort on his behalf; and fifty percent the grace of God.” Because the guru is a channel for God Himself, it may even be said without error that God, both in and through the guru, accounts for seventy-five percent of the disciple’s spiritual journey.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Is it important to be physically near the guru? Not necessarily. Mental attunement is everything. My Guru told me that even one physical contact with the guru may suffice to seal that bond. There must, however—so he told me—be at least that one contact. It can occur through the mediation of an advanced disciple. Those, however, who think to form it only by mental acceptance on their part do not achieve the same results.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“In the midst of death, life persists.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Don’t think you can love God purely and entirely if you are able to treat even one human being unkindly. The one Lord is equally present in all. To mistreat or even to feel ill will toward any of His creatures is, at least to that extent, to separate yourself from God.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Many spiritually inclined people feel fulfillment in the vicarious knowledge they get from reading and discussing spiritual truths. Intellectual knowledge, however, does not touch a person inwardly. It is not based on direct experience, but only on the thoughts, opinions, and experiences of others.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If one learns, by such action, to see and appreciate that others, too, have their needs, then even selfish activity can lead upward, toward a freer consciousness. But if one determinedly excludes the needs of others from one’s own struggle for self-fulfillment, his consciousness will shrink inward upon itself, and his energy will move downward in the spine into the lower chakras.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A seed cannot suddenly become a tree. Every human being needs to grow from that stage which he has reached so far. Instead of expecting overnight perfection on the spiritual path, one must work realistically with the tools he has to hand. The seed will grow if it is watered regularly. That watering process, for a devotee, is daily meditation and constant practice of the presence of God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The veil cast by maya, however, is heavy. Even masters must make a conscious effort to cast off its last lingering traces in their consciousness. When death comes to you, therefore, make a serious effort to sever the cords of attachment that bind you to this life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>jivan muktas—freed, that is to say, while still living in the body—even if their freedom comes only at the moment of death.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The less you allow your ego to identify itself with any quality, the more you’ll be able to pick and choose the qualities you’d like to manifest, and will thus learn to act appropriately under all circumstances.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Otherwise, if you become satisfied with yourself, you’ll only fall—once more!—because you’ll have reaffirmed your ego.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>have the faith required to follow him implicitly. True faith in the guru is not passive, nor is it an indication of ignorance. Disciples blessed with that faith soon emerge from the confines of ego into the spotless skies of divine consciousness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a true guru makes every effort to ensure that his disciple’s obedience will be both deliberate (free-willed) and intelligent, and will not be a matter of blind or merely submissive acquiescence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The soul, as has been explained before, is encased in three such bodies, the subtlest, or causal, being the innermost, the one enclosing that (the astral body) coming next, and the outermost sheath being the physical.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There cannot be consciousness without feeling. Indeed, feeling is consciousness. Spiritual progress depends on refining the receptivity of feeling. This is possible only when the intuition is calm and, therefore, pure.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Accept nothing that doesn’t appeal to your highest sense of what is right and true. Even then, be guided by the supportive opinions of the wise. When wise persons in general agree on the spiritual authenticity of a document, then only—so wisdom dictates—may the document be safely accepted as true scripture.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Once one has removed his ego’s natural impulse to wrest what it wants from life, he achieves his goals effortlessly, often with willing help from others.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Only when we face reality as it is can we begin to change it to what it should be.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>action without personal desire for the fruits of action.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When others are agitated (and you might be, too), tell yourself, “Things will be normal again in a few hours, or days, or another week—or another month—or another year.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When others are agitated (and you might be, too), tell yourself, “Things will be normal again in a few hours, or days, or another week—or another month—or another year.” However long the period, it will end.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>accepting whatever is as, simply, what it is.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>For much that passes for success in worldly eyes is not really even good karma, and may actually result in a person’s eventual spiritual downfall and long-range misery.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One is the fact that success comes as a result of focused concentration.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“As long as you make the effort, God will never let you down.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Arjuna, know this for a certainty: My devotee is never lost.” One further thought remains, both to stiffen one’s resolution and to brighten one’s hope: Once the desire for God awakens in the heart, that desire must be fulfilled. It is already his guarantee of salvation</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The very fact that desires can lead to anger should be a sufficient indication that the desires themselves are manifestations of bondage, not of freedom.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>fight dispassionately, without attachment to the results. This is the secret of true ahimsa, non-violence (harmlessness). Sometimes one must destroy in order to honor his higher duty. He need not, however, wish destruction on anything or anyone.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the effect of prayer depends not on any prayer-formula, however valid in itself, but on the attitude of the person praying.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Each one’s faith depends upon his nature. As a man is, so is his faith. As his faith is, so is the man.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are, in other words, what we believe.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the vibrations of what one eats. For this reason also, it is important that food be prepared in an uplifted frame of mind, and not under the influence of such harmful emotions as anger, grief, deep worry, or depression.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Because the food one eats has an effect on mental clarity and upliftment, it plays an important role not only in one’s bodily health but also in one’s spiritual life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This threefold austerity (of body, speech, and mind) is sattwic in nature; it is practiced by persevering seekers (blessed with) deep devotion, who desire not the fruits of their actions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My Guru used to say that to give food or money to someone in need is good; to give him a job is better; and to help him to become qualified to get a good job is best of all.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>On a mental plane, to give good advice inappropriately, to someone who is not likely to benefit from it, would be a mistake also. Give counsel charily, when it is clearly wanted and requested, and never impose it on anybody: This is sattwic counseling.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sat stands for eternal and absolute truth: the Supreme Spirit, above and beyond all vibration.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>on continued effort until there is no sense of doing, doer, and done because one is merged in the Infinite</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Krishna means also that one should abandon as early as possible the absurd tendency of the doubting mind</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The wise understand renunciation to be the relinquishing of any action performed with (personal) desire. They also declare that it is not action itself which should be abandoned, but only that action which desires the fruits of action.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Tantra is an approach to God that teaches one to be strong in himself in the very teeth of temptation. It is a “back staircase” to God, and spiritually very dangerous.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The activity involved in yagya (sacrifice), philanthropic works, and the austerities (listed in 17:14–16) ought certainly to be engaged in, and should not be abandoned, for, when performed with wisdom, (they) purify the heart. (18:6) Even these (self-uplifting) activities, however, ought to be performed without attachment (either) to them or to their fruits.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One who gives up a duty because he finds it difficult, or because he fears it will cause him pain, relinquishes that action with rajasic consciousness (motivated by desire and attachment).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>(A true disciple of a true guru will never pit one of those against the other.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One who is wise in his renunciation is ever calm in himself, and is never doubtful. He has no aversion to unpleasant actions, nor is he attached to pleasant ones.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>who thinks of his ego as the sole doer of everything accomplished by him shows no understanding at all.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is no such thing as death, but only transition.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In divine consciousness, knowing, knower, and known are one and the same. The person is, in fact, the thing known: he is not only the knower. Thus, for example, learning, for him, is no longer difficult, since he already is that knowledge! He is also the act of knowing, which means that, in learning, he doesn’t really absorb anything new.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sattwic action is motivated by superconscious inspiration. It is performed without attachment, without likes or dislikes, and without desire for any fruits accruing from</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sattwic courage, on the other hand, is based on perfect knowledge, and on acceptance of the possible consequences.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Krishna has said there may, occasionally, be a right motivation for fear: when the action one contemplates might put one in karmic error.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>body and senses controlled by pranayama.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“When we lift up one hand to God, He reaches two down to help us.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Even saints manifest tamoguna (tamas), although, relatively speaking, to a very mild degree. They manifest it in the fact that they sleep, or take rest. Even tamasic or very evil people, moreover, show the sattwic quality to a mild degree when they do anything good for anyone.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>sense control (by the practice of pranayama),</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>mind control (concentration), sense control (by the practice of pranayama), self-restraint, purity, forgiveness, integrity, wisdom, meditation to attain Self-realization, and faith in a higher truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The duty of a Vaishya is to include the benefit of others in his own activities. Thus, he will become more sensitive to the needs of others, and will develop, in time, the nature of a Kshatriya.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A true Kshatriya stands up for what he believes, but his rectitude will be appropriate.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If a duty conflicts with a higher duty, it ceases to be a duty.” In other words, if there are several things one can do well, he should concentrate on that activity which will most expand his sympathies and uplift his consciousness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every human being must follow his own star. The higher one rises toward inner freedom, the more imperative becomes this advice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>one should not abandon the work dictated by his own nature, even though (the work) contain some imperfection, for all undertakings (even the best) are marred by blemishes, even as a flame is (obscured) by smoke.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That person comes closest to attaining perfection who keeps his intellect non-attached to everything outside the Self, who reigns in victory over the Self, and from whom (all) desires have fled.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To know one’s Self is to know God! To know one’s Self is to know everything!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>abiding in a solitary place, eating lightly, controlling the body, speech, and mind; absorbing oneself in divine yoga meditation; dispassionate</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>creating a “place of seclusion” in one’s own home. Set aside one room, or even a screened-off portion of your bedroom, where the only activity allowed is meditation. Superconscious vibrations will develop there, and will effectively “screen out” the surrounding, worldly atmosphere.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Now then, do as you feel.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The cosmic drama needs suspense, excitement, at times terror, and at other times thrilling beauty. Man needs to feel that the ending to it all is highly uncertain, and may, for him, prove disastrous. Only thus will his interest throughout keep him “on the edge of his seat.” Every soul’s journey is unique. It is filled with uncertainties, with sorrow mingled with joy, with hope mingled with despair, with triumph mingled with crushing defeat, with dark doubt as to whether life has any meaning at all followed by the discovery of human love, of success, of history-making knowledge, of undreamed-of power, of joyful laughter followed by heart-wrenching tears. If man could know, through this long journey, that God’s love was always with him—deeply, eternally, unconditionally—he might well preen himself on that “good fortune,” grow cocky, and never learn the attitudes absolutely necessary for entering into, and becoming one with, that love.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Never share these truths with one who is without self-control or devotion, nor with one who won’t share with others in a spirit of service, nor give them to one who is indifferent to them, or who finds fault with Me.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>never try to impose even good ideas on anyone, even if you are sure of those truths in yourself. People need to ask, first. They must seek understanding. To try to force even wisdom on them would be an offense against their eternal birthright of free will.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Tribes, We Need You to Lead Us</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-10-21-tribes.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-10-21-tribes.html</id>
    <published>2017-10-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#tribes-we-need-you-to-lead-us-godin-seth">Tribes: We Need You to Lead Us (Godin, Seth)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1347711639l/3828382.jpg" />

</div>
<h3 id="tribes-we-need-you-to-lead-us-godin-seth">Tribes: We Need You to Lead Us (Godin, Seth)</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Generous and authentic leadership will always defeat the selfish efforts of someone doing it just because she can.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Leadership, on the other hand, is about creating change that you believe in.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Marketing used to be about advertising, and advertising is expensive. Today, marketing is about engaging with the tribe and delivering products and services with stories that spread.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>New rule: If you want to grow, you need to find customers who are willing to join you or believe in you or donate to you or support you. And guess what? The only customers willing to do that are looking for something new. The growth comes from change and light and noise.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One man with no authority suddenly becomes a key figure. Tribes give each of us the very same opportunity. Skill and attitude are essential. Authority is not. In fact, authority can get in the way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The movement happens when people talk to one another, when ideas spread within the community, and most of all, when peer support leads people to do what they always knew was the right thing. Great leaders create movements by empowering the tribe to communicate. They establish the foundation for people to make connections, as opposed to commanding people to follow them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>viral activity, or a virtuous cycle. The better you do, the better you do. Connections lead to connections. Great ideas spread.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Just a few can change everything. What they</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Fans, true fans, are hard to find and precious. Just a few can change everything. What they demand, though, is generosity and bravery.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Organizations that destroy the status quo win.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whatever the status quo is, changing it gives you the opportunity to be remarkable</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the levers are here. The proof is here. The power is here. The only thing holding you back is your own fear. Not easy to admit, but essential to understand.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When you are leading a tribe, a tribe that you belong to, the benefits increase, the work gets easier, and the results are more obvious. That’s the best reason to overcome the fear.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I realize what a badge of honor it is to get a bit of criticism at all. It means that I confounded expectations—that I didn’t deliver the sequel or the simple, practical guide that some expected. It means that, in fact, I did something worth remarking</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>They’re generous. They exist to help the tribe find something, to enable the tribe to thrive. But they understand that the most powerful way to enable is to be statueworthy: by getting out front, by making a point, by challenging convention, and by speaking up. Those are brave acts, and bravery begets statues.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When you identify the discomfort, you’ve found the place where a leader is needed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Leaning in or backing off, but not doing nothing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>trying to lead everyone results in leading no one in particular. This leads to an interesting thought: you get to choose the tribe you will lead.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Almost all the growth that’s available to you exists when you aren’t like most people and when you work hard to appeal to folks who aren’t most people.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Change isn’t made by asking permission. Change is made by asking forgiveness, later.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is merely about developing the faith that it’ll work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Merely,” of course, is a huge step. It’s nothing but a few neurons’ worth of faith, just the knowledge that you can do it. But without faith, the leap never works.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When you fall in love with the system, you lose the ability to grow.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Training a student to be a sheep is a lot easier than the alternative. Teaching to the test, ensuring compliant behavior, and using fear as a motivator are the easiest and fastest ways to get a kid through school. So why does it surprise us that we graduate so many sheep?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Isn’t it sad that we have a job where we spend two weeks avoiding the stuff we have to do fifty weeks a year?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Life’s too short” is repeated often enough to be a cliché, but this time it’s true. You don’t have enough time to be both unhappy and mediocre. It’s not just pointless, it’s painful. Instead of wondering when your next vacation is, maybe you ought to set up a life you don’t need to escape from.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>micromovement consist of five things to do and six principles:</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>insights per polymath movement</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The secret of being wrong isn’t to avoid being wrong! The secret is being willing to be wrong. The secret is realizing that wrong isn’t fatal. The only thing that makes people and organizations great is their willingness to be not great along the way. The desire to fail on the way to reaching a bigger goal is the untold secret of success. I’ve been waiting for you to ask for the shortcut, the error-free, failure-free way to get people to do what you want, to make change happen without risk or fear, to magically alter the status quo. That, after all, is the best way to sell you on the ideas here. If I could just give you the answer, you’d be leading a tribe right now. The honest answer is: There isn’t an easy way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The secret of leadership is simple: Do what you believe in. Paint a picture of the future. Go there. People will follow.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>to switch sides is to admit that we made a mistake.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>they get when they’re part of a vibrant, growing tribe, but who are still looking for that feeling.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Because, of course, it has nothing to do with knowing how the trick is done, and everything to do with the art of doing it. The tactics of leadership are easy. The art is the difficult part.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Your tribe communicates. They probably don’t do it the way you would; they don’t do it as efficiently as you might like, but they communicate. The challenge for the leader is to help your tribe sing, whatever form that song takes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The idea wasn’t the point. Organizing the tribe was.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The secret, Reagan’s secret, is to listen, to value what you hear, and then to make a decision even if it contradicts the very people you are listening to. Reagan impressed his advisers, his adversaries, and his voters by actively listening. People want to be sure you heard what they said—they’re less focused on whether or not you do what they said.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Tribes grow when people recruit other people. That’s how ideas spread as well. The tribe doesn’t do it for you, of course. They do it for each other. Leadership is the art of giving people a platform for spreading ideas that work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s a myth that change happens overnight, that right answers succeed in the marketplace right away, or that big ideas happen in a flash. They don’t. It’s always (almost always, anyway) a matter of accretion. Drip, drip, drip. Improvements happen a bit at a time, not as grand-slam home runs that are easy to get.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Part of leadership (a big part of it, actually) is the ability to stick with the dream for a long time. Long enough that the critics realize that you’re going to get there one way or another . . . so they follow.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There’s no record of Martin Luther King, Jr., or Gandhi whining about credit. Credit isn’t the point. Change is.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Once you choose to lead, you’ll be under huge pressure to reconsider your choice, to compromise, to dumb it down, or to give up. Of course you will. That’s the world’s job: to get you to be quiet and follow. The status quo is the status quo for a reason. But once you choose to lead, you’ll also discover that it’s not so difficult. That the options available to you seem really clear, and that yes, in fact, you can get from here to there.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Your Move, The Underdog’s Guide to Building Your Business</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-09-06-your-move.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-09-06-your-move.html</id>
    <published>2017-09-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-09-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#your-move-the-underdogs-guide-to-building-your-business-sethi-ramit">Your Move: The Underdog’s Guide to Building Your Business (Sethi, Ramit)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1495487317l/35202699._SY475_.jpg" />

</div>
<h3 id="your-move-the-underdogs-guide-to-building-your-business-sethi-ramit">Your Move: The Underdog’s Guide to Building Your Business (Sethi, Ramit)</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>if you create value for others, they’ll happily pay for it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There are a million different ways to approach any topic. The key is: Instead of focusing on the competition, focus on your audience. Who is your audience, and what do they want that they are not being served right now?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Be different to be better. Don’t be different for the sake of being different</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you are solving a problem that’s important to people, AND if you have the credibility so that they believe you can solve it, then price becomes a mere triviality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To sell, you need to know four key things about your customers: their hopes, dreams, pain points, and fears.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you can’t think of anyone to talk to, look for Facebook groups that match your target audience. Then reach out to people in those groups to ask about chatting with them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s the psychology that separates the winners from everyone else.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Thank you for dressing up in a suit and thank you for being professional.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I’m polite but firm. I’m communicating my value. That’s professionalism</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>that first meeting is as little about me as possible. I want to learn from them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Instead, it’s about showing what you can offer them, not asking for anything, and building a relationship.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>attracting a mentor.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I thought I couldn’t go on, and I was getting ready to quit, but instead of letting me quit or even coast, my coach pushed me to do even more.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It made me think about how easy it is to quit — and how rare it is to find someone who’ll push you harder than you even thought was possible.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You’re capable of 20 times what you think you are.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Everything is figure-out-able.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>With each step, your confidence builds, slowly creating powerful, unshakable confidence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“failing forward,” because each failure propels your business another step ahead, until it’s inevitable that you become successful.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I strongly recommend you set a tiny, realistic goal for the day. When you achieve it, then move on to the next tiny, realistic goal. Your business is going to see better results from taking action on small goals then dreaming about unrealistic big goals that you never achieve.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>nobody cares what you did. They only care what you’re doing.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Then we look at the other entrepreneurs around us and use them for support. We ask for help. We ask excellent questions. And together, we all grow.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All he cares about is the solution that you can offer him.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Sleep</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-08-16-sleep.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-08-16-sleep.html</id>
    <published>2017-08-16T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-08-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#sleep">Sleep</a><ul>
<li><a href="#pre-sleep-routine">Pre Sleep Routine</a></li>
<li><a href="#post-sleep-routine">Post Sleep Routine</a></li>
<li><a href="#nap">NAP</a></li>
<li><a href="#quotes">Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="sleep">Sleep</h1>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1471745675l/31566948.jpg" />

</div>
<ul>
<li>It is better to think about quality rather than quantity when dealing with sleep. Quality can be determined not only when your are asleep, your routine while you are awake is important too.</li>
<li>Try to improve one step at a time. Little progresses make big differences.</li>
<li>Our biological clocks are regulated by external stimuli such as:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>sunlight</li>
<li>temperature</li>
<li>meal time</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Circadian rhythms work also without external stimuli</li>
<li>Homeostatic pressure determine our need to sleep. This need start when we wake up and keep increase while we are awake.</li>
<li>During night we attain the more efficient sleeping time near 2-3am (twelve hours later there is a compensation time span, it is really common for most of us to feel drowsy.</li>
<li>Light stimulate seratonin production, a neurotransmitter that increase well being and which melatonin is a derivative.</li>
<li>Blue light, dring the day as beneficial effects such as increase performance and reflexes. It is also reduce melatonin levels. It is a bad habit use blue light during the night as you might expect. Professor Idzikowsky define consequences of that bad habit (blue light from monitors before going to sleep) “junk sleep”. It is self explanatory.</li>
<li><p>In literature exist <code>3</code> chronotypes:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>He who go to sleep and get up early (<strong>AM</strong>)</li>
<li>He who go to sleep and get up late (<strong>PM</strong>)</li>
<li>He who stay between <strong>1</strong> and <strong>2</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>Check out the online quiz and <a href="https://www.bioinfo.mpg.de/mctq/core_work_life/core/introduction.jsp">find what is your chronotype</a> (thanks to University of Monaco).</p></li>
<li>Melatonina is a hormone that is produced by the pineal gland. It regulate your need to go to sleep.</li>
<li>Caffeine is a central nervous system stimulant. It is the world’s most widely consumed psychoactive drug. Unlike many other psychoactive substances, it is legal and unregulated in nearly all parts of the world. It reversibly blocks the action of adenosine on its receptor and consequently prevents the onset of drowsiness induced by adenosine. Caffeine also stimulates certain portions of the autonomic nervous system. Optimal dose for athletes is <code>3-6</code> milligrams per kilograms of body mass. It is a half-life that can be arrive up to six hours. <em>Use caffeine as a power boost, not as a substance that you need in order to do the minimum.</em></li>
<li>Stop waking up late during the weekend, try to keep your morning routine as much as possible.</li>
<li>Is is proven that <code>90</code> minutes is the range needed to pass through each sleep phases. The more important are:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><strong>light sleep</strong>: in which information are consolidated and motor skills performance increase.</li>
<li><p><strong>deep sleep</strong>: brain produce delta wave, the least frequency wave emitted (where we are awake brain produce beta waves that have an higher frequency). More deep sleep the better. We have the most beneficial effects and one of them is the production of growth hormone.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>born new cells, fix tissue and leave a feeling of renewal.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><strong>REM (Rapid Eye Movement)</strong>: dreaming phase, here the mind trick us with dreams while the body is paralyzed. Studies report that <strong>REM sleep increase creativity</strong>.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>It is not possible to get back lost sleep. Try to go to bed early or sleep for too long is time wasted. Our body is able to adapt, if you want to recover something, focus on keep your routine without too much worrying.</li>
<li>Keep a fix time to wake up is the best method we have to increase our sleeping quality.</li>
<li>Focus on <strong>cycles</strong> per night. A cycle is <strong>90 minutes of sleep</strong>.</li>
<li>Try to find out how many cycles are best suite for us. If for example we have seen that we need <code>5</code> cycles per night, we must try to not have three consecutive nights with less cycles. It is really important to find out <strong>How many cycles we need to feel restful and increase our daily routine performance</strong>. We must be ready to feel our body and mind responses while change cycles per night. Try at least for a week before switch.</li>
<li>Do not think that sleep can only be done only monophasically. In a time window of 24 hours there are other opportunities to compensate a poor night sleep.</li>
<li>Our biggest problem is psychological. Common bias that we need <code>8</code> hours of sleep per night is a real beast. It is difficult now think that <code>4.30</code> is enough.</li>
<li>When we get older, our sleep habit shift one bit at a time from a monophasic to a polyphasic sleep.</li>
<li>Sleep on your side is the recommended position. Better if your slave side, because is the side least used so less sensible. In addition, the dominant side can be think as “the reactive” side that can help you defense against attacks while sleeping (in order to sleep well we need to feel secure).</li>
<li>Try to use your bedroom only for sleeping activities.</li>
<li>“<em>Mouth breathing increase the number of sleep apnoea as well as probability to snore.</em>” - Patrick McKeown <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26533127-the-oxygen-advantage">The Oxygen Advantage</a></li>
<li>You can find if you have a good mattress if while you are on your side, the distance between the mattress and your head is less than two fist.</li>
<li>Double bed, as the word say <strong>must</strong> be at least <code>180</code> centimeters (width). Lesser the space we have higher is the probability to disturb our or our partner sleep. Sleep with someone else have benefits <strong>pre</strong> and <strong>post</strong> sleep. In an ideal world, we only [pre/post]sleep together.</li>
<li>Duvet optimal values: <code>13,5</code> tog during winter, <code>4,5</code> tog during summer, <code>9,0</code> tog during autumn and spring. In hot summer obviously we can use only a duvet cover or nothing at all.</li>
<li>Bedroom best practices:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>minimal forniture, cleaned space and color neutral.</li>
<li>can be totally overshadowed (use a night mask can be bothersome, we must be as free as possible).</li>
<li>temperature should be between <code>16-18</code> celsius degree.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Use your bed only for sleeping.</li>
<li>Try to avoid a bottle of water near the bed. Think: why do you need it? If you wake up with a dry throat probably is because you are breathing with your mouth while sleeping. If you wake up in order to go to the bathroom, maybe you have drink too much before sleep. In addition keep a bottle of water near your bed, let your mind think about it during night, with higher probability to think you need a sip.</li>
<li>The best alarm clock is a sunrise simulator. A device useful not only for whom suffering SAD (Seasonal Affective Disorder) but for everyone that try to wake up with a “sunrise”. A sunrise simulator has beneficial brain and body effects in addition to emotional feelings and well being.</li>
<li>Benefits that come with <strong>R90 program</strong> (all tips mentioned above and below) become effective only in addition to good nutrition and body exercises. Tackle these three problems together and each one enhance benefits to the rest. Your life surely will be better.</li>
<li>Tryptophan is an α-amino acid that is used in the biosynthesis of proteins. It is essential in humans, meaning the body cannot synthesize it and thus it must be obtained from the diet (fish, banana, dried fruit). Tryptophan is also a precursor to the neurotransmitter serotonin and the hormone melatonin. Sport athletes use <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1082898/">Montmorency’s cherry</a> as bio-hacking supplement. Glyn Howatson professor of Northumbria University has lead numerous studies that prove his beneficial effects and his efficiency after an intensive physical activity. In addition Glyn proved that these black berry increase melatonin production.</li>
<li>Oregon State University stated that <code>150</code> minutes of physical training per week, enhance sleep quality by <code>65%</code>.</li>
<li>Sleeping pills can give addiction, memory loss and sleepwalking</li>
<li>Think about your sleep in a time window of <code>7</code> days. One night is not enough to draw conclusions</li>
<li><p>Usually it is more problematic to <strong>travel</strong> eastward rather than westward. Good tips are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Go to bed and get up early some days before your departure.</li>
<li>Expose to sunlight early each day and avoid it during the evening</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sunlights</strong> is a lot of more effective rather than caffeine to keep you awake and sleeping pills to make you sleep.</p></li>
<li>An unbalanced sleep, typical to shift workers can lead to different problems such as depression, immune system imbalance, increase risk for cancer, cronic cardiopathy and metabolism disorders (type 2 diabetes). It is proven that being under these changes has severe health consequences. A study done to a sample of <code>70.000</code> nurses with a time window of 22 years has proven that after 5 years of shift work, probabilities to early death increase. Play with our internal clock has consequences. Always.</li>
<li><strong>winter blues</strong>: winter tendency to slow down mood and wants. You can try to avoid winter blues trying to go out and get direct sunlight between 11am to 16pm</li>
<li>National Sleep Foundation recommend for newborns from 14 to 17 sleep hours per day. A quantity that decrease while children grow. 9 to 11 when they start to go to school and 8 to 10 at the age of fourteen.</li>
<li>Help your children to sleep well using pre and post routines and avoid/banish stimulant substances such as sugars.</li>
<li>Teenagers sleep more because is your body that need more sleep.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="pre-sleep-routine">Pre Sleep Routine</h2>
<ul>
<li>A pre-sleep routine enhance your sleeping quality. Sometimes is better to reduce sleeping time in order to do your routine. Remember that it is a way much better <strong>quality</strong> rather than <strong>quantity</strong> in sleep.</li>
<li>Keep your bedroom with fresh air (not cold) is really important.</li>
<li>Have a warm shower rise your body temperature. When you get into bed, a little colder than you, works as naturally thermal excursion. In addition a lot of people feel comfortable getting into bed clean. It is not indispensable having a full shower, a rinse is enough.</li>
<li>Intensive training during afternoon or even evening increase bloody pressure (already at his maximum levels at that time) and for that reason it is not recommended before sleep, above all for the erderly. However going for a walk, yoga, stretching or low intensive exercises are recommended because as we said earlier rising your body temperature before sleeping can help.</li>
<li>Soften all surroundings is another tip. Switch off lights or keep them low, if possible choose lights with a warm color temperature.</li>
<li><p>Recommended activities:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Have a shower</li>
<li>Tidy up</li>
<li>Writing (thoughts, appointments, TODOs for the next day, stoic diary, …)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote></li>
<li>You might eat at least <code>3</code> hours before going to sleep. It is possible to have a snack but only before your pre-sleep routine (that is around <code>90</code> minutes).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="post-sleep-routine">Post Sleep Routine</h2>
<ul>
<li>Post sleep routine enhance our efficiency during the day.</li>
<li>If you wake up and your mouth is dry probably you breath throughout your mouth while asleep. Conversely if your mouth is wet, you are using your nose to breathe.</li>
<li>Cortisol (steroid hormone released in response to stress and low blood-glucose concentration) has his maximal level soon after your wake up time. It is useful start your day with relaxing activities, such as meditation, yoga, daily journal, reading…</li>
<li>When you wake up, get direct sunlight, it enhance our clarity of mind, it balance our biological clock and it prepare our body to switch from melatonin production to serotonin production.</li>
<li>Avoid un-healthy snacks (with too much sugar or difficult to digest).</li>
<li>If it is possible, have breakfast outdoor or at least in a room with a lot of sunlight. If outside the sun is not rise yet, switch on an artificial natural light.</li>
<li>It is a good habit doing some exercises, both high or low intensive. Having a walk, yoga, Taiji..</li>
<li>Easy mental activities such as listen to the radio, iron some clothes, tidy up, read and fix something are welcome.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="nap">NAP</h2>
<ul>
<li><em>Nap with steroids</em>: assume caffeine before having your nap boost results. <strong>NB</strong> (the desired effects arise approximately <code>30</code> minutes after consumption).</li>
<li>It is not necessary to have perfect conditions. You can make a nap while you are in a sitting position.</li>
<li>It is not important if you fall asleep or not. It is important that you take advantage of this resting time, <em>“switching off”</em> your brain.</li>
<li>Find a way to rest. Rest improve your efficiency and concentration, it is scientifically proven.</li>
<li>In addition, switching off your brain reduce stress and keep your productivity high during all day.</li>
<li>If you sleep (<code>1</code> cycle, <code>90</code> minutes, or more) during the day, it is preferred to choose between (<code>13-15</code>, <code>1pm-3pm</code>) and (<code>17-19</code>, <code>5pm-7pm</code>). The first one is better because is like the night period between <code>2am</code> and <code>3am</code> where the circadian stimulus is at his higher rate.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>We do not really know what sleep is. This may be upsetting for outsiders. - <a href="https://profiles.stanford.edu/philippe-mourrain?tab=bio">Philippe Mourrain</a></p>
<p>Breakfast is the most important meal. Period.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://sleepspecialist.co.uk/site-info-old/chris-idzikowski-1">Chris Idzikowski</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26533127-the-oxygen-advantage">The Oxygen Advantage</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1082898/">Montmorency’s cherry</a></li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>La Grande Via</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-05-29-grandevia.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-05-29-grandevia.html</id>
    <published>2017-05-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-05-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#la-grande-via">La Grande Via</a><ul>
<li><a href="#diet">Diet</a></li>
<li><a href="#exercise">Exercise</a></li>
<li><a href="#meditation">Meditation</a></li>
<li><a href="#other-hints">Other hints</a></li>
<li><a href="#quotes">Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="la-grande-via">La Grande Via</h1>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://www.lagrandevia.it/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/lagrandevia-berrino-fontana.jpg" style="width:50.0%" />

</div>
<h2 id="diet">Diet</h2>
<ul>
<li>Stop eat before being full.</li>
<li>Fasting is a good habit. Do not eat few and often. Stomach needs to rest.</li>
<li>Eat until 3/4 full.</li>
<li>People can live eating 1/4, with other 3/4 live doctors.</li>
<li>TRF (Time Restricted Feeding) is lowering by 30% Kcal income per meal.</li>
<li><p>Fast 2 or 3 times a week. It is considered fasting:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Eat raw/cooked vegetables (avoid potatoes) with dressing such as olive oil (1 tbs per meal a day), lemon or vinegar No cereals, fruits or proteins.</li>
<li>Keep your stomach at rest at least 14 to 16 hours a day.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Have a bit of hungry is good, our body produces an hormone called Ghrelin. Ghrelin gene products have several actions on acute and chronic inflammation and autoimmunity.</li>
<li>Best breakfast time slot is between 7am to 9am</li>
<li>Buckwheat can be used to make cornmeal mush</li>
<li>Rye has lower glycemic load</li>
<li>Soybean has more proteins than parmigiano</li>
<li>Legumes raise HDL levels, you must eat them at least 2 or 4 times a week</li>
<li>Raw rice and lentils is a balance dish</li>
<li>Use malts and almond/hazelnut/sesame cremes together. Malts have high glycemia index but do not have fructose. Eat them with healthy fat as almon/hazelnut/sesame cremes decrease glucose absorption time. It useful eat them with legumes also.</li>
<li>Daily salt upper bound: 2,4g</li>
<li>Do not give sugar (in every form) to babies until 2 years old. White sugar if possible NEVER.</li>
<li>Mother feeding during pregnancy will be liked to her baby too</li>
<li>Eat fish 1 or 2 times a week</li>
<li>Eat fruits or jasmine Tea as dessert</li>
<li>Cultivate enhance health, Okinawa people are a living example</li>
<li><em>Nan kuru nai sa</em> - Everything will be OK</li>
<li>Pesco-vegetarians have much higher health levels (stats)</li>
<li>Calcium, tea, coffee, cocoa inhibits iron and zinc assimilation. Food with high levels of iron and zinc are grain cream, tahin, soy, azuki beans. Fermentation, sprouting and long leavening are practices that keep nutrients more assimilable</li>
<li>Vitamin D help calcium absorption. Calcium can be found in high quantities into turnip greens, cabbage (40-60% in comparison to only 30% in cow milk), legumes (eg: soy), figs.</li>
<li>In order to assimilate as much as possible nutrients from lettuce, use olive oil as dressing and add wild herbs such as lemon balm, mint, marjoram.</li>
<li>Pan-fry (with olive oil) vegetables in order to better assimilate carotenoids. Carotenoids:
<ul>
<li>alpha e beta carotene: green leaf or yellow vegetables</li>
<li>lycopene: tomatoes, peanuts</li>
<li>beta criptoxantina: pumpkin</li>
<li>lutein: cabbage</li>
<li>capsanthin: chili pepper, red pepper, paprika</li>
<li>crocin: saffron</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Vegetables must be eaten both raw and cooked (pan-fry or in hot water or steamed) Pan-fry cabbage enhance his nutrients, same with onion.</li>
<li>Garlic is better squashed. It releases chemical nutrients as defense mechanism.</li>
<li>Olive oil is useful to prevent thrombosis</li>
<li><p>Almonds and hazelnuts both raw or toasted reduce LDL</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="exercise">Exercise</h2>
<ul>
<li>Aerobic exercises for heart and lungs are walking, jogging, running, cycling, dancing, swimming and skiing</li>
<li>Doing exercises increase mitochondria levels (power and speed)</li>
<li>Benefits from exercises shade after 24-48 hours, keep your training session inside this time slot</li>
<li>Exercises and weight loss increase HDL levels</li>
<li>Exercises produce catepsina B useful in cognitive functions and memory</li>
<li>Heart rate upper bound is: 220 - age</li>
<li>HIT(High Interval Training) = switch between high intensive exercises (60s 90/85% max heart rate) with resting periods (60s). Do it 10 times per row Do not exceed 5/10 minutes of work. Metabolic effects are the same as long training sessions of aerobic exercises (100 minutes)</li>
<li>Exertion, feeding, alcohol, sleep and sex need caution</li>
<li>Exhale while lifting</li>
<li>Do not stay too much seated, change your posture often</li>
<li>Stretching! After some time passed seated and before exercises. It increase muscle grow, oxygenation and movement awareness</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="meditation">Meditation</h2>
<ul>
<li>“OM” vibes inhibit limbic system, it is responsible in controlling emotions</li>
<li>You don’t need to be in a temple or have particular things, nothing will follow you up</li>
<li><p>Yoga stages (by Patañjali):</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>External
<ul>
<li>Yama (passions)</li>
<li>Niyama (emotions)</li>
<li>Asana (know and keep healthy your body)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Breathing
<ul>
<li>Pranayama</li>
<li>Pratyahara</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Meditation (dharana, dhyana, samadhi)</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>Yoga and martial arts are good for kids:</p>
<ul>
<li>enhance ideas and planning</li>
<li>inhibit irrelevant informations and suppress their impulses</li>
<li>change and adapts behaviours</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Ataraxia = imperturbable spirit</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="other-hints">Other hints</h2>
<ul>
<li>Vitamin D is really important. During summer 5-15 minutes of direct sunlight are enough. For a much longer exposure sunscreen is needed. During winter before 10am and after 4pm UVB ray can’t go beyond ozone layer. It is useful sunbathing between 10am and 4pm. A dietary supplement of 800-1000 UI per day can be helpful (in winter).</li>
<li>Amory Lovins, expert in energy efficiency. He also wrote an interesting book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/12742309-reinventing-fire">Reinventing Fire</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Eat breakfast like a king, lunch like a prince, and dinner like a pauper.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Breakfast is for you, lunch to be shared and dinner gifted.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Fasting is the best cure, our doctor inside- Filippo Paracelso</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Meditation must start with the body. The body is the vehicle of himself, you need to control it in order to really meditate - Iyengar</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>A life without research is a life wasted</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Sky roads can be seen without looking out the windows</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Only in finite is expressed infinite and in time the eternal.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Watch your thoughts, they become words; watch your words, they become actions; watch your actions, they become habits; watch your habits, they become character; watch your character, for it becomes your destiny. - Frank Outlaw</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Happiness is also a way of interpreting the world, since while it may be difficult to change the world, it is always possible to change the way we look at it. - Matthieu Ricard</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>If something make you angry, think about what is more important: that thing or your health? In a moment, if you are wise enough, angry vanished. - Cao Tingdong</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>In cultivating body, mind and spirit it is necessary to keep in mind: be friendly, loyal and with broadminded. Not too much happy for praises nor too much angry for blames.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.lagrandevia.it/la-grande-via/">La grande via</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52036.Siddhartha">Siddharta</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/67896.Tao_Te_Ching">Tao te chin - Lao Tzu</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2340397.The_Philosophy_of_Spinoza">The philosophy of spinoza - Ratner J</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Longevity-Life-Preservation-Chinese-MING/dp/753772606X">Gong Ting Xian - Longevità e preservazione della vita</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun_Simiao">Sun Simiao</a></li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Predictably Irrational</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-04-14-predictably-irrational.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-04-14-predictably-irrational.html</id>
    <published>2017-04-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#predictably-irrational-the-hidden-forces-that-shape-our-decisions-ariely-dan">Predictably Irrational: The Hidden Forces that Shape Our Decisions (Ariely, Dan)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1255573980l/1713426.jpg" />

</div>
<h3 id="predictably-irrational-the-hidden-forces-that-shape-our-decisions-ariely-dan">Predictably Irrational: The Hidden Forces that Shape Our Decisions (Ariely, Dan)</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>creating an expensive dish, a restaurateur can lure customers into ordering the second most expensive choice (which can be cleverly engineered to deliver a higher profit margin</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we are always looking at the things around us in relation to others.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we not only tend to compare things with one another but also tend to focus on comparing things that are easily comparable—and avoid comparing things that cannot be compared easily.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we are wired to compare.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That’s a lesson we can all learn: the more we have, the more we want. And the only cure is to break the cycle of relativity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>decoy effect</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Tom had discovered a great law of human action, namely, that in order to make a man covet a thing, it is only necessary to make the thing difficult to attain.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That our first decisions resonate over a long sequence of decisions. First impressions are important,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We call this type of behavior herding. It happens when we assume that something is good (or bad) on the basis of other people’s previous behavior, and our own actions follow suit.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You might begin by questioning that habit. How did it begin? Second, ask yourself what amount of pleasure you will be getting out of it. Is the pleasure as much as you thought you would get? Could you cut back a little and better spend the remaining money on something else? With everything you do, in fact, you should train yourself to question your repeated behaviors.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We should also pay particular attention to the first decision we make in what is going to be a long stream of decisions (about clothing, food, etc.). When we face such a decision, it might seem to us that this is just one decision, without large consequences; but in fact the power of the first decision can have such a long-lasting effect that it will percolate into our future decisions for years to come. Given this effect, the first decision is crucial, and we should give it an appropriate amount of attention.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>what consumers are willing to pay can easily be manipulated, and this means that consumers don’t in fact have a good handle on their own preferences and the prices they are willing to pay for different goods and experiences.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the sensitivity we show to price changes might in fact be largely a result of our memory for the prices we have paid in the past and our desire for coherence with our past decisions—not at all a reflection of our true preferences or our level of demand.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>humans are intrinsically afraid of loss. The real allure of FREE! is tied to this fear. There’s no visible possibility of loss when we choose a FREE! item (it’s free). But suppose we choose the item that’s not free. Uh-oh, now there’s a risk of having made a poor decision—the possibility of a loss. And so, given the choice, we go for what is free.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Zero is not just another discount. Zero is a different place. The difference between two cents and one cent is small. But the difference between one cent and zero is huge! If you are in business, and understand that, you can do some marvelous things. Want to draw a crowd? Make something FREE! Want to sell more</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>products? Make part of the purchase FREE!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There are many examples to show that people will work more for a cause than for cash.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The conclusion: no one is offended by a small gift, because even small gifts keep us in the social exchange world and away from market norms.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>for heaven’s sake don’t mention the price of the selections.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>SO WE LIVE in two worlds: one characterized by social exchanges and the other characterized by market exchanges. And we apply different norms to these two kinds of relationships. Moreover, introducing market norms into social exchanges, as we have seen, violates the social norms and hurts the relationships. Once this type of mistake has been committed, recovering a social relationship is difficult.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There are social rewards that strongly motivate behavior—and one of the least used in corporate life is the encouragement of social rewards and reputation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>to be flexible, concerned, and willing to pitch in. That’s what a social relationship delivers.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But money has also taken on a life of its own. As we have seen, it can remove the best in human interactions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We should probably first rethink school curricula, and link them in more obvious ways to social goals (elimination of poverty and crime, elevation of human rights, etc.), technological goals (boosting energy conservation, space exploration, nanotechnology, etc.), and medical goals (cures for cancer, diabetes, obesity, etc.) that we care about as a society.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>MONEY, AS IT turns out, is very often the most expensive way to motivate people. Social norms are not only cheaper, but often more effective as well.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Money is not accepted at Burning Man. Rather, the whole place works as a gift exchange economy—you give things to other people, with the understanding that they will give something back to you (or to someone else) at some point in the future</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>life with fewer market norms and more social norms would be more satisfying, creative, fulfilling, and fun.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Even so, we all systematically underpredict the degree to which arousal completely negates our superego, and the way emotions can take control of our behavior.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>LOOKING FROM ONE emotional state to another is difficult. It’s not always possible; and as Sumi learned it can be painful. But to make informed decisions we need to somehow experience and understand the emotional state we will be in at the other side of the experience. Learning how to bridge this gap is essential to making some of the important decisions of our lives.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>that tightly restricting their freedom (equally spaced deadlines, imposed from above) is the best cure for procrastination</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>simply offering the students a tool by which they could precommit to deadlines helped them achieve better grades.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Because without precommitments, we keep on falling for temptation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the best course might be to give people an opportunity to commit up front to their preferred path of action. This approach might not be as effective as the dictatorial treatment, but it can help push us in the right direction (perhaps even more so if we train people to do it, and give them experience in setting their own deadlines). What’s the bottom line? We have problems with self-control, related to immediate and delayed gratification—no doubt there. But each of the problems we face has potential self-control mechanisms, as well. If we can’t save from our paycheck, we can take advantage of our employer’s automatic deduction option; if we don’t have the will to exercise regularly alone, we can make an appointment to exercise in the company of our friends. These are the tools that we can commit to in advance, and they may help us be the kind of people we want to be.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>simplification is one mark of real genius.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>OWNERSHIP PERVADES OUR lives and, in a strange way, shapes many of the things we do. Adam Smith wrote, “Every man [and woman] … lives by exchanging, or becomes in some measure a merchant, and the society itself grows to be what is properly a commercial society.” That’s an awesome thought. Much of our life story can be told by describing the ebb and flow of our particular possessions—what we get and what we give up. We buy clothes and food, automobiles and homes, for instance. And we sell things as well—homes and cars, and in the course of our careers, our time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first quirk, as we saw in the case of the basketball tickets, is that we fall in love with what we already have.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The second quirk is that we focus on what we may lose, rather than what we may gain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our aversion to loss is a strong emotion, and as I will explain later in the book, one that sometimes causes us to make bad decisions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The third quirk is that we assume other people will see the transaction from the same perspective as we do.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Another peculiarity is that we can begin to feel ownership even before we own something.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>OWNERSHIP IS NOT limited to material things. It can also apply to points of view.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My own approach is to try to view all transactions (particularly large ones) as if I were a nonowner, putting some distance between myself and the item of interest. In this attempt, I’m not certain if I have achieved the uninterest in material things that is espoused by the Hindu sannyasi, but at least I try to be as Zen as I can about it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The truth is that they could have made more money by picking a room—any room—and merely staying there for the whole experiment! (Think about that in terms of your life or career.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Erich Fromm wrote a book called Escape from Freedom. In a modern democracy, he said, people are beset not by a lack of opportunity, but by a dizzying abundance of it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We may work more hours at our jobs, for instance, without realizing that the childhood of our sons and daughters is slipping away. Sometimes these doors close too slowly for us to see them vanishing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What we need is to consciously start closing some of our doors. Small doors, of course, are rather easy to close. We can easily strike names off our holiday card lists or omit the tae kwon do from our daughter’s string of activities.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We have an irrational compulsion to keep doors open. It’s just the way we’re wired. But that doesn’t mean we shouldn’t try to close them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>focusing on the similarities and minor differences between two things was to take into account the consequences of not deciding.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>WHEN WE BELIEVE beforehand that something will be good, therefore, it generally will be good—and when we think it will be bad, it will bad.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we acknowledge that we are trapped within our perspective, which partially blinds us to the truth, we may be able to accept the idea that conflicts generally require a neutral third party—who has not been tainted with our expectations—to set down the rules and regulations. Of course, accepting the word of a third party is not easy and not always possible; but when it is possible, it can yield substantial benefits. And for that reason alone, we must continue to try. Di’ tutte queste cose agli altri, ma in modo da udire anche tu, nel dirle; scrivile, ma per leggerle mentre le scrivi; e rivolgi ogni tuo impegno a migliorare i costumi e a placare il furore delle passioni. Sia tua cura non di saper di più, ma di sapere meglio.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>GENERAL, TWO mechanisms shape the expectations that make placebos work. One is belief—our confidence or faith in the drug, the procedure, or the caregiver. Sometimes just the fact that a doctor or nurse is paying attention to us and reassuring us not only makes us feel better but also triggers our internal healing processes. Even a doctor’s enthusiasm for a particular treatment or procedure may predispose us toward a positive outcome. The second mechanism is conditioning. Like Pavlov’s famous dogs (that learned to salivate at the ring of a bell), the body builds up expectancy after repeated experiences and releases various chemicals to prepare us for the future.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>there is nothing “just” about the power of a placebo, and in reality it represents the amazing way our mind controls our body. How the mind achieves these amazing outcomes is not always very clear. Some of the effect, to be sure, has to do with reducing the level of stress, changing hormonal secretions, changing the immune system, etc. The more we understand the connection between brain and body, the more things that once seemed clear-cut become ambiguous. Nowhere is this as apparent as with the placebo.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Behavioral economists, on the other hand, believe that people are susceptible to irrelevant influences from their immediate environment (which we call context effects), irrelevant emotions, shortsightedness, and other forms of irrationality</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>why not develop new strategies, tools, and methods to help us make better decisions and improve our overall well-being? That’s exactly the meaning of free lunches from the perspective of behavioral economics—the idea that there are tools, methods, and policies that can help all of us make better decisions and as a consequence achieve what we desire.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>fact, research in behavioral economics points to many possible reasons why people are not saving enough for retirement. People procrastinate. People have a hard time understanding the real cost of not saving as well as the benefits of saving.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>IF I WERE to distill one main lesson from the research described in this book, it is that we are pawns in a game whose forces we largely fail to comprehend. We usually think of ourselves as sitting in the driver’s seat, with ultimate control over the decisions we make and the direction our life takes; but, alas, this perception has more to do with our desires—with how we want to view ourselves—than with reality.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Leisure - The Basis of Culture</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-11-01-leisure.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-11-01-leisure.html</id>
    <published>2016-11-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-11-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#leisure-the-basis-of-culture-pieper-joseph">Leisure: The Basis of Culture (Pieper, Joseph)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1389227160l/767958.jpg" />

</div>
<h2 id="leisure-the-basis-of-culture-pieper-joseph">Leisure: The Basis of Culture (Pieper, Joseph)</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>We shall see each other again.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ratio is the power of discursive, logical thought, of searching and of examination, of abstraction, of definition and drawing conclusions. Intellectus, on the other hand, is the name for the understanding in so far as it is the capacity of simplex intuitus, of that simple vision to which truth offers itself like a landscape to the eye.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The tendency to overvalue hard work and the effort of doing something difficult is so deep-rooted that it even infects our notion of love. Why should it be that the average Christian regards loving one’s enemy as the most exalted form of love? Principally because it offers an example of a natural bent heroically curbed; the exceptional difficulty, the impossibility one might almost say, of loving one’s enemy constitutes the greatness of the love. And what does Aquinas say? “It is not the difficulty of loving one’s enemy that matters when the essence of the merit of doing so is concerned, excepting in so far as the perfection of love wipes out the difficulty. And therefore, if love were to be so perfect that the difficulty vanished altogether—it would be more meritorious still.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>And in the same way, the essence of knowledge does not consist in the effort for which it calls, but in grasping existing things and in unveiling reality. Moreover, just as the highest form of virtue knows nothing of “difficulty”, so too the highest form of knowledge comes to man like a gift—the sudden illumination, a stroke of genius, true contemplation; it comes effortlessly and without trouble. On one occasion St. Thomas speaks of contemplation and play in the same breath: “because of the leisure that goes with contemplation” the divine wisdom itself, Holy Scripture says, is “always at play, playing through the whole world”(</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>man seems to mistrust everything that is effortless; he can only enjoy, with a good conscience, what he has acquired with toil and trouble; he refuses to have anything as a gift.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The liberal arts, then, include all forms of human activity which are an end in themselves; the servile arts are those which have an end beyond themselves, and more precisely an end which consists in a utilitarian result attainable in practice, a practicable result.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Education concerns the whole man; an educated man is a man with a point of view from which he takes in the whole world.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Aquinas writes, “that there should be men who devote their lives to contemplation”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Compared with the exclusive ideal of work as activity, leisure implies (in the first place) an attitude of non-activity, of inward calm, of silence; it means not being “busy”, but letting things happen.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Silence, as it is used in this context, does not mean “dumbness” or “noiselessness”; it means more nearly that the soul’s power to “answer” to the reality of the world is left undisturbed. For leisure is a receptive attitude of mind, a contemplative attitude, and it is not only the occasion but also the capacity for steeping oneself in the whole of creation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Furthermore, there is also a certain serenity in leisure. That serenity springs precisely from our inability to understand, from our recognition of the mysterious nature of the universe; it springs from the courage of deep confidence, so that we are content to let things take their course; and there is something about it which Konrad Weiss, the poet, called “confidence in the fragmentariness of life and history.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>leisure appears (secondly) in its character as an attitude of contemplative “celebration”,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Leisure is possible only on the premise that man consents to his own true nature and abides in concord with the meaning of the universe</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Leisure draws its vitality from affirmation. It is not the same as non-activity, nor is it identical with tranquility; it is not even the same as inward tranquility. Rather, it is like the tranquil silence of lovers, which draws its strength from concord.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A break in one’s work, whether of an hour, a day or a week, is still part of the world of work. It is a link in the chain of utilitarian functions. The pause is made for the sake of work and in order to work, and a man is not only refreshed from work but for work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The soul of leisure, it can be said, lies in “celebration”.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>its ultimate justification derive from its roots in divine worship.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Temple” means (as may be seen from the original sense of the word): that a particular piece of ground is specially reserved, and marked off from the remainder of the land which is used either for agriculture or for habitation. And this plot of land is transferred to the estate of the gods, it is neither lived on, nor cultivated. And similarly in divine worship a certain definite space of time is set aside from working hours and days, a limited time, specially marked off—and like the space allotted to the temple, is not used, is withdrawn from all merely utilitarian ends. Every seventh day is such a period of time. It is the “festival time”, and it arises in this way and no other.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is in fact no room in the world of “total labor” either for divine worship, or for a feast: because the “worker’s” world, the world of “labor” rests solely upon the principle of rational utilization.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>sacrifice mean? It means a voluntary offering freely given. It definitely does not involve utility; it is in fact absolutely antithetic to utility. Thus, the act of worship creates a store of real wealth that cannot be consumed by the workaday world.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The vacancy left by absence of worship is filled by mere killing of time and by boredom, which is directly related to inability to enjoy leisure; for one can only be bored if the spiritual power to be leisurely has been lost.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The opening question, What does philosophizing mean? is certainly philosophical.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But like all philosophical questions, it cannot be answered with complete finality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>because you think you are doing something when you are really doing nothing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>serves no purpose whatsoever beyond itself and its own end or that it can never be used apart from its own end. Philosophy is not functional knowledge but, as Newman said, “the knowledge of a gentleman”;9 not a useful knowledge, but a “free” knowledge. Freedom, here, means that philosophical knowledge is not legitimized by its usefulness or usableness, or by virtue of its social function, or with reference to the “common need”. This is the selfsame sense in which “freedom” was used in the phrase “artes liberales”, the liberal arts—in contradistinction to the “artes serviles”, the servile arts which, as Aquinas says, are “ordered to the satisfaction of a need through activity.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“freedom” being understood to mean “not being at the disposal of external aims and ends”. The different branches of science are “free” in this sense, provided only that they are pursued philosophically and in so far as they share the freedom of philosophy. “Knowledge is free”, writes Newman, “in the truest sense, as soon as and in so far as it is philosophical.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whenever we look at being philosophically, we discourse purely “theoretically” about it, in a manner, that is to say, untouched in any way whatsoever by practical considerations, by the desire to change it; and it is in this sense that philosophy is said to be above any and every “purpose”.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>transcends the world of work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“What do they not see, who see him who sees all things?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Aqhinas = San Tommaso d’Aquino, citazione presa da ‘commento alle sentenze di Pietro Lombardo’ o ‘Somma Teologica’</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That, then, is the first point: the world is a field of relations. To have a world is to be the center, the coordinator, of a field of relations. The second point is: the higher the order of a being, the more embracing and wider its power of establishing relations—the greater the field of relations within its power. This may also be expressed by saying that the higher a being stands in the order of reality, in the hierarchic order of being, the wider and deeper its world.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>And “surroundings”, even “surroundings” which could “in themselves” be apprehended, do not yet constitute a “world”. Though this view was far from generally held until Jacob von Uexküll, the</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That would explain why so many insects feign death. If their motionless form simply does not exist in the field of vision of their enemies, then by shamming death they drop out of that world with absolute certainty and cannot be found even though searched for.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>human world “cannot claim to be any more real than the animal’s world”;4 man, then, is limited by his environment in exactly the same way as an animal, that is to say, he is limited to a selected environment assembled, as it were, by natural selection and biological necessity; he is incapable of apprehending anything and, even though searching for it, of finding anything outside his environment—like the crow that cannot find a motionless grasshopper. (The question does arise, however, as to how a creature limited to its own environment and imprisoned so effectively within it could study the theory of environment.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>anima est quodammodo omnia, the soul is in a certain sense all things, the all.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To the philosophers of the past—to Plato, Aristotle, Augustine, and Thomas Aquinas—the concepts of “spirit” and “world” (in the sense of the whole of reality) are not only interrelated; their correspondence is complete. These philosophers not only held that “spirit is relatedness to the totality of existing things”, but also that all existing things are essentially related to spirit. Moreover, they formulated that relation in such precise terms that at first we scarcely dare to take them at their word. Not only, they said, is it of the nature of the spirit for its frame of reference to be the totality of existing things; but it is also of the nature of existing things for them to lie within spirit’s frame of reference. Furthermore, in the philosophical tradition of which I am speaking, it comes to the same thing whether I say, “Things have being” or whether I say, “Things exist in the spirit’s frame of reference.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the world of a spiritual being is the totality of existing things; and their correspondence is so complete that it is both essential to spirit (spirit is the power of embracing the totality of being) and equally it is essential to things themselves (“to be” means “to be in relation to spirit”).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>that the greater the capacity for relations the greater the dimensions of the coordinated field, until that field becomes (for spirit) “the” world.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the same time it is one of the characteristics of man, a corporeal and spiritual being, that it should be his spiritual soul which informs the physical and sensitive realms—to such a degree that taking food in man and animal are two utterly different things (quite apart from the fact that in the human sphere a “meal” may have a spiritual or even a religious character). It is so true that the spiritual soul informs the whole of man’s nature that even when a man “vegetates” it is ultimately only possible because he is spiritual—a cabbage can’t vegetate. Equally, when man shuts himself up in his environment, in the sphere defined and limited by his immediate needs, the degeneration that follows is only possible because spiritual degeneration is possible. The really human thing is to see the stars above the roof, to preserve our apprehension of the universality of things in the midst of the habits of daily life, and to see “the world” above and beyond our immediate environment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Socrates and says that the teacher only induces the learner to remember “and to win knowledge from out of himself”; “there is no such thing as learning, one only remembers once again.”14 Yet another man comes along maintaining that we are all faced by or face the same reality: the teacher only points it out, the learner, the hearer, then sees it for himself.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The distinctive mark of a philosophical question is, then, that it brings out what constitutes the essence of spirit: convenire cum omni ente, in harmony with everything that is. One cannot ask a philosophical question or think philosophically without bringing the whole of being into play, the totality of existing things, “God and the world”.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>to philosophize means to step beyond the sectional, partial environment of the workaday world into a position vis-à-vis de l’univers: a step that takes one into the open, for the heavens are not a roof over a man’s head—though one ought always to leave the door open behind one, for a man cannot live like that continuously.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To philosophize means to withdraw—not from the things of everyday life—but from the currently accepted meaning attached to them, or to question the value placed upon them. This does not, of course, take place by virtue of some decision to differentiate our attitude from that of others and to see things “differently”, but because, quite suddenly, things themselves assume a different aspect.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the beginning of philosophy is wonder.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Theoria” is only possible in so far as man is not blind to the wonderful fact that things are. For our sense of wonder, in the philosophical meaning of the word, is not aroused by enormous, sensational things—though that is what a dulled sensibility requires to provoke it to a sort of ersatz experience of wonder. A man who needs the unusual to make him “wonder” shows that he has lost the capacity to find the true answer to the wonder of being.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>doubt is the beginning of philosophy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The innermost meaning of wonder is fulfilled in a deepened sense of mystery. It does not end in doubt, but is the awakening of the knowledge that being, qua being, is mysterious and inconceivable, and that it is a mystery in the full sense of the word: neither a dead end, nor a contradiction, nor even something impenetrable and dark. Rather, mystery means that a reality cannot be comprehended because its light is ever-flowing, unfathomable, and inexhaustible. And that is what the wonderer really experiences.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the Summa Theologica 7 wonder is defined as the desiderium sciendi, the longing for knowledge, an active desire for knowledge. Although to wonder means, as we have said, not to know, it does not mean that we are, in a kind of despair, resigned to ignorance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“the really damaging thing about stupidity is its self-satisfaction.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>to wonder, to philosophize, means to hope!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Philosophy never claimed to be a superior form of knowledge but, on the contrary, a form of humility, and restrained, and conscious of this restraint and humility in relation to knowledge. The words philosopher and philosophy were coined, according to legend—and the legend is of great antiquity—by Pythagoras in explicit contrast to the words sophia and sophos: no man is wise, and no man “knows”;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>is because of the ambivalent structure of philosophy, because “marveling” sets one on a road that never ends, because the structure of philosophy is that of hope, that to philosophize is so essentially human—and in a sense to philosophize means living a truly human life.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Peace Is Every Step</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-09-13-peace-every-step.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-09-13-peace-every-step.html</id>
    <published>2016-09-13T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-09-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#peace-is-every-step-the-path-of-mindfulness-in-everyday-life-hanh-thich-nhat">Peace Is Every Step: The Path of Mindfulness in Everyday Life (Hanh, Thich Nhat)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1320544155l/14572.jpg" />

</div>
<h2 id="peace-is-every-step-the-path-of-mindfulness-in-everyday-life-hanh-thich-nhat">Peace Is Every Step: The Path of Mindfulness in Everyday Life (Hanh, Thich Nhat)</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Every time you do an activity, or have a thought, you are changing a piece of yourself into something slightly different than it was before. Every hour you spend with others, you become more like the people around you. Gradually, you become a different person. If there is a large gap between your daily conduct and your core commitment, you will become more like your daily activities and less attached to your original commitment.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if we can only quiet our distracted thinking long enough to come back to the present moment and notice the blue sky, the child’s smile, the beautiful sunrise. “If we are peaceful, if we are happy, we can smile, and everyone in our family, our entire society, will benefit from our peace.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are very good at preparing to live, but not very good at living.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>mind and body are not unified. By concentrating on our breathing, “In” and “Out,” we bring body and mind back together, and become whole again. Conscious breathing is an important bridge.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are what we feel and perceive. If we are angry, we are the anger. If we are in love, we are love. If we look at a snow-covered mountain peak, we are the mountain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whether we are in the city, the countryside, or the wilderness, we need to sustain ourselves by choosing our surroundings carefully and nourishing our awareness in each moment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We need to practice meditation gently, but steadily, throughout daily life, not wasting a single opportunity or event to see deeply into the true nature of life, including our everyday problems. Practicing in this way, we dwell in profound communion with life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We have to learn to really enjoy our church bells and our school bells. Bells are beautiful, and they can wake us up.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Everything is still there, and if you really want it, you can find it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Eating mindfully is a most important practice of meditation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You become a bodhisattva, helping a living being become enlightened. Children, in particular, are very capable of practicing mindfulness and reminding others to do the same.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mindfulness can penetrate the activities of everyday life, each minute, each hour of our daily life, and not just be a description of something far away.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>By taking good care of the present moment, we take good care of the future. Working for peace in the future is to work for peace in the present moment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>has become a kind of habit to look at things with the intention of getting something. We call it “pragmatism,” and we say that the truth is something that pays. If we meditate in order to get to the truth, it seems we will be well paid. In meditation, we stop, and we look deeply. We stop just to be there, to be with ourselves and with the world. When we are capable of stopping, we begin to see and, if we can see, we understand. Peace and happiness are the fruit of this process.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we just act in each moment with composure and mindfulness, each minute of our life is a work of art. Even when we are not painting or writing, we are still creating. We are pregnant with beauty, joy, and peace, and we are making life more beautiful for many people. Sometimes it is better not to talk about art by using the word “art.” If we just act with awareness and integrity, our art will flower, and we don’t have to talk about it at all. When we know how to be peace, we find that art is a wonderful way to share our peacefulness. Artistic expression will take place in one way or another, but the being is essential. So we must go back to ourselves, and when we have joy and peace in ourselves, our creations of art will be quite natural, and they will serve the world in a positive way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When I think deeply about the nature of hope, I see something tragic. Since we cling to our hope in the future, we do not focus our energies and capabilities on the present moment. We use hope to believe something better will happen in the future, that we will arrive at peace, or the Kingdom of God. Hope becomes a kind of obstacle. If you can refrain from hoping, you can bring yourself entirely into the present moment and discover the joy that is already here.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I do not mean that you should not have hope, but that hope is not enough. Hope can create an obstacle for you, and if you dwell in the energy of hope, you will not bring yourself back entirely into the present moment. If you re-channel those energies into being aware of what is going on in the present moment, you will be able to make a breakthrough and discover joy and peace right in the present moment, inside of yourself and all around you.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When someone holds up a flower and shows it to you, he wants you to see it. If you keep thinking, you miss the flower. The person who was not thinking, who was just himself, was able to encounter the flower in depth, and he smiled. That is the problem of life. If we are not fully ourselves, truly in the present moment, we miss everything</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mindful observation is based on the principle of “non-duality”: our feeling is not separate from us or caused merely by something outside us; our feeling is us, and for the moment we are that feeling. We are neither drowned in nor terrorized by the feeling, nor do we reject it. Our attitude of not clinging to or rejecting our feelings is the attitude of letting go, an important part of meditation practice. If we face our unpleasant feelings with care, affection, and nonviolence, we can transform them into the kind of energy that is healthy and has the capacity to nourish us. By the work of mindful observation, our unpleasant feelings can illuminate so much for us, offering us insight and understanding into ourselves and society.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Instead of acting as if we can dispose of parts of ourselves, we should learn the art of transformation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we become angry at our anger, we will have two angers at the same time. We only have to observe it with love and attention. If we take care of our anger in this way, without trying to run away from it, it will transform itself.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first step in dealing with feelings is to recognize each feeling as it arises.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You calm your feeling just by being with it, like a mother tenderly holding her crying baby.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The second step is to become one with the feeling.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The third step is to calm the feeling.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The fourth step is to release the feeling, to let it go.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The fifth step is to look deeply.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you will know what to do and what not to do to transform the feeling and be free.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>After recognizing the feeling, becoming one with it, calming it down, and releasing it, we can look deeply into its causes, which are often based on inaccurate perceptions. As soon as we understand the causes and nature of our feelings, they begin to transform themselves</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is best if we do not listen to or look at the person whom we consider to be the cause of our anger.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We need the insight and non-dual vision of the organic gardener with regard to our anger. We need not be afraid of it or reject it. We know that anger can be a kind of compost, and that it is within its power to give birth to something beautiful. We need anger in the way the organic gardener needs compost. If we know how to accept our anger, we already have some peace and joy. Gradually we can transform anger completely into peace, love, and understanding.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>our anger will subside and we will feel stronger. Then we can begin to observe the anger directly and try to understand it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Thanks to the illuminating light of awareness, after practicing mindful observation for a while, we begin to see the primary causes of our anger. Meditation helps us look deeply into things in order to see their nature. If we look into our anger, we can see its roots, such as misunderstanding, clumsiness, injustice, resentment, or conditioning. These roots can be present in ourselves and in the person who played the principal role in precipitating our anger. We observe mindfully in order to be able to see and to understand. Seeing and understanding are the elements of liberation that bring about love and compassion. The method of mindful observation in order to see and understand the roots of the anger is a method that has lasting effectiveness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The absence of clear understanding is the basis for every knot.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a term in Buddhist psychology that can be translated as “internal formations,” “fetters,” or “knots.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Internal formations need our full attention as soon as they manifest, while they are still weak, so that the work of transformation is easy. If we do not untie our knots when they form, they will grow tighter and stronger.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In psychology, this is called resistance. We are afraid to bring into our conscious mind the feelings of pain that are buried in us, because they will make us suffer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>they are not considered in relation to our real problems, our meditation is not really very valuable or helpful. If we know how to live every moment in an awakened way, we will be aware of what is going on in our feelings and perceptions in the present moment, and we will not let knots form or become tighter in our consciousness. And if we know how to observe our feelings, we can find the roots of long-standing internal formations and transform them, even those that have become quite strong.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“suchness” is used to mean “the essence or particular characteristics of a thing or a person, its true nature.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We do not expect a person always to be a flower. We have to understand his or her garbage as well.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>realized that if I didn’t do something about the anger in me, I would transmit it to my children.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>three components: the giver, the gift, and the one who receives the gift. The giver is our parents; we are the continuation of our parents and our ancestors. The gift is our body itself. The one who receives the gift is us. As we continue to meditate on this, we see clearly that the giver, the gift, and the receiver are one. All three are present in our body. When we are deeply in touch with the present moment, we can see that all our ancestors and all future generations are present in us. Seeing this, we will know what to do and what not to do—for ourselves, our ancestors, our children, and their children.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Consciousness exists on two levels: as seeds and as manifestations of these seeds.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Each of us needs a reserve of seeds that are beautiful, healthy, and strong enough to help us during difficult moments.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Awareness of the precious elements of happiness is itself the practice of right mindfulness. Elements like these are within us and all around us. In each second of our lives we can enjoy them. If we do so, seeds of peace, joy, and happiness will be planted in us, and they will become strong. The secret to happiness is happiness itself. Wherever we are, any time, we have the capacity to enjoy the sunshine, the presence of each other, the wonder of our breathing. We don’t have to travel anywhere else to do so. We can be in touch with these things right now.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Blaming has no positive effect at all, nor does trying to persuade using reason and arguments. That is my experience. No blame, no reasoning, no argument, just understanding. If you understand, and you show that you understand, you can love, and the situation will change.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you love, you naturally act in a way that can relieve the suffering of people.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we know only our own needs and ignore the needs of the other person, we cannot love. We must look deeply in order to see and understand the needs, aspirations, and suffering of the person we love. This is the ground of real love. You cannot resist loving another person when you really understand him or her.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>True love needs understanding.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Compassion means, literally, “to suffer with.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To look deeply is to understand. Once we understand the reasons he has acted badly, our bitterness towards him will vanish, and we will long for him to suffer less. We will feel cool and light, and we can smile. We do not need the other person to be present in order to bring about reconciliation. When we look deeply, we become reconciled with ourselves, and, for us, the problem no longer exists.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We can get in touch with the refreshing, healing elements within and around us thanks to the loving support of other people. If we have a good community of friends, we are very fortunate. To create a good community, we first have to transform ourselves into a good element of the community. After that, we can go to another person and help him or her become an element of the community. We build our network of friends that way. We have to think of friends and community as investments, as our most important asset. They can comfort us and help us in difficult times, and they can share our joy and happiness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mindfulness must be engaged. Once there is seeing, there must be acting. Otherwise, what is the use of seeing?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Wealth is made of non-wealth elements, and poverty is made by non-poverty elements. It is exactly the same as with the sheet of paper. So we must be careful not to imprison ourselves in concepts. The truth is that everything contains everything else. We cannot just be, we can only inter-be. We are responsible for everything that happens around us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Real strength is not in power, money, or weapons, but in deep, inner peace.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you are a mountain climber or someone who enjoys the countryside, or the green forest, you know that the forests are our lungs outside of our bodies, just as the sun is our heart outside of our bodies. Yet we have been acting in a way that has allowed two million square miles of forest land to be destroyed by acid rain, and we have destroyed parts of the ozone layer that regulate how much direct sunlight we receive. We are imprisoned in our small selves, thinking only of the comfortable conditions for this small self, while we destroy our large self. We should be able to be our true self. That means we should be able to be the river, we should be able to be the forest, the sun, and the ozone layer. We must do this to understand and to have hope for the future.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Awareness of this fact alone can help us overcome many of our own psychological pains. Eventually our contemplations can help us see how to assist those who need our help so much.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We need harmony, we need peace. Peace is based on respect for life, the spirit of reverence for life. Not only do we have to respect the lives of human beings, but we have to respect the lives of animals, vegetables, and minerals. Rocks can be alive. A rock can be destroyed. The Earth also. The destruction of our health by pollution of the air and water is linked to the destruction of the minerals. The way we farm, the way we deal with our garbage, all these things are related to each other.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We cannot just blame one side or the other. We have to transcend the tendency to take sides.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I asked the leaf whether it was frightened because it was autumn and the other leaves were falling. The leaf told me, “No. During the whole spring and summer I was completely alive. I worked hard to help nourish the tree, and now much of me is in the tree. I am not limited by this form. I am also the whole tree, and when I go back to the soil, I will continue to nourish the tree. So I don’t worry at all. As I leave this branch and float to the ground, I will wave to the tree and tell her, ‘I will see you again very soon.’”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What we need are people who are capable of loving, of not taking sides so that they can embrace the whole of reality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I asked the question, how could people live like this when things are like that? But if you stay in Paris for ten years without being in touch, you find it normal. Meditation is a point of contact. Sometimes you do not have to go to the place of suffering. You just sit quietly on your cushion, and you can see everything. You can actualize everything, and you can be aware of what is going on in the world. Out of that kind of awareness, compassion and understanding arise naturally, and you can stay right in your own country and perform social action.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All systems of thought are guiding means; they are not absolute truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Avoid being narrow-minded and bound to present views. Learn and practice non-attachment from views in order to be open to receive others’ viewpoints. Truth is found in life and not merely in conceptual knowledge. Be ready to learn throughout your entire life and to observe reality in yourself and in the world at all times.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As soon as anger or hatred arises, turn your attention to your breathing in order to see and understand the nature of your anger or hatred and the nature of the persons who have caused your anger or hatred.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>9 Do not say untruthful things for the sake of personal interest or to impress people. Do not utter words that cause division and hatred. Do not spread news that you do not know to be certain. Do not criticize or condemn things that you are not sure of. Always speak truthfully and constructively. Have the courage to speak out about situations of injustice, even when doing so may threaten your own safety.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>14 Do not mistreat your body. Learn to handle it with respect. Do not look on your body as only an instrument. Preserve vital energies for the realization of the Way. Sexual expression should not happen without love and commitment. In sexual relationships, be aware of future suffering that may be caused. To preserve the happiness of others, respect the rights and commitments of others. Be fully aware of the responsibility of bringing new lives into the world. Meditate on the world into which you are bringing new beings.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The next morning when the sun was in the sky, she discovered something beautiful. She saw the blue sky for the first time. She had never noticed it before. She had only been interested in clouds, and she had missed seeing the sky, which is the home of all the clouds. Clouds are impermanent, but the sky is stable. She realized that the immense sky had been within her heart since the very beginning. This great insight brought her peace and happiness. As she saw the vast wonderful blue sky, she knew that her peace and stability would never be lost again.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Take the hand of your child and invite her to go out and sit with you on the grass. The two of you may want to contemplate the green grass, the little flowers that grow among the grasses, and the sky. Breathing and smiling together—that is peace education. If we know how to appreciate these beautiful things, we will not have to search for anything else. Peace is available in every moment, in every breath, in every step.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
