<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>condensō [en]</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Giacomo Mantani</name>
        <email>name.surname on gmail</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2021-02-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Davening (Schachter-Shalomi, Rabbi Zalman)</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2021-02-18-davening.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2021-02-18-davening.html</id>
    <published>2021-02-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#davening">Davening</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1355843320l/15893573.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="davening">Davening</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>We need that skepticism for quality assurance, because fooling oneself is easy. This is why I so love the statement in Psalm 34:9, “Taste and see that God is good.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if an insight emerges for you, take a few quiet moments to daven it in. And may you, too, as so many holy ones have before, experience the vision of prayer in your mind’s eye, the living taste of prayer in your heart, and the deep and gentle glow of prayer in your soul.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Deuteronomy 26:17–18, which speak of a reciprocal relationship between us and God. The verb used to capture this relationship is aleph-mem-resh. In the simple form this means “to say,” but here—uniquely in Torah—it is used in a transitive form: he’emarta and he’emirkha. God “says” us, and we “say” God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Just as I heard it said to me in a whisper, so I told it to you in a whisper” (Genesis Rabbah 3:4).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The imaginal world is a real world. Real things happen in the imaginal world that affect this world in turn.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>prayer begins with kavanah. To daven with kavanah means to pray with focus, intention, meaning. It means praying from the heart, rather than prayer centered solely in the mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kavanah is not attained in a day. We start small and build patiently on every small success. But if we aim our actions and our davening toward a godly place, we will get there.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I can’t do this without Your help.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Dear God, please help me to let this thought go.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>), wisdom to yield ko’ach mah (), the power of “What?”—the wisdom of getting to know what a thing is. Wise Mind seeks to understand the mitzvah lifnai ve-lifnim, inside and out. He wants to do the mitzvah in a completely integrated and organic way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“duties of the heart,” in Bachya ibn Pakuda’s famous phrase,3 cannot be fulfilled without conscious and deliberate intention.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Saying the words without intent is clearly unsatisfactory; on the other hand, saying every word and syllable with full and true kavanah is close to impossible.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My entire life and everything I do are nothing but God Godding Godself as Zalman. The best thing I can do, then, is to make my life a good ride for God, to consciously devote my actions to that purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The awareness that we stand in the presence of the Living God is one of the most important realizations we can install in our operative consciousness. God is always present. The question is, how present are we? We want to stand in that Presence without opacity. Our work is to penetrate, in meditation and in action, to the very heart of being nokhach penei ha-Shem (Lamentations 2:19), of being truly present before God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Meister Eckhart was trying to express when he wrote, “The eye with which I see God is the same eye with which God sees me. My eye and God’s eye are one eye, one sight, one knowledge, and one love.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>meditating on the Tetragrammaton, the letters of God’s mysterious name, can open a channel to bring down the holy. As in Vipassana or pranayama, we can use our breathing to help us get there. Your lungs without breath are like the yud, the smallest letter, the vanishing point. Our inhalation forms the hey, letter of breath: hhhhhhh. At the top of the breath we form the vav, straight as an erect backbone. Then we breathe out—hhhhhhh—another hey. So we invite YHVH to come down and dwell within us. As Jews we are concerned about living in this world. Ours is not primarily an Ein Sof focus, a preoccupation with the world beyond the beyond, but a Gaia focus. Our fundamental kavanah is not to leave the world behind but to bring God into this world, to create the “Kingdom of heaven” in the life we live, right here and now.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Yir’ah, awe, is sometimes translated as fear, but neither completely captures the idea. The Hebrew root of yir’ah is yud-resh-aleph . The root of words meaning sight or to see is resh-aleph-hey . Yir’ah arises from the state of being seen for what we really are.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The awareness that we are being seen, that we do everything we do in the presence of that Witness—that is the true path to and meaning of yir’ah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The disciple says, “Master, I couldn’t find a place where no One can see me.” The awareness that we are being seen, that we do everything we do in the presence of that Witness—that is the true path to and meaning of yir’ah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If I ascend to heaven, there You are; if I make my bed in hell, You are there” (Psalm 139:8).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Proverbs 3:6, “Be-khol derakhekha da’eihu, Know God in all your ways.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>important forms of consciousness maintenance, of kavanah watching kavanah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If I knew it, I would be it; if I were it, I would know it.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>le-khaven el ha-matarah, to aim at the bull’s-eye. (Le-khaven is from the same root as kavanah, kaf-vav-nun.) This is a useful metaphor. When I finally embrace a matarah—a bull’s-eye, a target for my existence—and I say, “Yes, I will go with that, I will collaborate with that, I will invest myself in that,” then my embracing becomes a kavanah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>olam ha-ba—not “the world to come,” as the phrase is usually translated, but a world that is, at this very moment, becoming in us and around us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I come with a scroll-book on me,” says the psalmist, “in which there is one thing written”—like a journal, in which you declare its purpose on page one. This is what the scroll says: “My only desire is to do Your will. I want Your teaching in my very kishkes” (Psalm 40:8–9). This is my intent. This is what I want to do. I’m not there yet, but I’m on my way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>At the heart of kavanah lies the question: Why? Hebrew has two different words for why, madu’a and lamah, and each has a slightly different emphasis. Madu’a asks, “Mah yadu’a? What is known to us?” Philosophers might call this the what of etiology. It wants to know about origins and causes. Lamah asks, “Le-mah? What for?” This is the why of teleology. It asks: Where are we going with this? What is the goal? The why at the heart of kavanah is not only the madu’a of origins but the lamah of ultimate purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Every locksmith has a master key with which he can open many doors. Neginah is such a key, for it can unlock all doors.” Why? Because a niggun sung in the proper way is like doing teshuvah, like a moment of true repentance and turning to God. The wellsprings of niggun and teshuvah are the simple yearnings of the heart that we all share.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The word nusach can mean both text and melody.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>nusach can also mean the melody or musical mode of a given time and place, which is what I mean here. Nusach conveys information.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nusach also conveys emotion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The ga’agu’im or longing niggunim that raise up these unspoken questions can create a sacred space that all can share.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes the heart wants to daven, and the mind starts arguing. But, as the great cantor and educator Max Helfman said once, “you can’t argue with a song or a dance!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Maybe “the work is not upon you to finish” (Pirkei Avot 2:21). Someone else may complete your tune someday.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>with the emotions that you hear behind the words.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>emotional landscapes—sometimes within a single paragraph.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A niggun is a path to God, a “song of ascension.” But we must set out along that path! We must travel with that intention in mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>True prayer is like the iceberg: little that is visible on the surface, much that happens below.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the invitation to prayer says “come as you are.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>our souls accept only one outcome when it comes to prayer: transformation. We do not wish just to spin our mental wheels: We want to be changed. We want to be moved. We want to end in a better place than where we started. Our souls yearn for this. If we really mean the words we say, how can we help but be moved?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>prayers as a journey through four different landscapes, four distinct facets of human experience: physical, emotional, intellectual, and spiritual. Each facet has its own character; each communicates in its own language; each speaks to a different part of us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Asiyah is the realm of the practical and the sensible—the stuff we apprehend with our senses. We’re packing for our spiritual journey here, grounding ourselves in our physical bodies and in the here and now.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Yetzirah, on a human level, is the world of feelings, the world of passion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The language here is plural. In Yetzirah, the realm of emotions and love, the boundaries between ourselves and others begin to feel permeable</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I’m attracted to you in Asiyah! I love you in Yetzirah!” She’s saying, “Meet me in Beriyah.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In Beriyah, the language is no longer immanent but transcendent. Beriyah is the place of Wow, the place of wonder. We praise and give thanks for the constant and miraculous regeneration by a Creator who “renews, each day and always, the work of creation.” This is not the big bang understanding, in which a single event set the rest of the universe in motion. It is a mystical vision of the entire world being created anew in every instant. A person who sees the universe with such eyes can welcome each and every moment as a new opportunity for praise. In Beriyah, we are still in the group, but what the group does at this stage is to give you a matrix in which to do your individual work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>An important part of davening is to just sit be-nachat ru’ach, in serenity of spirit, and to allow for that to come in.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The word Atzilut refers to something that is noble, high, beyond. The world of Atzilut transcends our level of understanding. Boundaries are gone, definitions are gone. Individual words and thoughts are gone. We ourselves do not exist. Being as we know it has ceased.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kabbalistic tradition imagines us davening the Amidah in the world of Atzilut.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So never mind the achievements and attainments; just talk like a friend to God about what you are really concerned about. If a thought comes, turn it into a prayer. These heartfelt prayers are the ones that are really important; these are the prayers we save for Atzilut, sending them directly to the highest level. I start by saying the introductory verse: “Adonai sefatai tiftach u-fi yagid tehilatekha, Please God, open my lips and let my mouth declare Your praise.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When a concern comes up for anything, turn it into a bakashah, a request. Then set is aside and go back to stillness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Each dimension of ourselves—physical, emotional, intellectual, spiritual—has its own needs and speaks its own language. I don’t want to leave any part of me out. I want my davening, my spiritual life and practice, to integrate them all. How can this holy conversation be real unless my entire self is engaged?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We cannot think our way to God. We cannot reach God by a safe, step-by-step process.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we limit God to the ultimate abstraction, then whom are we praying to? But if instead we come at this from a Yetzirah heart space, that changes everything. If we attune ourselves to Yetzirah, the language of the davening makes sense, and all the stuff that we’re talking about here make sense. The feeling that we’re “doing the divine thing” makes sense—that’s why I like the term davening best, to describe what we’re doing at prayer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Where in this many-layered universe does compassion reside? Who is the You of God for you?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All we need are feelings that we want to share with the listening presence of the universe. If you are not yet used to praying, start by expressing yourself in your own words.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>how much time they had. I got some flak</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Voice arouses kavanah,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Daven so your heart can feel what your lips are saying!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Every breath will praise Yah” (Psalm 150:6). We can use this as a meditation with the YHVH, the Tetragrammaton. First empty your lungs and contemplate the yud, the smallest Hebrew letter, closest to emptiness. Then you breathe in, making a hhhhh sound; that’s the first hey. You hold the breath for a moment, sending it to all six directions in your body—that’s the vav, the sixth letter of the alphabet. Then you breathe out, hhhhh, to make the other hey. So we can use this prayer to scan our lung capacity and check in with our breath.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Barukh ha-Shem—thank God. At last! Now I am free just to sit and enjoy. I don’t need to run; I don’t need to make, do, fix, or change. For one day, I can just be.” If we pause from running through our day to offer a prayer, we find that we have created a little piece of Shabbos</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Throughout the centuries, the payyetanim—Jewish writers of spiritual poetry (piyyut, piyyutim)—have sought new ways of declaring their love for God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ashkenazi siddurim have “Ahavah rabbah ahavtanu” in the morning prayers and “Ahavat olam beit Yisrael amkha ahavtah” in the evening prayer. Chabad and some of the Sepharad siddurim, however, follow the Ari, who saw an important kavanah in the first letters of ahavat olam ahavtanu: aleph (1) + ayin (70) + aleph (1) add up to 72, a number the kabbalists saw as a permutation of YHVH: yud = 10; yud hey = 15; yud hey vav = 21; yud hey vav hey = 26. And 10 + 15 + 21 + 26 = 72.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we study Torah, may we see clearly what is meant for us to know. When we do Mitzvot, may all our feelings sit harmonious in our heart. Focus all our hearts’ longing on that moment, when we stand in Your Presence, in awe and adoration.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>harder to grasp than it sounds. The Tikkunei Zohar marvels, “You are One, but not in the sense of enumeration”—not “one” as an alternative to two, three, or four, but a Unity of infinite existence and infinite potential.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>asking for what we truly need is the hardest part of prayer. We throw up all sorts of obstacles.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whom am I praying to? I am praying to God, however I understand and experience that word right here and right now. I may not be praying to the God that is All, but simply sharing my tsuris with the face of God with which I am most intimate. Perhaps I am praying to whatever it is that listens in the universe. I don’t need to do any more than that. Who am I to ask for anything? I am a creation and manifestation of godliness. I am a wave in the ocean and a world unto myself. The infinite potential for creativity and love in the universe manifests in me and through me, as it does in every other creature. And will it help? We know some parents pray with all their hearts for a child to be cured of a life-threatening disease, and yet the little one dies. We pray daily for peace, yet we are still at war. Prayer is not a switch with which we can control the universe. But I do believe that we can, with our prayers, reach dimensions of existence that we do not otherwise have access to and that the openings in those higher worlds bring blessings down to us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A prayer truly prayed is the beginnings of its own answer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“O God, open up my lips, and let my mouth speak Your praise.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This first sentence reminds us that prayer begins with silence. Think back to the silence that follows the last, enlarged dalet of the Shema statement’s final ECHAD. This is not a silence of absence but a silence full of the presence of the One, a silence of infinite potential.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we want our prayers to be answered, we have to make sure not to hang up the phone too quickly.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>During the week, you can take a piece of notepaper and a pencil. Reflect for a few moments after your davening and see what comes down. “So what do I have to do today, Ribbono shel olam?” Write down what comes to you, and try to refer to it during the day or before you go to sleep at night.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I begin in Asiyah, putting on my tallis and tefillin first, creating the prayer space that I need. I check in with my body, and I say Asher Yatzar, acknowledging the miracle of the limbs and organs that sustain me. Then I look out of the window and see the world outside, the people and the buildings and the trees, the sun or the rain or the snow, and I say, “Thank You, Ribbono shel olam, all of these are wonderful, and I thank You.” I want to spend a little time in Yetzirah if I possibly can, giving my emotions a voice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I know that without help I’m not going to make it. I close with the Amidah’s final thought: “Oseh shalom, just as in the heavens everything works out as it should, so please, bring peace and tranquility upon us as well.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the first task before us is to empty ourselves of our expectations—to free ourselves of the hold they have over us. I always quote Swami Satchidananda, who would say, “Don’t make any appointments, you won’t have any dis-appointments!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Dear God, whatever jealousies and resentments I might harbor in my heart, please remove this judgment from me.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Reb Pinchas of Koretz, the great Hasidic master, wondered how we can pray for other people to become better. Are we not depriving that person of their choice and free will? The answer, he says, is that we are all part of each other. You are in me, and I am in you. Praying for the “you in me” to be better—the “you” that resides in my heart—somehow helps the “me in you” to do something good for you, and the “you in you” to become better. This is not a moral vision but an organismic vision. On a prayerful level, we are all part of each other and of the greater whole.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If I am not for myself, who will be? But if I am only for myself, what am I?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>aleph-mem-nun, meaning to be firm or trustworthy. Amen means “So be it. May your words come to pass.” It is prayer and affirmation in one.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Sleep</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-08-16-sleep.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-08-16-sleep.html</id>
    <published>2017-08-16T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-08-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#sleep">Sleep</a><ul>
<li><a href="#pre-sleep-routine">Pre Sleep Routine</a></li>
<li><a href="#post-sleep-routine">Post Sleep Routine</a></li>
<li><a href="#nap">NAP</a></li>
<li><a href="#quotes">Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="sleep">Sleep</h1>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1471745675l/31566948.jpg" />

</div>
<ul>
<li>It is better to think about quality rather than quantity when dealing with sleep. Quality can be determined not only when your are asleep, your routine while you are awake is important too.</li>
<li>Try to improve one step at a time. Little progresses make big differences.</li>
<li>Our biological clocks are regulated by external stimuli such as:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>sunlight</li>
<li>temperature</li>
<li>meal time</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Circadian rhythms work also without external stimuli</li>
<li>Homeostatic pressure determine our need to sleep. This need start when we wake up and keep increase while we are awake.</li>
<li>During night we attain the more efficient sleeping time near 2-3am (twelve hours later there is a compensation time span, it is really common for most of us to feel drowsy.</li>
<li>Light stimulate seratonin production, a neurotransmitter that increase well being and which melatonin is a derivative.</li>
<li>Blue light, dring the day as beneficial effects such as increase performance and reflexes. It is also reduce melatonin levels. It is a bad habit use blue light during the night as you might expect. Professor Idzikowsky define consequences of that bad habit (blue light from monitors before going to sleep) “junk sleep”. It is self explanatory.</li>
<li><p>In literature exist <code>3</code> chronotypes:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>He who go to sleep and get up early (<strong>AM</strong>)</li>
<li>He who go to sleep and get up late (<strong>PM</strong>)</li>
<li>He who stay between <strong>1</strong> and <strong>2</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>Check out the online quiz and <a href="https://www.bioinfo.mpg.de/mctq/core_work_life/core/introduction.jsp">find what is your chronotype</a> (thanks to University of Monaco).</p></li>
<li>Melatonina is a hormone that is produced by the pineal gland. It regulate your need to go to sleep.</li>
<li>Caffeine is a central nervous system stimulant. It is the world’s most widely consumed psychoactive drug. Unlike many other psychoactive substances, it is legal and unregulated in nearly all parts of the world. It reversibly blocks the action of adenosine on its receptor and consequently prevents the onset of drowsiness induced by adenosine. Caffeine also stimulates certain portions of the autonomic nervous system. Optimal dose for athletes is <code>3-6</code> milligrams per kilograms of body mass. It is a half-life that can be arrive up to six hours. <em>Use caffeine as a power boost, not as a substance that you need in order to do the minimum.</em></li>
<li>Stop waking up late during the weekend, try to keep your morning routine as much as possible.</li>
<li>Is is proven that <code>90</code> minutes is the range needed to pass through each sleep phases. The more important are:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><strong>light sleep</strong>: in which information are consolidated and motor skills performance increase.</li>
<li><p><strong>deep sleep</strong>: brain produce delta wave, the least frequency wave emitted (where we are awake brain produce beta waves that have an higher frequency). More deep sleep the better. We have the most beneficial effects and one of them is the production of growth hormone.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>born new cells, fix tissue and leave a feeling of renewal.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><strong>REM (Rapid Eye Movement)</strong>: dreaming phase, here the mind trick us with dreams while the body is paralyzed. Studies report that <strong>REM sleep increase creativity</strong>.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>It is not possible to get back lost sleep. Try to go to bed early or sleep for too long is time wasted. Our body is able to adapt, if you want to recover something, focus on keep your routine without too much worrying.</li>
<li>Keep a fix time to wake up is the best method we have to increase our sleeping quality.</li>
<li>Focus on <strong>cycles</strong> per night. A cycle is <strong>90 minutes of sleep</strong>.</li>
<li>Try to find out how many cycles are best suite for us. If for example we have seen that we need <code>5</code> cycles per night, we must try to not have three consecutive nights with less cycles. It is really important to find out <strong>How many cycles we need to feel restful and increase our daily routine performance</strong>. We must be ready to feel our body and mind responses while change cycles per night. Try at least for a week before switch.</li>
<li>Do not think that sleep can only be done only monophasically. In a time window of 24 hours there are other opportunities to compensate a poor night sleep.</li>
<li>Our biggest problem is psychological. Common bias that we need <code>8</code> hours of sleep per night is a real beast. It is difficult now think that <code>4.30</code> is enough.</li>
<li>When we get older, our sleep habit shift one bit at a time from a monophasic to a polyphasic sleep.</li>
<li>Sleep on your side is the recommended position. Better if your slave side, because is the side least used so less sensible. In addition, the dominant side can be think as “the reactive” side that can help you defense against attacks while sleeping (in order to sleep well we need to feel secure).</li>
<li>Try to use your bedroom only for sleeping activities.</li>
<li>“<em>Mouth breathing increase the number of sleep apnoea as well as probability to snore.</em>” - Patrick McKeown <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26533127-the-oxygen-advantage">The Oxygen Advantage</a></li>
<li>You can find if you have a good mattress if while you are on your side, the distance between the mattress and your head is less than two fist.</li>
<li>Double bed, as the word say <strong>must</strong> be at least <code>180</code> centimeters (width). Lesser the space we have higher is the probability to disturb our or our partner sleep. Sleep with someone else have benefits <strong>pre</strong> and <strong>post</strong> sleep. In an ideal world, we only [pre/post]sleep together.</li>
<li>Duvet optimal values: <code>13,5</code> tog during winter, <code>4,5</code> tog during summer, <code>9,0</code> tog during autumn and spring. In hot summer obviously we can use only a duvet cover or nothing at all.</li>
<li>Bedroom best practices:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>minimal forniture, cleaned space and color neutral.</li>
<li>can be totally overshadowed (use a night mask can be bothersome, we must be as free as possible).</li>
<li>temperature should be between <code>16-18</code> celsius degree.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Use your bed only for sleeping.</li>
<li>Try to avoid a bottle of water near the bed. Think: why do you need it? If you wake up with a dry throat probably is because you are breathing with your mouth while sleeping. If you wake up in order to go to the bathroom, maybe you have drink too much before sleep. In addition keep a bottle of water near your bed, let your mind think about it during night, with higher probability to think you need a sip.</li>
<li>The best alarm clock is a sunrise simulator. A device useful not only for whom suffering SAD (Seasonal Affective Disorder) but for everyone that try to wake up with a “sunrise”. A sunrise simulator has beneficial brain and body effects in addition to emotional feelings and well being.</li>
<li>Benefits that come with <strong>R90 program</strong> (all tips mentioned above and below) become effective only in addition to good nutrition and body exercises. Tackle these three problems together and each one enhance benefits to the rest. Your life surely will be better.</li>
<li>Tryptophan is an α-amino acid that is used in the biosynthesis of proteins. It is essential in humans, meaning the body cannot synthesize it and thus it must be obtained from the diet (fish, banana, dried fruit). Tryptophan is also a precursor to the neurotransmitter serotonin and the hormone melatonin. Sport athletes use <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1082898/">Montmorency’s cherry</a> as bio-hacking supplement. Glyn Howatson professor of Northumbria University has lead numerous studies that prove his beneficial effects and his efficiency after an intensive physical activity. In addition Glyn proved that these black berry increase melatonin production.</li>
<li>Oregon State University stated that <code>150</code> minutes of physical training per week, enhance sleep quality by <code>65%</code>.</li>
<li>Sleeping pills can give addiction, memory loss and sleepwalking</li>
<li>Think about your sleep in a time window of <code>7</code> days. One night is not enough to draw conclusions</li>
<li><p>Usually it is more problematic to <strong>travel</strong> eastward rather than westward. Good tips are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Go to bed and get up early some days before your departure.</li>
<li>Expose to sunlight early each day and avoid it during the evening</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sunlights</strong> is a lot of more effective rather than caffeine to keep you awake and sleeping pills to make you sleep.</p></li>
<li>An unbalanced sleep, typical to shift workers can lead to different problems such as depression, immune system imbalance, increase risk for cancer, cronic cardiopathy and metabolism disorders (type 2 diabetes). It is proven that being under these changes has severe health consequences. A study done to a sample of <code>70.000</code> nurses with a time window of 22 years has proven that after 5 years of shift work, probabilities to early death increase. Play with our internal clock has consequences. Always.</li>
<li><strong>winter blues</strong>: winter tendency to slow down mood and wants. You can try to avoid winter blues trying to go out and get direct sunlight between 11am to 16pm</li>
<li>National Sleep Foundation recommend for newborns from 14 to 17 sleep hours per day. A quantity that decrease while children grow. 9 to 11 when they start to go to school and 8 to 10 at the age of fourteen.</li>
<li>Help your children to sleep well using pre and post routines and avoid/banish stimulant substances such as sugars.</li>
<li>Teenagers sleep more because is your body that need more sleep.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="pre-sleep-routine">Pre Sleep Routine</h2>
<ul>
<li>A pre-sleep routine enhance your sleeping quality. Sometimes is better to reduce sleeping time in order to do your routine. Remember that it is a way much better <strong>quality</strong> rather than <strong>quantity</strong> in sleep.</li>
<li>Keep your bedroom with fresh air (not cold) is really important.</li>
<li>Have a warm shower rise your body temperature. When you get into bed, a little colder than you, works as naturally thermal excursion. In addition a lot of people feel comfortable getting into bed clean. It is not indispensable having a full shower, a rinse is enough.</li>
<li>Intensive training during afternoon or even evening increase bloody pressure (already at his maximum levels at that time) and for that reason it is not recommended before sleep, above all for the erderly. However going for a walk, yoga, stretching or low intensive exercises are recommended because as we said earlier rising your body temperature before sleeping can help.</li>
<li>Soften all surroundings is another tip. Switch off lights or keep them low, if possible choose lights with a warm color temperature.</li>
<li><p>Recommended activities:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Have a shower</li>
<li>Tidy up</li>
<li>Writing (thoughts, appointments, TODOs for the next day, stoic diary, …)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote></li>
<li>You might eat at least <code>3</code> hours before going to sleep. It is possible to have a snack but only before your pre-sleep routine (that is around <code>90</code> minutes).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="post-sleep-routine">Post Sleep Routine</h2>
<ul>
<li>Post sleep routine enhance our efficiency during the day.</li>
<li>If you wake up and your mouth is dry probably you breath throughout your mouth while asleep. Conversely if your mouth is wet, you are using your nose to breathe.</li>
<li>Cortisol (steroid hormone released in response to stress and low blood-glucose concentration) has his maximal level soon after your wake up time. It is useful start your day with relaxing activities, such as meditation, yoga, daily journal, reading…</li>
<li>When you wake up, get direct sunlight, it enhance our clarity of mind, it balance our biological clock and it prepare our body to switch from melatonin production to serotonin production.</li>
<li>Avoid un-healthy snacks (with too much sugar or difficult to digest).</li>
<li>If it is possible, have breakfast outdoor or at least in a room with a lot of sunlight. If outside the sun is not rise yet, switch on an artificial natural light.</li>
<li>It is a good habit doing some exercises, both high or low intensive. Having a walk, yoga, Taiji..</li>
<li>Easy mental activities such as listen to the radio, iron some clothes, tidy up, read and fix something are welcome.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="nap">NAP</h2>
<ul>
<li><em>Nap with steroids</em>: assume caffeine before having your nap boost results. <strong>NB</strong> (the desired effects arise approximately <code>30</code> minutes after consumption).</li>
<li>It is not necessary to have perfect conditions. You can make a nap while you are in a sitting position.</li>
<li>It is not important if you fall asleep or not. It is important that you take advantage of this resting time, <em>“switching off”</em> your brain.</li>
<li>Find a way to rest. Rest improve your efficiency and concentration, it is scientifically proven.</li>
<li>In addition, switching off your brain reduce stress and keep your productivity high during all day.</li>
<li>If you sleep (<code>1</code> cycle, <code>90</code> minutes, or more) during the day, it is preferred to choose between (<code>13-15</code>, <code>1pm-3pm</code>) and (<code>17-19</code>, <code>5pm-7pm</code>). The first one is better because is like the night period between <code>2am</code> and <code>3am</code> where the circadian stimulus is at his higher rate.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>We do not really know what sleep is. This may be upsetting for outsiders. - <a href="https://profiles.stanford.edu/philippe-mourrain?tab=bio">Philippe Mourrain</a></p>
<p>Breakfast is the most important meal. Period.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://sleepspecialist.co.uk/site-info-old/chris-idzikowski-1">Chris Idzikowski</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26533127-the-oxygen-advantage">The Oxygen Advantage</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1082898/">Montmorency’s cherry</a></li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>La Grande Via</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-05-29-grandevia.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-05-29-grandevia.html</id>
    <published>2017-05-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-05-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#la-grande-via">La Grande Via</a><ul>
<li><a href="#diet">Diet</a></li>
<li><a href="#exercise">Exercise</a></li>
<li><a href="#meditation">Meditation</a></li>
<li><a href="#other-hints">Other hints</a></li>
<li><a href="#quotes">Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="la-grande-via">La Grande Via</h1>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://www.lagrandevia.it/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/lagrandevia-berrino-fontana.jpg" style="width:50.0%" />

</div>
<h2 id="diet">Diet</h2>
<ul>
<li>Stop eat before being full.</li>
<li>Fasting is a good habit. Do not eat few and often. Stomach needs to rest.</li>
<li>Eat until 3/4 full.</li>
<li>People can live eating 1/4, with other 3/4 live doctors.</li>
<li>TRF (Time Restricted Feeding) is lowering by 30% Kcal income per meal.</li>
<li><p>Fast 2 or 3 times a week. It is considered fasting:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Eat raw/cooked vegetables (avoid potatoes) with dressing such as olive oil (1 tbs per meal a day), lemon or vinegar No cereals, fruits or proteins.</li>
<li>Keep your stomach at rest at least 14 to 16 hours a day.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Have a bit of hungry is good, our body produces an hormone called Ghrelin. Ghrelin gene products have several actions on acute and chronic inflammation and autoimmunity.</li>
<li>Best breakfast time slot is between 7am to 9am</li>
<li>Buckwheat can be used to make cornmeal mush</li>
<li>Rye has lower glycemic load</li>
<li>Soybean has more proteins than parmigiano</li>
<li>Legumes raise HDL levels, you must eat them at least 2 or 4 times a week</li>
<li>Raw rice and lentils is a balance dish</li>
<li>Use malts and almond/hazelnut/sesame cremes together. Malts have high glycemia index but do not have fructose. Eat them with healthy fat as almon/hazelnut/sesame cremes decrease glucose absorption time. It useful eat them with legumes also.</li>
<li>Daily salt upper bound: 2,4g</li>
<li>Do not give sugar (in every form) to babies until 2 years old. White sugar if possible NEVER.</li>
<li>Mother feeding during pregnancy will be liked to her baby too</li>
<li>Eat fish 1 or 2 times a week</li>
<li>Eat fruits or jasmine Tea as dessert</li>
<li>Cultivate enhance health, Okinawa people are a living example</li>
<li><em>Nan kuru nai sa</em> - Everything will be OK</li>
<li>Pesco-vegetarians have much higher health levels (stats)</li>
<li>Calcium, tea, coffee, cocoa inhibits iron and zinc assimilation. Food with high levels of iron and zinc are grain cream, tahin, soy, azuki beans. Fermentation, sprouting and long leavening are practices that keep nutrients more assimilable</li>
<li>Vitamin D help calcium absorption. Calcium can be found in high quantities into turnip greens, cabbage (40-60% in comparison to only 30% in cow milk), legumes (eg: soy), figs.</li>
<li>In order to assimilate as much as possible nutrients from lettuce, use olive oil as dressing and add wild herbs such as lemon balm, mint, marjoram.</li>
<li>Pan-fry (with olive oil) vegetables in order to better assimilate carotenoids. Carotenoids:
<ul>
<li>alpha e beta carotene: green leaf or yellow vegetables</li>
<li>lycopene: tomatoes, peanuts</li>
<li>beta criptoxantina: pumpkin</li>
<li>lutein: cabbage</li>
<li>capsanthin: chili pepper, red pepper, paprika</li>
<li>crocin: saffron</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Vegetables must be eaten both raw and cooked (pan-fry or in hot water or steamed) Pan-fry cabbage enhance his nutrients, same with onion.</li>
<li>Garlic is better squashed. It releases chemical nutrients as defense mechanism.</li>
<li>Olive oil is useful to prevent thrombosis</li>
<li><p>Almonds and hazelnuts both raw or toasted reduce LDL</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="exercise">Exercise</h2>
<ul>
<li>Aerobic exercises for heart and lungs are walking, jogging, running, cycling, dancing, swimming and skiing</li>
<li>Doing exercises increase mitochondria levels (power and speed)</li>
<li>Benefits from exercises shade after 24-48 hours, keep your training session inside this time slot</li>
<li>Exercises and weight loss increase HDL levels</li>
<li>Exercises produce catepsina B useful in cognitive functions and memory</li>
<li>Heart rate upper bound is: 220 - age</li>
<li>HIT(High Interval Training) = switch between high intensive exercises (60s 90/85% max heart rate) with resting periods (60s). Do it 10 times per row Do not exceed 5/10 minutes of work. Metabolic effects are the same as long training sessions of aerobic exercises (100 minutes)</li>
<li>Exertion, feeding, alcohol, sleep and sex need caution</li>
<li>Exhale while lifting</li>
<li>Do not stay too much seated, change your posture often</li>
<li>Stretching! After some time passed seated and before exercises. It increase muscle grow, oxygenation and movement awareness</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="meditation">Meditation</h2>
<ul>
<li>“OM” vibes inhibit limbic system, it is responsible in controlling emotions</li>
<li>You don’t need to be in a temple or have particular things, nothing will follow you up</li>
<li><p>Yoga stages (by Patañjali):</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>External
<ul>
<li>Yama (passions)</li>
<li>Niyama (emotions)</li>
<li>Asana (know and keep healthy your body)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Breathing
<ul>
<li>Pranayama</li>
<li>Pratyahara</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Meditation (dharana, dhyana, samadhi)</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>Yoga and martial arts are good for kids:</p>
<ul>
<li>enhance ideas and planning</li>
<li>inhibit irrelevant informations and suppress their impulses</li>
<li>change and adapts behaviours</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Ataraxia = imperturbable spirit</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="other-hints">Other hints</h2>
<ul>
<li>Vitamin D is really important. During summer 5-15 minutes of direct sunlight are enough. For a much longer exposure sunscreen is needed. During winter before 10am and after 4pm UVB ray can’t go beyond ozone layer. It is useful sunbathing between 10am and 4pm. A dietary supplement of 800-1000 UI per day can be helpful (in winter).</li>
<li>Amory Lovins, expert in energy efficiency. He also wrote an interesting book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/12742309-reinventing-fire">Reinventing Fire</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Eat breakfast like a king, lunch like a prince, and dinner like a pauper.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Breakfast is for you, lunch to be shared and dinner gifted.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Fasting is the best cure, our doctor inside- Filippo Paracelso</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Meditation must start with the body. The body is the vehicle of himself, you need to control it in order to really meditate - Iyengar</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>A life without research is a life wasted</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Sky roads can be seen without looking out the windows</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Only in finite is expressed infinite and in time the eternal.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Watch your thoughts, they become words; watch your words, they become actions; watch your actions, they become habits; watch your habits, they become character; watch your character, for it becomes your destiny. - Frank Outlaw</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Happiness is also a way of interpreting the world, since while it may be difficult to change the world, it is always possible to change the way we look at it. - Matthieu Ricard</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>If something make you angry, think about what is more important: that thing or your health? In a moment, if you are wise enough, angry vanished. - Cao Tingdong</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>In cultivating body, mind and spirit it is necessary to keep in mind: be friendly, loyal and with broadminded. Not too much happy for praises nor too much angry for blames.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.lagrandevia.it/la-grande-via/">La grande via</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52036.Siddhartha">Siddharta</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/67896.Tao_Te_Ching">Tao te chin - Lao Tzu</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2340397.The_Philosophy_of_Spinoza">The philosophy of spinoza - Ratner J</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Longevity-Life-Preservation-Chinese-MING/dp/753772606X">Gong Ting Xian - Longevità e preservazione della vita</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun_Simiao">Sun Simiao</a></li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Armi, acciaio e malattie. Breve storia del mondo negli ultimi tredicimila anni</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-04-21-armi-acciaio-malattie.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-04-21-armi-acciaio-malattie.html</id>
    <published>2016-04-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-04-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#armi-acciaio-e-malattie-breve-storia-del-mondo-negli-ultimi-tredicimila-anni-diamond-jared">Armi, acciaio e malattie: Breve storia del mondo negli ultimi tredicimila anni (Diamond, Jared)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1409315304l/9549612.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="armi-acciaio-e-malattie-breve-storia-del-mondo-negli-ultimi-tredicimila-anni-diamond-jared">Armi, acciaio e malattie: Breve storia del mondo negli ultimi tredicimila anni (Diamond, Jared)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>«I destini dei popoli sono stati cosí diversi a causa delle differenze ambientali, non biologiche, tra i popoli medesimi».</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>la storia non è una semplice «collezione di fatti», uno dopo l’altro, come direbbe un cinico. La storia presenta fenomeni su larga scala che devono essere individuati</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>sei gruppi di cause: il clima, la geologia, l’orografia, le risorse marine, l’estensione, l’isolamento.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In generale, a popolazioni numerose e affollate corrispondeva un livello piú complesso e raffinato di civiltà,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>una popolazione numerosa e densa non tutti sono obbligati a coltivare la terra, perché c’è un surplus alimentare che può servire a mantenere gli strati sociali non produttivi.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>la Polinesia è un esempio convincente dell’importanza delle diversità ambientali nello sviluppo delle società umane. Ne deduciamo però che queste influenze possono essere importanti (come è stato per l’appunto in Polinesia), non che sono universali. È lecito ripetere gli stessi discorsi per i continenti? E se sí, quali sono le differenze ambientali da prendere in considerazione, e quali sono i loro effetti?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In questo libro le date comprese negli ultimi 15 000 anni sono tutte calibrate, il che può spiegare l’apparente discrepanza con quelle citate in altri testi sull’argomento.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In breve, l’agricoltura e l’allevamento comparvero in modo spontaneo in poche aree del pianeta, con tempi assai diversi, e si diffusero da questi nuclei originari in due modi: tramite l’apprendimento delle tecniche da parte dei popoli confinanti, o con l’invasione da parte dei primi agricoltori – e anche questo avvenne in momenti assai diversi nelle varie parti del mondo. In alcune aree in cui le condizioni climatiche erano favorevoli, tuttavia, l’agricoltura non nacque mai spontaneamente, né fu portata in tempi preistorici, e l’uomo vi continuò a vivere per millenni come cacciatore e raccoglitore fino a quando non venne in collisione con il mondo moderno. I popoli che divennero agricoltori per primi si guadagnarono un grande vantaggio sulla strada che porta alle armi, all’acciaio e alle malattie: da allora, la storia è stata una lunga serie di scontri impari tra chi aveva qualcosa e chi no.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Tutti questi esempi dovrebbero convincerci che il passaggio all’agricoltura e all’allevamento non coincide sempre con l’abbandono del nomadismo a favore della vita sedentaria.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Le mandorle sono un esempio lampante. Quasi tutte le mandorle selvatiche contengono un composto chimico assai amaro chiamato amigdalina, che a sua volta si scinde e dà luogo al velenosissimo cianuro:</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Tra le piante coltivate i cui progenitori sono immangiabili o velenosi troviamo i fagioli di Lima, i cocomeri, le patate, le melanzane e i cavoli;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Alcuni individui possono produrre frutti senza essere impollinati, il che ci dà banane, uva, arance e ananas senza semi; certi ermafroditi insufficienti possono diventare sufficienti e cominciare ad autoimpollinarsi, come avviene per prugne, pesche, mele, albicocche e ciliege;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>semi oleosi, si diversificarono ancora di piú: furono selezionati di volta in volta per le foglie (le verze), gli steli (i cavoli rapa), i germogli (i cavolini di Bruxelles) o le infiorescenze (i cavolfiori e i broccoli).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>tecnica dell’innesto, messa a punto in Cina molto tempo dopo la nascita dell’agricoltura.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>le cui ghiande sono sempre state mangiate dagli indiani d’America, e hanno rappresentato la salvezza per molti contadini europei in tempo di carestia. Le ghiande sono nutrienti, ricche di amido e di oli; come molte altre bacche hanno una componente tannica amara, ma abbiamo imparato ad aggirare l’ostacolo macinandole e mischiandole all’acqua,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>l’einkorn, il farro e l’orzo – avevano come ulteriore bonus il fatto di essere assai ricche di proteine (tra l’8 e il 14 per cento), molto piú dei cereali del Nuovo Mondo e della Cina (mais e riso).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mark Blumler, un geografo che studia la distribuzione mondiale delle erbacee. Blumler si è concentrato sulle 56 specie dal seme piú grosso (le piú utili all’uomo, come sappiamo), quelle il cui seme pesa almeno dieci volte tanto la media delle erbacee (vedi tab. 8.1</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Quali sono le caratteristiche che fanno bollare un animale come intrattabile? La risposta è nel principio di Anna Karenina: per essere domesticato un mammifero deve avere molte qualità (cosí come un matrimonio per funzionare), e basta che ne manchi una perché ogni sforzo sia destinato a esser vano.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>chi di voi è cosí ingenuo da pensare che il nostro migliore amico sia un carnivoro si vada a leggere gli ingredienti di una scatola di cibo per cani.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>al principio di Anna Karenina. Il matrimonio tra gli umani e gli animali è spesso infelice per una o piú ragioni: le abitudini alimentari, il tasso di crescita, i costumi riproduttivi, il carattere, la tendenza al panico e molte caratteristiche della loro struttura sociale. Solo poche specie garantiscono la nascita di una coppia felice, perché sono compatibili rispetto a tutti criteri visti prima.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>gli adulti sia – in maggior numero – i bambini contraggono malattie dai loro animali domestici. Molte sono semplici fastidi, ma alcune sono diventate in passato faccende molto piú serie. I peggiori killer dell’umanità nella nostra storia recente (vaiolo, influenza, tubercolosi, malaria, peste, morbillo e colera) sono sette malattie evolutesi a partire da infezioni degli animali, anche se i microbi che le causano sono al giorno d’oggi esclusivamente caratteristici della specie umana.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>gli eserciti vincitori non erano sempre quelli meglio armati e con i migliori strateghi, ma spesso quelli che diffondevano le peggiori malattie con cui infettare il nemico.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>palma della strategia piú ingegnosa va al virus della rabbia, che si cela nella saliva dei cani inducendoli nello stesso tempo a mordere indiscriminatamente. I piú laboriosi sono invece i vermi come gli schistosomi e gli anchilostomi, che si scavano un ingresso attraverso la pelle dell’ospite che ha la sventura di passare in acque o suoli contaminate dalle feci di una vittima precedente.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Se ogni malato riesce ad infettare in media piú di un altro individuo, la strategia del batterio è efficace, anche se capita che qualcuno dei suoi ospiti muoia durante il processo.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nel corso della storia, quindi, le popolazioni esposte ripetutamente a un particolare agente patogeno hanno finito per essere composte da percentuali piú alte di individui resistenti.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Le malattie, dunque, sono un esempio di selezione naturale al lavoro, e di adattamento dei microbi a nuovi ospiti e vettori. Ma le specie sono molto diverse tra loro anche dal punto di vista biochimico e immunitario, e quindi un germe deve sviluppare notevoli mutazioni se vuole sopravvivere nel nuovo ambiente. Ci sono molti casi istruttivi in cui gli scienziati hanno potuto osservare questo processo con i loro occhi.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>permettono di stimare il numero dei nativi in circa 20 milioni. Nel complesso del Nuovo Mondo, nei due secoli successivi al 1492 la popolazione indigena scomparve per il 95 per cento. I killer piú efficaci furono i germi portati dagli europei, ai quali i nativi non erano mai stati esposti, e ai quali non avevano resistenze di tipo immunitario o genetico.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ho volutamente parlato di «strategie» e non di «forme», perché nessun sistema di scrittura segue rigidamente una delle tre. Il cinese non usa solo logogrammi, e le lingue occidentali non si limitano agli alfabeti (pensiamo ai numerali, o a simboli di uso comune come «+», «%» e cosí via, tutti segni che rappresentano un’idea e non un suono).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>La prima scrittura sumera era dunque formata da logogrammi non fonetici, cioè non basati sui suoni specifici del sumero, che avrebbero potuto esser letti in qualsiasi altra lingua pur conservando lo stesso significato – proprio come accade per il segno «4», che indica sempre il numero 4 anche se viene pronunciato four, četyre, neliä e empat rispettivamente da un inglese, un russo, un finlandese e un indonesiano.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Questo parallelo tra i sistemi mediorientali e mesoamericani testimonia come la creatività umana abbia in sé elementi di universalità. La lingua dei sumeri e quella dei maya non hanno particolari relazioni di parentela tra loro, eppure i sistemi di scrittura di entrambe si sono dovuti confrontare con gli stessi problemi: le soluzioni escogitate dai primi nel 3000 a. C. furono riscoperte dai secondi tre millenni piú tardi e dalla parte opposta del globo.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>alfa, beta, gamma…), con piccole modifiche, tra cui la sostituzione della «c» latina laddove il greco e le lingue semitiche hanno «g» (lettera, quest’ultima, che fu reinventata dai romani e messa al suo posto attuale).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>L’interpretazione piú plausibile, secondo me, è la diffusione dell’idea di base come è avvenuto con l’alfabeto cherokee: gli egizi, gli ittiti e tutti gli altri popoli sono venuti a conoscere grazie ai sumeri i principî generali della questione, e poi hanno sviluppato da soli soluzioni e forme specifiche.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Quindi l’agricoltura e la successiva, millenaria evoluzione dei gruppi umani che la praticavano furono essenziali per la nascita della scrittura, cosí come per quella delle malattie infettive. La scrittura sorse in modo indipendente solo nella Mezzaluna Fertile, in Messico e (con buone probabilità) in Cina, cioè proprio nelle aree dove l’agricoltura si sviluppò per prima, nei rispettivi emisferi. Dopo l’iniziale invenzione, per mezzo dei commerci, delle conquiste e della religione si diffuse in altre società dotate di analoghe strutture economiche e politiche.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ma gli uomini sono frenati da barriere ambientali che la «linea d’aria» non prende in considerazione.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>in tutte le piú famose e importanti invenzioni moderne c’è sempre un precursore negletto che viene oscurato dalla frase «X ha inventato Y». Si afferma, ad esempio, che «James Watt ha inventato la macchina a vapore nel 1769», ispirato – si dice – dal vapore che usciva da una teiera. Una bella storia, ma in realtà Watt ebbe l’idea decisiva mentre stava riparando un modello del motore inventato da Thomas Newcomen 57 anni prima, di cui erano stati costruiti piú di cento esemplari in Inghilterra. La macchina di Newcomen, a sua volta, era basata su quella brevettata da Thomas Savery nel 1698, a sua volta modellata su quella che il francese Denis Papin aveva disegnato ma non costruito nel 1680, a sua volta ispirata dalle idee di Christiaan Huygens e di altri scienziati. Con questo non voglio negare che i miglioramenti di Watt (tra cui la camera di condensazione separata e il cilindro a doppia corsa) rispetto a Newcomen fossero notevoli, cosí come quelli di quest’ultimo rispetto a Savery.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>la tecnologia progredisce accumulando le esperienze di molti, non per atti isolati di singoli eroi; e i suoi usi vengono quasi sempre alla luce in un secondo tempo, perché quasi mai un oggetto si inventa pensando di soddisfare specifici bisogni.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>QWERTY (o QZERTY), cosí detta perché queste sono le prime sei lettere da sinistra della prima fila. Può sembrare incredibile, ma questa disposizione dei tasti fu disegnata nel 1873 in modo da essere apposta irrazionale. È progettata in modo da rallentare il lavoro di chi la usa, perché ad esempio le lettere piú comuni sono distanti fra loro e concentrate sul lato sinistro. Questo fu fatto perché i modelli del 1873 si bloccavano se due tasti adiacenti erano battuti in rapida successione,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Concludendo, è falso che esistano continenti popolati da gruppi umani innovativi e altri abitati solo da conservatori. In ogni parte del mondo, in ogni epoca, si possono avere società aperte o chiuse al nuovo, e anche all’interno delle singole civiltà la situazione può mutare nel corso del tempo. Pensandoci bene, queste conclusioni sono proprio quelle che ci aspetteremmo di trovare se il tasso di inventiva di un popolo fosse determinato da molti fattori indipendenti, senza la conoscenza precisa dei quali non si potrebbero fare previsioni.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>le novità bisogna anche saperle mantenere, il che dipende da un buon numero di fattori imprevedibili.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Senza interscambi si acquisiscono meno invenzioni, e se ne perdono di piú.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Poiché la tecnologia genera altra tecnologia, la buona diffusione di una invenzione è forse piú importante dell’invenzione stessa. La storia delle innovazioni si può definire un processo autocatalitico, che accelera col tempo perché si alimenta e si favorisce da solo. L’esplosione scientifica e tecnica seguita alla rivoluzione industriale fu davvero notevole, ma anche quella del tardo Medioevo fu impressionante se paragonata a quella dell’Età del bronzo, che a sua volta oscurò quella del Paleolitico superiore. Un motivo per cui la tecnologia è spesso autocatalitica è che i grandi progressi dipendono dalla soluzione preventiva di problemi piú semplici. Gli uomini del Paleolitico non inventarono di punto</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>la tecnologia si alimenta da sola perché è in grado di dare origine a nuove soluzioni per combinazione di componenti.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mi sembra che si vada nella giusta direzione se si osserva che il semplice numero degli abitanti di una regione è tra i piú sicuri indicatori di complessità della medesima. Abbiamo visto che nel passaggio dalle bande alle tribú, alle chefferies e agli stati, la popolazione aumenta in modo considerevole, da poche decine fino ad almeno 50 000. Oltre a questa correlazione generale tra numero e tipo di società, se ne osserva una analoga anche all’interno delle singole categorie: le chefferies piú popolose, ad esempio, sono sempre le piú socialmente stratificate e le piú centralizzate</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>progredire dell’agricoltura che fa aumentare la popolazione e quindi nascere le società complesse, o sono queste ultime che permettono la nascita dell’agricoltura? La domanda, cosí posta, ci porta fuori strada. In realtà l’una favorisce l’altra per autocatalisi.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Queste realtà geografiche complesse hanno bisogno di organizzazioni complesse. La risoluzione dei conflitti, i processi decisionali, l’economia, lo spazio a disposizione: ecco quattro fattori che spingono le società numerose a darsi delle autorità di governo centrali. E</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>guerra e la minaccia hanno giocato un ruolo fondamentale nella formazione di quasi tutte (se non proprio tutte) le società complesse.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>L’unico animale domestico venne da fuori: il cane arrivò attorno al 1500 a. C. (presumibilmente a bordo di canoe austronesiane), e si inselvatichí diventando il dingo. Gli aborigeni catturavano i dinghi per farne animali da compagnia e da guardia, e addirittura come coperte viventi – da cui espressioni come «notte da cinque cani» per indicare una nottata molto fredda. Ma non se li mangiavano, come in Polinesia, né li usavano per la caccia, come in Nuova Guinea.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>arretratezza» dell’Australia è dovuta in parte proprio a questi fattori – isolamento e popolazione – che limitano la capacità di un popolo di inventare nuova tecnologia e di conservare quella già esistente. Gli stessi effetti hanno giocato il loro ruolo nel determinare le differenze tra il continente piú grosso (l’Eurasia) e gli altri.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Anche se una classificazione molto grossolana raggruppa tutti i cinesi nel gruppo etnico mongolico, in realtà le differenze al suo interno sono assai piú marcate di quelle, ad esempio, tra svedesi, italiani e irlandesi dentro il gruppo degli europei. I cinesi del nord e del sud sono molto diversi: i primi assomigliano ai tibetani e ai nepalesi, e sono in genere piú alti, robusti, chiari di carnagione, e dagli occhi piú «tagliati» (grazie alla cosiddetta plica epicantica); mentre i secondi sono avvicinabili ai vietnamiti e ai filippini.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>nessun altro continente può vantare la diversità umana presente in Africa.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>se non sapessimo nulla della storia mondiale, potremmo dire che la lingua inglese si è originata in America, dove c’è di gran lunga il piú folto gruppo di parlanti, ed è stata portata in Gran Bretagna e Australia dai coloni. Ma l’inglese fa parte della famiglia germanica, e tutte le altre lingue germaniche sono concentrate nell’Europa nordoccidentale. In particolare, quella piú simile all’inglese è il frisone, confinato in poche isolette sulla costa olandese e tedesca. Ecco allora che un linguista può concludere che l’inglese è nato lí, e si è poi diffuso nel mondo in seguito a grandi migrazioni. Sappiamo che è andata proprio cosí.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Gli africani usavano le noci di cola come narcotico molto prima che alla Coca-Cola venisse l’idea di usarne gli estratti per una bevanda.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>accidenti della geografia e della biogeografia a determinare l’esito finale: le differenti storie di questi due continenti dipendono in ultima analisi dal valore della loro terra.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In tutti i popoli esistono persone geniali; è solo che certi ambienti forniscono piú materiale con cui partire e condizioni piú favorevoli per continuare.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>mille altre invenzioni: c’era sempre qualche regnante che si opponeva per sue personali idiosincrasie, ma una volta che la cosa era adottata in una nazione si diffondeva alla fine in tutta Europa. In Cina accadeva l’esatto opposto. Per motivi apparentemente inspiegabili, furono banditi gli orologi, i filatoi ad acqua, e dopo la fine del XV secolo quasi tutta la tecnologia meccanica.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>la facilità di contatti ha avuto effetti sia positivi sia negativi sul progresso tecnologico. Come tendenza di lungo periodo, le aree favorite sono probabilmente quelle moderatamente collegate. L’evoluzione degli ultimi mille anni in Cina, Europa e (forse) India mostra gli effetti di una connessione rispettivamente alta, media e bassa</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>la preferenza avrebbe potuto cambiare e andare per caso a un altro tipo di tastiera: non c’era niente nell’ambiente americano che favorisse in modo intrinseco la QWERTY. Una volta presa la decisione, però, non si tornò piú indietro, e un secolo dopo i computer si ritrovarono con la stessa tastiera. Forse ragioni altrettanto banali stanno dietro al sistema in base 12 dei sumeri (a causa del quale oggi dividiamo il giorno in 24 ore, le ore in 60 minuti e cosí via), e a quello in base 20 dei maya.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>piccoli eventi quasi casuali che alla fine diventano caratteristiche permanenti.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>la radice della parola scientia sta nel verbo scire, cioè conoscere; e la conoscenza si ottiene con i metodi appropriati alle singole discipline. Ecco perché sono solidale con gli studenti di storia. Le scienze storiche intese in questo senso allargato hanno molte caratteristiche in comune che le rendono diverse dalla fisica, dalla chimica e dalla biologia molecolare. Ne isolerei quattro: metodologia, catena di cause ed effetti, previsioni e complessità.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>è difficile fare previsioni a priori (quale specie si estinguerà) senza una dettagliata conoscenza del presente. In alcuni casi si fanno previsioni su cosa i dati futuri ci potranno mostrare del passato.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I sistemi storici sono estremamente complessi, perché sono caratterizzati da un numero enorme di variabili correlate. Piccoli cambiamenti a basso livello possono avere grandi effetti ad alto livello</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ma l’introspezione ci può far conoscere molto piú sulla storia degli uomini che su quella dei dinosauri. Ecco perché sono ottimista, e penso che lo studio storico delle società umane potrà essere affrontato con metodi simili a quelli delle altre scienze. Faremo un grande regalo alla nostra società se capiremo cosa ha plasmato il mondo moderno, e cosa potrebbe plasmare il futuro.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Parlare di archeologia in Giappone è particolarmente difficile perché l’interpretazione del passato si riflette in modo diretto sulle azioni del presente.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Oggi il Giappone e la Corea sono due colossi economici che si fronteggiano ai lati dello stretto di Tsushima, guardandosi in cagnesco attraverso le nebbie dei falsi miti e delle vere atrocità passate. Questa tensione non è di buon auspicio per il futuro dell’Asia orientale. Scoprire chi sono davvero i giapponesi e come e quando si sono divisi dai loro stretti parenti coreani potrebbe essere un buon punto di partenza per stabilire un terreno comune di dialogo.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>è il paese piú piovoso al mondo tra quelli a clima temperato.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Oggi il Giappone è il primo paese al mondo per pesca, esportazione e consumo di prodotti ittici. Non mancano poi molluschi e crostacei, come vongole, ostriche, granchi e gamberi, e molte specie di alghe commestibili. Come vedremo, la ricchezza delle terre e delle acque giapponesi fu un fattore chiave nella storia di questa parte di mondo.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>La società jomon era un universo in miniatura, conservatore e isolato, quasi immutato nel corso di 10 000 anni: un’isola di stabilità circondata da un mondo in subbuglio.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>influenza culturale della Corea, che portò all’adozione del buddismo, della scrittura, dei cavalli come mezzo di trasporto e di nuove tecniche ceramiche e metallurgiche. Non si sa, però, se questa trasmissione di conoscenze avvenne grazie all’invasione della Corea da parte del Giappone (come sostengono i giapponesi) o viceversa (come pensano i coreani).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Come accade agli arabi e agli ebrei, giapponesi e coreani hanno origini comuni, ma sono bloccati da antiche inimicizie. La situazione è distruttiva per entrambi i contendenti, sia in Asia orientale sia in Medio Oriente. Anche se sono riluttanti a riconoscerlo, giapponesi e coreani sono come fratelli gemelli che hanno trascorso insieme gli anni formativi della giovinezza. Il futuro politico di quella zona del mondo dipende in gran parte dalla loro capacità di riscoprire questi antichi legami.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>principio di frammentazione ottimale», secondo il quale l’innovazione si diffonde piú rapidamente in una società che al suo interno ha un giusto grado di divisione: non troppo (come l’India) e non troppo poco (come la Cina).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Le aziende nipponiche iniziano sempre a lavorare un minuto dopo la mezzanotte, in modo che il latte immesso sul mercato possa essere etichettato come «fresco di giornata».</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>vogliamo essere innovativi e competere sul mercato, non dobbiamo organizzarci in modo troppo gerarchico/monolitico, né troppo frammentario, ma dividerci in sottogruppi in competizione interna e con un alto livello di comunicazione . Questo vale a molti livelli, per le aziende, i distretti industriali e le nazioni (come insegna il caso degli Stati Uniti e del suo sistema di governo federale).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Una lunga storia agricola e una lunga esperienza all’interno di società complesse porta a una buona tradizione di governo, a una buona gestione dell’economia e cosí via. Dal punto di vista statistico, l’effetto delle cause remote è mediato da quello della causa prossima piú nota, cioè dalla presenza di buone istituzioni. Ma l’effetto di quest’ultime non è sufficiente a spiegare la variabilità, per cui devono esistere altri fattori contingenti. Il prossimo problema da affrontare è quello di enucleare la catena delle cause e degli effetti che portano le nazioni a partire da una lunga storia di pratiche agricole e complessità sociale per approdare al benessere. Sarà piú facile, allora, insegnare ai paesi poveri a compiere lo stesso percorso.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>i temi che fanno da sfondo alla storia antica dell’umanità mi sembrano essere utili anche nello studio di molti fenomeni del mondo contemporaneo.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Brain Maker, The Power of Gut Microbes to Heal and Protect Your Brain</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-01-25-brain-maker.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-01-25-brain-maker.html</id>
    <published>2016-01-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2016-01-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#brain-maker-the-power-of-gut-microbes-to-heal-and-protect-your-brain---for-life-perlmutter-david">Brain Maker: The Power of Gut Microbes to Heal and Protect Your Brain - for Life (Perlmutter, David)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1415588147l/22875118.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="brain-maker-the-power-of-gut-microbes-to-heal-and-protect-your-brain---for-life-perlmutter-david">Brain Maker: The Power of Gut Microbes to Heal and Protect Your Brain - for Life (Perlmutter, David)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>“Let food be thy medicine and medicine be thy food.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Foods such as garlic, Jerusalem artichoke, jicama, and even dandelion greens, as well as fermented foods such as sauerkraut, kombucha, and kimchi open the door for heightened levels of health in general, and brain function and protection in particular</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The vagus nerve, the longest of the twelve cranial nerves, is the primary channel of information between the hundreds of millions of nerve cells in our intestinal nervous system and our central nervous system. Also known as cranial nerve X, it extends from the brain stem to the abdomen, directing many bodily processes that we don’t consciously control. These include such important tasks as maintaining the heart rate and controlling digestion. And it turns out that the population of bacteria in the gut directly affects the stimulation and function of the cells along the vagus nerve.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>How does the microbiome come into play? It regulates or manages the immune response. So it, in turn, takes part in the story of inflammation in your body.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The reason most of your immune system is deployed in your gut is simple: the intestinal wall is the border with the outside world. Aside from skin, it’s where your body has the most chances of encountering foreign material and organisms. And it is in constant communication with every other immune system cell in the body. If it meets a problematic substance in the gut, it alerts the rest of the immune system to be on guard.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Elevated blood sugar stirs up inflammation in the bloodstream, as excess sugar can be toxic if it’s not swept up and used by cells. It also triggers a reaction called glycation — the biological process by which sugar binds to proteins and certain fats, resulting in deformed molecules that don’t function well. These sugar proteins are technically called advanced glycation end products (AGEs). The body does not recognize AGEs as normal, so they set off inflammatory reactions. In the brain, sugar molecules and brain proteins combine to produce lethal new structures that contribute to the degeneration of the brain and its functioning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>These studies together support the crucial role of microbiota in maintaining the intestinal barrier integrity, sustaining a normal metabolic homeostasis, protecting the host from infection by pathogens, enhancing host defense systems and even influencing the nervous system in type-2 diabetes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Chinese herbal components berberine and ginseng, as well as the compounds found in tea, coffee, wine, and chocolate have anti-diabetic qualities through their effects on gut bacteria.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Dr. Fasano’s recent discovery that not only is there increased gut permeability when the gut is exposed to gliadin, a protein found in gluten, but in fact the blood-brain barrier also becomes more permeable in response to gliadin exposure.24</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>they can even produce various vitamins that are essential to brain health, including B12. It’s well substantiated that low levels of B12 are a huge risk factor for dementia, not to mention other neurological challenges such as depression.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>An important byproduct of the work done by mitochondria is the production of chemicals, related to oxygen, called reactive oxygen species (ROS). ROS are more commonly known as free radicals.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>MS patients almost always were either born by C-section, not breast-fed, or treated with antibiotics for some illness early in life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the idea that people will take a pill to treat symptoms, while the underlying disorder is ignored. So there’s never any real focus on actually curing or even improving the root cause of the illness, let alone getting people off the medication.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>High blood sugar, in fact, is one of the biggest risk factors for depression, just as it is for Alzheimer’s.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>fructose has been shown to increase circulating LPS by 40 percent.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>LPS make the gut more permeable, but it can cross the blood-brain barrier and allow pro-inflammatory chemicals to bombard the brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>cocoa, coffee, and curcumin (turmeric), for example — can have the opposite effect of lowering the risk of depression by helping balance the microbiome.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>obesity during pregnancy harms the developing fetus’s stem cells, which are responsible for creating and sustaining lifelong blood and immune-system function.5</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes; between them, these two groups make up more than 90 percent of the gut’s population. The ratio of these two groups to each other determines levels of inflammation and squarely relates to such conditions as obesity, diabetes, coronary artery disease, and inflammation in general.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>higher levels of Firmicutes changes our genetic expression, noting that this paves the way for obesity, diabetes, cardiovascular disease, and inflammation. But, as they also revealed in their study, you can change this. Just increasing dietary fiber can improve the ratio.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our cells can accept glucose only with the help of insulin, which acts like a transporter and is produced by the pancreas. Insulin shuttles glucose from the bloodstream into cells, where it can then be used as fuel. When a cell is normal and healthy, it has abundant receptors for insulin, so it has no problem responding to it. But when a cell is mercilessly exposed to high levels of insulin through a never-ending presence of glucose — caused by consuming too many carbohydrates and refined sugars — the cell does something brilliant to adapt: It reduces the number of insulin-responsive receptors on its surfaces. It’s as if the cell closes a few doors so it can’t hear insulin knocking. This ultimately causes the cell to become desensitized or “resistant” to insulin. Once a cell is insulin resistant, it’s unable to take glucose from the blood, leaving glucose in the bloodstream. As with most biological processes, there’s a “fail-safe” backup system in place. The body wants to fix this problem, as it knows it can’t have glucose loitering in the blood. So it tells the pancreas to increase production of insulin to mop up that glucose, which the pancreas dutifully does. It will continue to pump out as much insulin as needed to push glucose into cells. And higher levels of insulin are needed because the cells aren’t as responsive to insulin</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>relationship between high carbohydrate consumption and diabetes is almost indisputable.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This same outcome — a lack of satiety — is also seen with artificial sweeteners. Although we used to think that sugar substitutes like saccharin, sucralose, and aspartame didn’t have a metabolic impact because they don’t raise insulin, it turns out that they can indeed wreak tremendous metabolic havoc and cause the same metabolic disorders as real sugar.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Obviously, B. fragilis, or any other single probiotic for that matter, is not a guaranteed treatment. But I have no doubt that future therapies for autism will include probiotics, some of which might work wonders on some symptoms of autism in some patients. I also have a hunch that in the future, we’ll begin to view brain disorders like autism as mitochondrial diseases that have strong ties to the gut’s tribes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>best of all, these new therapies won’t be pharmaceutical drugs that come with side effects. They will, for the most part, come from dietary choices and probiotic treatments to rebalance the microbiome. They will be lifestyle interventions that are highly accessible and economical for everyone.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What’s empowering about this is that we can change our health’s destiny, as well as the destiny of our children’s health, if we make the right choices. Now that we have evidence to suggest that food, stress, exercise, sleep — and the state of our microbiome — affect which of our genes are activated and which remain suppressed, we can take some degree of control in all of these realms. To be sure, we may never be able to totally eradicate the possibility of autism or another brain disorder, but we can most certainly do our best to reduce the chances. And now that we know that the gut bacteria factor in somewhere, harnessing the microbiome for the benefit of the brain becomes key. What also becomes key is knowing how a good microbiome can go bad. Hence the purpose of part II.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Knowledge, after all, is power.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it has the lowest GI of all the natural sugars because the liver metabolizes most of the fructose, so it has no immediate effect on our blood-sugar and insulin levels.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I call gluten a “silent germ” because it can inflict lasting damage without your knowing it. While its effects might start with unexplained headaches and feeling anxious, or “wired and tired,” they can worsen to more dire disorders such as depression and dementia.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Gluten is made up of two main groups of proteins, the glutenins and the gliadins.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>exposure to the gliadin protein in particular increases gut permeability in all of us.5 That’s right, all humans have some degree of gluten sensitivity. Once you have a leaky gut, you’re highly susceptible to other food sensitivities in the future. You’re also vulnerable to the impact of LPS making its way into the bloodstream. Lipopolysaccharide, or LPS as you’ll recall, is a structural component of many microbial cells in the gut. If LPS gets past those tight junctions, it increases systemic inflammation and irritates the immune system — a double strike that puts you at risk for myriad brain ailments, autoimmune disease, and cancer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Although there’s a huge market now for gluten-free products, the bottom line is they are just that — products, and they can be just as junky and nutrient-poor as processed products that don’t come with a “gluten-free” claim. Many are made with refined, gluten-free grains that are low in fiber, vitamins, and other nutrients. That’s why it’s crucial to pay attention to ingredients and choose gluten-free foods that are authentic in their nutrition and wholesomeness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Based on studies of chlorine’s effects on human cells, the EPA sets the safe level in drinking water at no more than four parts per million. Even that dilution can wipe out lots of organisms, as anyone knows who has killed a goldfish using tap water. in chapter 9, I’ll offer ideas on how to avoid chlorinated water. It’s easier than you think, and you won’t have to call a plumber or invest in a water delivery service.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>changes in the array of gut bacteria can take place in as little as six days after instituting a new dietary protocol,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>coconut yogurt</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>coconut kefir,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kombucha tea.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Tempeh.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>great source of vitamin B12, tempeh</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kimchi.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sauerkraut.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Pickles.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Even setting aside the gluten factor, one of the main reasons that consuming too many grains and carbs is so harmful is that they spike blood sugar in ways other foods, such as meat, fish, poultry, and vegetables, do not.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This particular diet supplies the ingredients to nourish not only healthy biology (and thus a healthy microbiome) but also a healthy brain. A diet that keeps blood sugar balanced keeps gut bacteria balanced. A diet high in rich sources of fiber, which you’ll get from whole fruits and vegetables, feeds the good gut bacteria and produces the right balance of those short-chain fatty acids to keep the gut lining in check. A diet devoid of injurious gluten will further tip the scales in favor of healthy gut ecology as well as healthy brain physiology. And a diet that’s intrinsically anti-inflammatory is good for the gut and brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>sizeable portion of vegetables (two-thirds of your plate) and about 75 to 115g of protein.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You’ll get your fats from those found naturally in protein, from ingredients used to prepare the protein dish and vegetables, such as butter and olive oil, and from nuts and seeds.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Coffee also stimulates a specific gene pathway called the Nrf2 pathway. When this is triggered, it causes the body to make higher levels of protective antioxidants, while reducing inflammation and enhancing detoxification. Other Nrf2 activators are chocolate (another bonus for cocoa), green tea, turmeric, and resveratrol, an ingredient in red wine.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Interestingly, the effect was the same even when the alcohol was removed. The researchers also analyzed the bacterial composition of the stool of such individuals and found a significant increase in bifidobacteria. Red wine is also a rich source of those gut-loving polyphenols. Just be sure that you don’t drink too much. A glass a day for women, two for men at the most.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Prebiotics occur naturally in a variety of foods, including chicory, Jerusalem artichoke, garlic, onions, leeks, and jicama or Mexican yam;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Researchers have determined that beta-HBA, which is easily obtainable just by adding coconut oil to your diet, improves antioxidant function, increases the number of mitochondria, and stimulates the growth of new brain cells.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>No food but lots of water (avoid caffeine) for a twenty-four-hour period.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My fasting protocol is simple: No food but lots of water (avoid caffeine) for a twenty-four-hour period.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I recommend fasting at least four times a year; fasting during the seasonal changes (for example, the last week of September, December, March, and June) is an excellent practice to keep.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Louis Pasteur famously said “Chance favors the prepared mind.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Consider and then act, don’t react.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Laws of Medicine</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-12-28-laws-medicine.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-12-28-laws-medicine.html</id>
    <published>2015-12-28T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#the-laws-of-medicine-field-notes-from-an-uncertain-science-mukherjee-siddhartha">The Laws of Medicine: Field Notes from an Uncertain Science (Mukherjee, Siddhartha)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1439172237l/25409816.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="the-laws-of-medicine-field-notes-from-an-uncertain-science-mukherjee-siddhartha">The Laws of Medicine: Field Notes from an Uncertain Science (Mukherjee, Siddhartha)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>The only way to break the deadly monotony was to read. In the medieval story, a prisoner is sent to jail with just one book, but discovers a cosmos of a thousand books in that single volume.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if you had a hammer, as the saying goes, then everything looks like a nail.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sciences have laws—statements of truth based on repeated experimental observations that describe some universal or generalizable attributes of nature.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>law distills a relationship between observable phenomena that remains true across multiple circumstances and multiple conditions. Laws are rules that nature must live by. There are fewer laws in chemistry. Biology is the most lawless of the three basic sciences: there are few rules to begin with, and even fewer rules that are universal.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every diagnostic challenge in medicine can be imagined as a probability game.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a test can only be interpreted sanely in the context of prior probabilities.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This is the way we intuit the world, Bayes argued. There is no absolute knowledge; there is only conditional knowledge. History repeats itself—and so do statistical patterns. The past is the best guide to the future.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every outlier represents an opportunity to refine our understanding of illness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Inliers” allow us to create rules—but “outliers” act as portals to understand deeper laws.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Karl Popper proposed a crucial criterion for distinguishing a scientific system from an unscientific one. The fundamental feature of a scientific system, Popper argued, is not that its propositions are verifiable, but that its propositions are falsifiable—i.e., every theory carries an inherent possibility of proving it false. A theory or proposition can only be judged “scientific” if it carries within it a prediction or observation that will prove it false. Theories that fail to generate such “falsifiable” conjectures are not scientific</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The human genome has about twenty-four thousand genes in total.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every science suffers from human biases. Even as we train massive machines to collect, store, and manipulate data for us, humans are the final observers, interpreters, and arbiters of that data. In medicine, the biases are particularly acute for two reasons. The first is hope: we want our medicines to work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Doctors,” Voltaire wrote, “are men who prescribe medicines of which they know little, to cure diseases of which they know less, in human beings of whom they know nothing.” The pivotal word in this scathing description is know. The discipline of medicine concerns the manipulation of knowledge under uncertainty.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Thinking, Fast and Slow</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-12-07-thinking-fast-slow.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-12-07-thinking-fast-slow.html</id>
    <published>2015-12-07T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-12-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#thinking-fast-and-slow-kahneman-daniel">Thinking, Fast and Slow (Kahneman, Daniel)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1317793965l/11468377.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="thinking-fast-and-slow-kahneman-daniel">Thinking, Fast and Slow (Kahneman, Daniel)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>“The situation has provided a cue; this cue has given the expert access to information stored in memory, and the information provides the answer. Intuition is nothing more and nothing less than recognition.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Overconfidence is fed by the illusory certainty of hindsight. My views on this topic have been influenced by Nassim Taleb, the author of The Black Swan. I hope for watercooler conversations that intelligently explore the lessons that can be learned from the past while resisting the lure of hindsight and the illusion of certainty.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The gorilla study illustrates two important facts about our minds: we can be blind to the obvious, and we are also blind to our blindness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you know that the lines are equally long. If asked about their length, you will say what you know. But you still see the bottom line as longer. You have chosen to believe the measurement, but you cannot prevent System 1 from doing its thing; you cannot decide to see the lines as equal, although you know they are.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Not all illusions are visual. There are illusions of thought, which we call cognitive illusions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As a way to live your life, however, continuous vigilance is not necessarily good, and it is certainly impractical. Constantly questioning our own thinking would be impossibly tedious, and System 2 is much too slow and inefficient to serve as a substitute for System 1 in making routine decisions. The best we can do is a compromise: learn to recognize situations in which mistakes are likely and try harder to avoid significant mistakes when the stakes are high. The premise of this book is that it is easier to recognize other people’s mistakes than our own.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the pupil was a good measure of the physical arousal that accompanies mental effort, and we could go ahead and use it to understand how the mind works. Much like the electricity meter outside your house or apartment, the pupils offer an index of the current rate at which mental energy is used.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Any task that requires you to keep several ideas in mind at the same time has the same hurried character. Unless you have the good fortune of a capacious working memory, you may be forced to work uncomfortably hard. The most effortful forms of slow thinking are those that require you to think fast.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The psychologist Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi (pronounced six-cent-mihaly) has done more than anyone else to study this state of effortless attending, and the name he proposed for it, flow, has become part of the language. People who experience flow describe it as “a state of effortless concentration so deep that they lose their sense of time, of themselves, of their problems,” and their descriptions of the joy of that state are so compelling that Csikszentmihalyi has called it an “optimal experience.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>People who are cognitively busy are also more likely to make selfish choices, use sexist language, and make superficial judgments in social situations.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The nervous system consumes more glucose than most other parts of the body, and effortful mental activity appears to be especially expensive in the currency of glucose. When you are actively involved in difficult cognitive reasoning or engaged in a task that requires self-control, your blood glucose level drops. The effect is analogous to a runner who draws down glucose stored in her muscles during a sprint. The bold implication of this idea is that the effects of ego depletion could be undone by ingesting glucose,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if you have had to force yourself to do something, you are less willing or less able to exert self-control when the next challenge comes around. The phenomenon has been named ego depletion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when people believe a conclusion is true, they are also very likely to believe arguments that appear to support it, even when these arguments are unsound. If System 1 is involved, the conclusion comes first and the arguments follow.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Intelligence is not only the ability to reason; it is also the ability to find relevant material in memory and to deploy attention when needed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Those who avoid the sin of intellectual sloth could be called “engaged.” They are more alert, more intellectually active, less willing to be satisfied with superficially attractive answers, more skeptical about their intuitions. The psychologist Keith Stanovich would call them more rational.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As cognitive scientists have emphasized in recent years, cognition is embodied; you think with your body, not only with your brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This remarkable priming phenomenon—the influencing of an action by the idea—is known as the ideomotor effect.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>being amused tends to make you smile, and smiling tends to make you feel amused.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“act calm and kind regardless of how you feel” is very good advice: you are likely to be rewarded by actually feeling calm and kind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>reliable way to make people believe in falsehoods is frequent repetition, because familiarity is not easily distinguished from truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All this is very good advice, but we should not get carried away. High-quality paper, bright colors, and rhyming or simple language will not be much help if your message is obviously nonsensical, or if it contradicts facts that your audience knows to be true.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>performance was better with the bad font.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Zajonc argued that the effect of repetition on liking is a profoundly important biological fact, and that it extends to all animals. To survive in a frequently dangerous world, an organism should react cautiously to a novel stimulus, with withdrawal and fear. Survival prospects are poor for an animal that is not suspicious of novelty. However, it is also adaptive for the initial caution to fade if the stimulus is actually safe. The mere exposure effect occurs, Zajonc claimed, because the repeated exposure of a stimulus is followed by nothing bad. Such a stimulus will eventually become a safety signal, and safety is good.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mood evidently affects the operation of System 1: when we are uncomfortable and unhappy, we lose touch with our intuition.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the connection makes biological sense. A good mood is a signal that things are generally going well, the environment is safe, and it is all right to let one’s guard down. A bad mood indicates that things are not going very well, there may be a threat, and vigilance is required. Cognitive ease is both a cause and a consequence of a pleasant feeling.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We have norms for a vast number of categories, and these norms provide the background for the immediate detection of anomalies</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a large event is supposed to have consequences, and consequences need causes to explain them. We have limited information about what happened on a day, and System 1 is adept at finding a coherent causal story that links the fragments of knowledge at its disposal.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we are born prepared to make intentional attributions: infants under one year old identify bullies and victims, and expect a pursuer to follow the most direct path in attempting to catch whatever it is chasing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when System 2 is otherwise engaged, we will believe almost anything. System 1 is gullible and biased to believe, System 2 is in charge of doubting and unbelieving, but System 2 is sometimes busy, and often lazy. Indeed, there is evidence that people are more likely to be influenced by empty persuasive messages, such as commercials, when they are tired and depleted.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The tendency to like (or dislike) everything about a person—including things you have not observed—is known as the halo effect.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Gilbert proposed that understanding a statement must begin with an attempt to believe it: you must first know what the idea would mean if it were true. Only then can you decide whether or not to unbelieve it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>simple rule can help: before an issue is discussed, all members of the committee should be asked to write a very brief summary of their position. This procedure makes good use of the value of the diversity of knowledge and opinion in the group.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Jumping to conclusions on the basis of limited evidence is so important to an understanding of intuitive thinking, and comes up so often in this book, that I will use a cumbersome abbreviation for it: WYSIATI, which stands for what you see is all there is. System 1 is radically insensitive to both the quality and the quantity of the information that gives rise to impressions and intuitions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is the consistency of the information that matters for a good story, not its completeness. Indeed, you will often find that knowing little makes it easier to fit everything you know into a coherent pattern.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Here we encounter a new aptitude of System 1. An underlying scale of intensity allows matching across diverse dimensions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>assessment. You do that automatically whether or not you</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you often have answers to questions that you do not completely understand, relying on evidence that you can neither explain nor defend.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>How to Solve It: “If you can’t solve a problem, then there is an easier problem you can solve: find it.” Pólya’s heuristics are strategic procedures that are deliberately implemented by System 2.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The dominance of conclusions over arguments is most pronounced where emotions are involved.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“people are not adequately sensitive to sample size.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we are prone to exaggerate the consistency and coherence of what we see. The exaggerated faith of researchers in what can be learned from a few observations is closely related to the halo effect, the sense we often get that we know and understand a person about whom we actually know very little.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if you follow your intuition, you will more often than not err by misclassifying a random event as systematic. We are far too willing to reject the belief that much of what we see in life is random.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>anchoring effect. It occurs when people consider a particular value for an unknown quantity before estimating that quantity. What happens is one of the most reliable and robust results of experimental psychology: the estimates stay close to the number that people considered—hence the image of an anchor.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The conclusion is clear: anchors do not have their effects because people believe they are informative.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My advice to students when I taught negotiations was that if you think the other side has made an outrageous proposal, you should not come back with an equally outrageous counteroffer, creating a gap that will be difficult to bridge in further negotiations. Instead you should make a scene, storm out or threaten to do so, and make it clear—to yourself as well as to the other side—that you will not continue the negotiation with that number on the table.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>general, a strategy of deliberately “thinking the opposite” may be a good defense against anchoring effects, because it negates the biased recruitment of thoughts that produces these effects.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You are always aware of the anchor and even pay attention to it, but you do not know how it guides and constrains your thinking, because you cannot imagine how you would have thought if the anchor had been different (or absent). However, you should assume that any number that is on the table has had an anchoring effect on you, and if the stakes are high you should mobilize yourself (your System 2) to combat the effect.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kunreuther also observed that protective actions, whether by individuals or governments, are usually designed to be adequate to the worst disaster actually experienced.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The world in our heads is not a precise replica of reality; our expectations about the frequency of events are distorted by the prevalence and emotional intensity of the messages to which we are exposed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Slovic has challenged the foundation of their expertise: the idea that risk is objective. “Risk” does not exist “out there,” independent of our minds and culture, waiting to be measured. Human beings have invented the concept of “risk” to help them understand and cope with the dangers and uncertainties of life. Although these dangers are real, there is no such thing as “real risk” or “objective risk.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every parent who has stayed up waiting for a teenage daughter who is late from a party will recognize the feeling. You may know that there is really (almost) nothing to worry about, but you cannot help images of disaster from coming to mind. As Slovic has argued, the amount of concern is not adequately sensitive to the probability of harm; you are imagining the numerator—the tragic story you saw on the news—and not thinking about the denominator. Sunstein has coined the phrase “probability neglect” to describe the pattern. The combination of probability neglect with the social mechanisms of availability cascades inevitably leads to gross exaggeration of minor threats, sometimes with important consequences.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>mechanism through which biases flow into policy: the availability cascade.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Anchor your judgment of the probability of an outcome on a plausible base rate. Question the diagnosticity of your evidence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>individuals feel relieved of responsibility when they know that others have heard the same request for help.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Changing one’s mind about human nature is hard work, and changing one’s mind for the worse about oneself is even harder.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Subjects’ unwillingness to deduce the particular from the general was matched only by their willingness to infer the general from the particular.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You are more likely to learn something by finding surprises in your own behavior than by hearing surprising facts about people in general.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>rewards for improved performance work better than punishment of mistakes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>correlation and regression are not two concepts—they are different perspectives on the same concept. The general rule is straightforward but has surprising consequences: whenever the correlation between two scores is imperfect, there will be regression to the mean. To</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In order to conclude that an energy drink—or any other treatment—is effective, you must compare a group of patients who receive this treatment to a “control group” that receives no treatment (or, better, receives a placebo).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>general limitation of the human mind is its imperfect ability to reconstruct past states of knowledge, or beliefs that have changed. Once you adopt a new view of the world (or of any part of it), you immediately lose much of your ability to recall what you used to believe before your mind changed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In other words, people who spend their time, and earn their living, studying a particular topic produce poorer predictions than dart-throwing monkeys who would have distributed their choices evenly over the options. Even in the region they knew best, experts were not significantly better than nonspecialists. Those who know more forecast very slightly better than those who know less. But those with the most knowledge are often less reliable. The reason is that the person who acquires more knowledge develops an enhanced illusion of her skill and becomes unrealistically overconfident.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first lesson is that errors of prediction are inevitable because the world is unpredictable. The second is that high subjective confidence is not to be trusted as an indicator of accuracy (low confidence could be more informative).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Several studies have shown that human decision makers are inferior to a prediction formula even when they are given the score suggested by the formula!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The situation has provided a cue; this cue has given the expert access to information stored in memory, and the information provides the answer. Intuition is nothing more and nothing less than recognition.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>intuition cannot be trusted in the absence of stable regularities in the environment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when a project ends reasonably well: once you understand the main conclusion, it seems it was always obvious.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>how can we evaluate the probable validity of an intuitive judgment? When do judgments reflect true expertise? When do they display an illusion of validity? The answer comes from the two basic conditions for acquiring a skill: an environment that is sufficiently regular to be predictable an opportunity to learn these regularities through prolonged practice</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the likelihood that something will go wrong in a big project is high.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>people who have information about an individual case rarely feel the need to know the statistics of the class to which the case belongs. When we were eventually exposed to the outside view, we collectively ignored it. We can recognize what happened to us; it is similar to the experiment that suggested the futility of teaching psychology. When they made predictions about individual cases about which they had a little information (a brief and bland interview), Nisbett and Borgida’s students completely neglected the global results they had just learned. “Pallid” statistical information is routinely discarded when it is incompatible with one’s personal impressions of a case. In the competition with the inside view, the outside view doesn’t stand a chance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Bent Flyvbjerg, now at Oxford University, offered a forceful summary: The prevalent tendency to underweight or ignore distributional information is perhaps the major source of error in forecasting. Planners should therefore make every effort to frame the forecasting problem so as to facilitate utilizing all the distributional information that is available.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>for failing to allow for difficulties that they could not have anticipated—the unknown unknowns.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>call it theory-induced blindness: once you have accepted a theory and used it as a tool in your thinking, it is extraordinarily difficult to notice its flaws. If you come upon an observation that does not seem to fit the model, you assume that there must be a perfectly good explanation that you are somehow missing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You just like winning and dislike losing—and you almost certainly dislike losing more than you like winning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The slope of the function is steeper in the negative domain; the response to a loss is stronger than the response to a corresponding gain. This was the explanation of the endowment effect that Thaler had been searching for. And the first application of prospect theory to an economic puzzle now appears to have been a significant milestone in the development of behavioral economics.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>paper titled “Bad Is Stronger Than Good,” summarized the evidence as follows: “Bad emotions, bad parents, and bad feedback have more impact than good ones, and bad information is processed more thoroughly than good. The self is more motivated to avoid bad self-definitions than to pursue good ones. Bad impressions and bad stereotypes are quicker to form and more resistant to disconfirmation than good ones.” They cite John Gottman, the well-known expert in marital relations, who observed that the long-term success of a relationship depends far more on avoiding the negative than on seeking the positive. Gottman estimated that a stable relationship requires that good interactions outnumber bad interactions by at least 5 to 1.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Loss aversion refers to the relative strength of two motives: we are driven more strongly to avoid losses than to achieve gains.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Animals, including people, fight harder to prevent losses than to achieve gains. In the world of territorial animals, this principle explains the success of defenders. A biologist observed that “when a territory holder is challenged by a rival, the owner almost always wins the contest—usually within a matter of seconds.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>von Neumann and Morgenstern introduced in 1944. They proved that any weighting of uncertain outcomes that is not strictly proportional to probability leads to inconsistencies and other disasters.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My experience illustrates how terrorism works and why it is so effective: it induces an availability cascade.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The psychology of high-prize lotteries is similar to the psychology of terrorism. The thrilling possibility of winning the big prize is shared by the community and reinforced by conversations at work and at home. Buying a ticket is immediately rewarded by pleasant fantasies, just as avoiding a bus was immediately rewarded by relief from fear. In both cases, the actual probability is inconsequential; only possibility matters. The original formulation of prospect theory included the argument that “highly unlikely events are either ignored or overweighted,” but it did not specify the conditions under which one or the other will occur, nor did it propose a psychological interpretation of it. My current view of decision weights has been strongly influenced by recent research on the role of emotions and vividness in decision making. Overweighting of unlikely outcomes is rooted in System 1 features that are familiar by now. Emotion and vividness influence fluency, availability, and judgments of probability—and thus account for our excessive response to the few rare events that we do not ignore.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>People overestimate the probabilities of unlikely events. People overweight unlikely events in their decisions. Although overestimation and overweighting are distinct phenomena, the same psychological mechanisms are involved in both: focused attention, confirmation bias, and cognitive ease.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The common feature of these poignant stories is that they involve unusual events—and unusual events are easier than normal events to undo in imagination.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>An abnormal event attracts attention, and it also activates the idea of the event that would have been normal under the same circumstances.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Losses are weighted about twice as much as gains in several contexts: choice between gambles, the endowment effect, and reactions to price changes. The loss-aversion coefficient is much higher in some situations. In particular, you may be more loss averse for aspects of your life that are more important than money, such as health. Furthermore, your reluctance to “sell” important endowments increases dramatically when doing so might make you responsible for an awful outcome.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You can also take precautions that will inoculate you against regret. Perhaps the most useful is to be explicit about the anticipation of regret. If you can remember when things go badly that you considered the possibility of regret carefully before deciding, you are likely to experience less of it. You should also know that regret and hindsight bias will come together, so anything you can do to preclude hindsight is likely to be helpful. My personal hindsight-avoiding policy is to be either very thorough or completely casual when making a decision with long-term consequences. Hindsight is worse when you think a little, just enough to tell yourself later, “I almost made a better choice.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the emotion evoked by a word can “leak” into the final choice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But the experience was not actually ruined, only the memory of it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What we learn from the past is to maximize the qualities of our future memories, not necessarily of our future experience. This is the tyranny of the remembering self.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Tastes and decisions are shaped by memories, and the memories can be wrong.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>story is about significant events and memorable moments, not about time passing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Duration neglect is normal in a story, and the ending often defines its character. The same core features appear in the rules of narratives and in the memories of colonoscopies, vacations, and films. This is how the remembering self works: it composes stories and keeps them for future reference.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“You seem to be devoting your entire vacation to the construction of memories. Perhaps you should put away the camera and enjoy the moment, even if it is not very memorable?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Csikszentmihalyi calls flow—a state that some artists experience in their creative moments and that many other people achieve when enthralled by a film, a book, or a crossword puzzle: interruptions are not welcome in any of these situations.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>focusing illusion, which can be described in a single sentence: Nothing in life is as important as you think it is when you are thinking about it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We believe that duration is important, but our memory tells us it is not.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Humans, unlike Econs, need help to make good decisions, and there are informed and unintrusive ways to provide that help.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The way to block errors that originate in System 1 is simple in principle: recognize the signs that you are in a cognitive minefield, slow down, and ask for reinforcement from System 2.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Power of Full Engagement</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-08-15-fullengagement.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-08-15-fullengagement.html</id>
    <published>2015-08-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-08-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#the-power-of-full-engagement-managing-energy-not-time-is-the-key-to-high-performance-and-personal-renewal-loehr-jimschwartz-tony">The Power of Full Engagement: Managing Energy, Not Time, is the Key to High Performance and Personal Renewal (Loehr, Jim;Schwartz, Tony)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1431760957l/68985._SY475_.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="the-power-of-full-engagement-managing-energy-not-time-is-the-key-to-high-performance-and-personal-renewal-loehr-jimschwartz-tony">The Power of Full Engagement: Managing Energy, Not Time, is the Key to High Performance and Personal Renewal (Loehr, Jim;Schwartz, Tony)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>Human beings are complex energy systems, and full engagement is not simply one-dimensional. The energy that pulses through us is physical, emotional, mental, and spiritual.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We, too, must learn to live our own lives as a series of sprints—fully engaging for periods of time, and then fully disengaging and seeking renewal before jumping back into the fray to face whatever challenges confront us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As Nietzsche put it, “That which does not kill us makes us stronger.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The power of rituals is that they insure that we use as little conscious energy as possible where it is not absolutely necessary, leaving us free to strategically focus the energy available to us in creative, enriching ways.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Too much energy expenditure without sufficient recovery eventually leads to burnout and breakdown. (Overuse it and lose it.) Too much recovery without sufficient stress leads to atrophy and weakness. (Use it or lose it.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Cultures that encourage people to seek intermittent renewal not only inspire greater commitment, but also more productivity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are oscillatory beings in an oscillatory universe. Rhythmicity is our inheritance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Expanding capacity requires a willingness to endure short-term discomfort in the service of long-term reward.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“We can experience pleasure without any investment of psychic energy, whereas enjoyment happens only as a result of unusual investments of attention . . . ,” writes psychologist Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi, author of Flow. “The best moments [in our lives] usually occur when a person’s body or mind is stretched to its limits in a voluntary effort to accomplish something difficult and worthwhile.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the key to expanding capacity is both to push beyond one’s ordinary limits and to regularly seek recovery, which is when growth actually occurs.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The most important rhythms in our lives are the ones we typically take for granted—most notably breathing and eating.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>simplest antidotes to anger and anxiety is to take deep abdominal breaths.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>researchers found that a series of short doses of intense aerobic activity—each one sixty seconds or less—followed by complete aerobic recovery, had a profound positive impact on participants. In a period of just eight weeks, the subjects exhibited significant improvements in cardiovascular fitness, heart-rate variability and mood.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Rigorous training improves a person’s ability to perform on the battlefield. . . . The concept of stress inoculation is very much like the concept of preventing a particular disease through vaccination. Like immunization, which occurs only when the vaccine is given in the proper dosage, stress inoculation occurs only when the stress intensity is at the optimal level—high enough to activate a person’s psychological and biological systems, but low enough so as not to overwhelm them. If the stress level is not high enough, inoculation will not occur; if the stress level is too high, stress sensitization will occur, and the individual will probably perform less effectively when he is stressed again.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Snowden discovered that those nuns whose writing expressed a preponderance of positive emotions (happiness, love, hope, gratitude and contentment) tended to live longer and more productive lives.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Researchers such as Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi have found that prolonged television watching is actually correlated with increased anxiety and low-level depression. Conversely, the richer and deeper the source of emotional recovery, the more we refill our reserves and the more resilient we become. Effective emotional renewal puts us in a position to perform more effectively, especially under pressure.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To be fully engaged emotionally requires celebrating what the Stoic philosophers called anacoluthia—the mutual entailment of the virtues. By this notion, no virtue is a virtue by itself. Rather, all virtues are entailed. Honesty without compassion, for example, becomes cruelty. We are, in effect, the sum of our complexities and contradictions. Practically, we must focus on building emotional capacity wherever it is that we are most out of balance. The ultimate goal is to move more freely and flexibly between our own opposites.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The brain represents just 2 percent of the body’s weight, but requires almost 25 percent of its oxygen.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The greatest geniuses,” da Vinci told his patron, “sometimes accomplish more when they work less.” In his Treatise on Painting, da Vinci wrote, “It is a very good plan every now and then to go away and have a little relaxation. . . . When you come back to the work your judgment will be surer, since to remain constantly at work will cause you to lose the power of judgment.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Five stages are now widely recognized: first insight, saturation, incubation, illumination and verification.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The quantity of energy we have to spend at any given moment is a reflection of our physical capacity. Our motivation to spend what we have is largely a spiritual issue.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Some activities generate considerable spiritual renewal without demanding significant energy expenditure. These include walking in nature, reading an inspirational book, listening to music, or hearing a great speaker. Spiritual practices, by contrast, can be renewing and demanding at the same time. Meditation, for example, requires mobilizing highly focused attention to quiet the mind, but may also prompt a rejuvenating experience of expansive openness, connectedness and even joy. Like yoga, meditation is a practice that can cut across all dimensions, building spiritual capacity while also providing mental and emotional recovery.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>all service to others, which involves considerable effort and even inconvenience, but may also provide a profound source of meaning and deep satisfaction.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The irony is that self-absorption ultimately drains energy and impedes performance. The more preoccupied we are with our own fears and concerns, the less energy we have available to take positive action. Subordinating our self-interest to something beyond ourselves may feel threatening at first, but as Gary discovered, it can also be immensely rewarding—a means by which to experience a deeper sense of meaning and greater self-worth. The commitment to live according to our deepest values not only creates a more stable center in our lives but also helps us to better navigate the challenges we face along the way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nietzsche’s famous words, “He who has a why to live for can bear with almost any how.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we learned that visualizing a performance challenge in advance is a very effective way to allay anxiety and to perform without awkwardness or self-consciousness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Wade Roofs has defined spirituality as “knowing our deepest selves and what is sacred to us.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Arthur Ashe once put it: “From what we get in life, we make a living. From what we give, we make a life.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>emotions such as fear, anger and even hatred can be a powerful source of energy. The problem is the cost. As we saw earlier, negative emotions drain energy and prompt the release of hormones that are toxic to our systems over time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes it’s more important to stay connected with people than to be right.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we feel more passion for and derive more pleasure from doing what we freely choose and most enjoy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>capitolo <em>molto</em> bello. Deepest purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Purpose becomes a more powerful and enduring source of energy when its source moves from negative to positive, external to internal and self to others.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we aren’t investing energy in protecting our turf, we have the potential to see more of the truth and to continue to learn and grow.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We can derive as much value from studying and understanding our failures as we can from celebrating and reinforcing our successes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“What amazes me most,” Roger told us, “is that once my values became clear and I got the hang of building rituals, most of the changes I made weren’t that hard. My life acquired a certain rhythm. I can feel how much my energy has rubbed off on the people in my life. My challenge now is just to feel the pulse and keep the beat.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Eureka Factor</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-06-25-the-eureka-factor.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-06-25-the-eureka-factor.html</id>
    <published>2015-06-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-06-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#the-eureka-factor-creative-insights-and-the-brain-kounios-johnbeeman-mark">The Eureka Factor: Creative Insights and the Brain (Kounios, John;Beeman, Mark)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1423184765l/23210114.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="the-eureka-factor-creative-insights-and-the-brain-kounios-johnbeeman-mark">The Eureka Factor: Creative Insights and the Brain (Kounios, John;Beeman, Mark)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>The ultimate goal of Zen is “satori,” which Japanese scholar D. T. Suzuki explained as “acquiring a new viewpoint for looking into the essence of things.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Flynn effect”—startled the world: Average raw scores have been increasing. The worldwide “new normal” has been getting better and better. We don’t yet know for sure why this is happening, but the numbers don’t lie. People are getting smarter. Aren’t they?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Fire wasn’t just the problem—it was also the solution. He fought fire with fire. The conceptual restructuring that produces an insight can be relatively simple—in Dodge’s case, a straightforward inversion—or it can be a lens for viewing subtler relationships.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Analogical thinking solves a problem by revealing a deep relationship between two things that appear very different from each other on the surface. Insights aren’t the only way to experience an analogy. You can deliberately try to construct one. But when you spontaneously realize that one situation is similar to another, you’ve had an analogical insight.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The answer appeared when he took a break from work to enjoy a baseball game.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The difficulty lies, not in the new ideas, but in escaping from the old ones, which ramify, for those brought up as most of us have been, into every corner of our minds. —John Maynard Keynes, preface to The General Theory of Employment, Interest, and Money (1935)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Everything you do has the potential to limit what you do next.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Everything you do has the potential to limit what you do next. Everything you think has the potential to limit what you think next. And you won’t even know that this is happening.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The fact is that you are the sum total of your experiences, even fleeting ones. Your past informs your assumptions, beliefs, and expectations but also limits your ability to think and act flexibly.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This is how experts get better results while thinking less, not more.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That’s why you shouldn’t even attempt to consider all your options and possibilities. You can’t. If you tried to, then you’d never get anything done. So don’t knock the box. Ironically, although it limits your thinking, it also makes you smart. It helps you to stay one step ahead of reality. But also remember that your box isn’t perfect. It can’t enable you to anticipate everything, because doing so would mean that your brain would have to be as complex as the world around you. For those occasions when your box is insufficient, you have insight as a way to break out of an old box and swap it for a new and improved one.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Einstein’s razor”: “Everything should be made as simple as possible, but no simpler.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The notes I handle no better than many pianists. But the pauses between the notes—ah, that is where the art resides. —Artur Schnabel, pianist</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Just as your ability to use language requires two intact hemispheres, so does effective, practical, creative performance. But the right hemisphere provides the spark that ignites the creative fire.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Aspects of sleep stages can persist for a while. Descartes’s insight may have been the product of a conscious mind still under the partial influence of the last phase of the previous night’s sleep.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One way that sleep can incubate ideas and promote insight is by removing blocks that prevent a weakly activated idea from becoming conscious. Cognitive psychologists call this liberation of thought “fixation forgetting.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Zeigarnik effect”: An interruption improves memory for the unfinished task; but once completed, the odds of forgetting the task suddenly increase.10</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The universe tends toward disorder. Objects fall because falling is the most disorderly and likely outcome to emerge in this complex system.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To get the maximum benefit from a break, it helps if you “change your mind”—the greater the change, the better.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Context is the key. Your memories are associated with the contexts in which you originally acquired them. If you learn something in one place, type of situation, or frame of mind, then you’ll remember that information better if you recall it later in the same context. That’s why you sometimes can’t remember the name of a person you know only from your office when you encounter that person at the shopping mall. (Cognitive psychologists call this the “butcher-on-the-bus phenomenon.”) So when you’re stuck in a rut and take a break to resolve the impasse, you’ll shed the misleading ideas more quickly and thoroughly if you think about things that transport your mind far from your current situation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Of course, actually getting away and taking a walk, especially on an unfamiliar route, would be an even better way to change context (as long as you aren’t thinking about the problem during your walk). But if you can’t get away, try thinking about getting away, to another town, another country, or, even better, another planet. Thinking about a situation far removed from your current one might have additional benefits beyond those afforded by a mental reset. When you do this, you are also exercising your ability to change perspective, which seems to be the same sort of ability that you use when you reinterpret a situation to achieve insight. Later, we’ll tell you about research that suggests that exercising this mental flexibility can, at least temporarily, boost your insightfulness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, “When I am, as it were, completely myself, entirely alone, and of good cheer—say, traveling in a carriage or walking after a good meal … it is on such occasions that my ideas flow best and most abundantly,” and other such anecdotes would seem to suggest that a positive mood enhances creative insight.3</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But the fact is that cognition and emotion are closely intertwined, even blended, in the brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“mood congruency”: If you’re sad, then you’ll tend to think of sad things, even to the point of interpreting ambiguous situations negatively. Likewise, happy people tend to have positive thoughts and interpretations. Just as our unconscious associations are filters through which we view the world and ourselves, so, too, are our moods.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This suggests that being put in a good mood enhanced his creative thinking but not his analytic thinking.8</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One is the “winner-take-all” strategy (aka “the rich get richer”). Squash or ignore the weaker, less obvious tendencies and let the strongest, most obvious one dominate. This enables a person to focus on the most straightforward path to solving a problem without detours or distractions. Just twist the jar top harder! This is the analytic mind-set. The other approach is the “Robin Hood” strategy of taking from the rich and giving to the poor—let a weaker, less-obvious tendency dominate over a stronger, more obvious one. Forget brute force—use a can opener. This is the insight mind-set.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>remote associative thinking and positive mood can’t reinforce each other indefinitely. Otherwise, a person’s positive mood and insightfulness would amplify each other in an infinite chain reaction. We know that this doesn’t happen. Every once in a while, the cycle is broken, and this can have practical benefits.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To help you achieve a creative breakthrough, do things that make you happy. Take a walk in the park. Listen to music. But after you’ve had your aha moment, fun time is over. You’ll need to analyze and refine your new idea, and a state of bliss won’t help you to be at your critical best. In this case, a mild dose of anxiety may do the trick. To regain your critical edge, go see a scary movie, ride a roller coaster, or just watch the news—whatever makes you a little nervous. A positive mood may be the best kindling for a creative spark. But once that kindling starts burning, it takes careful work to turn that spark into a useful bonfire.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Try this: Open your mouth a little and then hold a pen in place horizontally with your lips for a few seconds without clenching your teeth. How do you feel? That exercise forces you to tighten the same muscles that you use to smile, causing a tiny, easy-to-miss wave of positive emotion. The researchers used that technique to induce a subtle good mood in their participants (who were tricked by a cover story).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A positive mood energizes a person’s unconscious associations so that when she views a coherent problem, the problem’s parts prime the solution and one another more strongly, making them easier to perceive. This triggers a little burst of pleasure that she interprets as an intuition that a solution is present. It also encourages her to continue working on the problem until the solution proclaims itself in the form of an insight.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>intuitions can be caused either by bursts of positive emotion from fluency or by bursts of negative emotion from disfluency. Either way, emotional surges, whether positive or negative, seem to have their strongest influence on intuition when they occur against the backdrop of an ongoing positive mood because that’s when a person’s associations are most energized.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So mood influences intuition, but not equally for everyone.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you have an intuition, don’t make an impulsive decision to either follow or reject it. Ask yourself why you are having that hunch, at that time, and at that place. The answers to these questions will help you to decide whether to trust a particular intuition. Remember, your brain knows more than you do, but it doesn’t know everything.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“bottom-up” processing is a grassroots movement. It occurs when something in the environment grabs control of the brain, as when you reflexively attend to a loud, unexpected sound, such as a door slamming. Bottom-up processing is dominated by what’s happening in the world around you; top-down control is an expression of your goals, plans, and values.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is reason to think that creativity and mental illness are related and that they are both expressions of something that is relatively stable—one’s genes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you purposely ignore something, even briefly, it’s difficult to immediately shift mental gears and pay full attention to it, a phenomenon called “negative priming.” This can sometimes be a minor inconvenience, but it occurs for a reason. When you ignore something, it’s because you deemed it to be unimportant. By inhibiting something that you’ve already labeled as irrelevant, you don’t have to waste time or energy reconsidering it. More generally, inhibition protects you from unimportant, distracting stimuli. Without it, your thoughts would wander all over the place, even retracing previous mental steps.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>However, all things being equal, you are at your inhibitory best during your peak time. This means that you are most analytical at your peak time and most insightful at your off-peak time. For creativity, your finest hour is literally the low point of your day.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>People can voluntarily broaden or narrow their attention. This isn’t news. Wegbreit’s innovation was to show that these adjustments can influence one’s cognitive style. After the participants’ attention was either broadened or narrowed, they tackled a set of remote associates problems. Narrowing increased the number of analytic solutions; broadening increased insights.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Once your attention has been broadened or narrowed, it stays that way for a while. It doesn’t immediately snap back to its previous focus. Your attention and cognitive style are flexible, but only within limits.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Experience and the environment are important, to a point.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Innovation has nothing to do with how many R&amp;D dollars you have…. It’s not about money. It’s about the people you have, how you’re led, and how much you get it. —Steve Jobs, co-founder of Apple, Inc., quoted in Fortune magazine, November 9, 1998</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when confronted with a deadline an Insightful tends to make “errors of omission” by drawing a blank, while an Analyst’s errors are more likely to be incorrect solutions (“errors of commission”).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Since creativity flows from a promotion orientation, not prevention, creative insight will be enhanced after a prize is won, not in anticipation of one. So make your way through the maze and eat your cheese in safety. Then your mind will expand.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Thinking, as well as feeling, can energize the mental machinery that produces creative insights.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Considering long-term consequences enhances creativity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>imagining a new world by adding something enhances creative thought; taking something away improves analytic problem solving.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To entertain an additive counterfactual, you have to expand your awareness beyond your current situation to include extra things in the mix. It’s the here and now plus something. This should broaden conceptual attention and enhance insight. But when you consider a subtractive counterfactual, you have to think about the here and now minus something. This isn’t as simple as pushing the banished thing out of your mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Like love, adapting to another culture demands the cognitive flexibility to consider situations from another perspective. It involves learning to think about alternate, even opposite, interpretations of events and circumstances. (If you haven’t ever lived abroad and don’t believe this, just watch a foreign news channel or read some foreign newspapers to prove this to yourself.) It</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We’ve seen that thinking about the distant future, faraway places, different cultures, and imaginary worlds can prime you for insightfulness. This is not a laundry list of unrelated techniques for enhancing creativity. These factors are all manifestations of a single psychological principle.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>to empower creative thought, you should imagine unusual people, alternate realities, and the distant future. Think about a loved one. Take in the view—and broaden it. Visit or envision faraway places and cultures. Ponder “what spring is like on Jupiter and Mars.”6</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The key point: The right kind of training and experience may help you learn how to solve specific kinds of problems, but it won’t help you solve other types of problems, and it won’t teach you how to have insights. Real-life problems aren’t circumscribed. For an Insightful, there is no boundary between the problem and the rest of the world or the rest of one’s experience.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes, insight is the specific tool that you need. Unfortunately, it can’t be pulled out of your mental toolbox at will.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You are more likely to have creative insights and valid intuitions when your brain is in a general state characterized by remote associations, broad flexible attention, abstract thought, positive mood, a sense of psychological distance, and a promotion orientation.7</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Quick reference that help you retrieve the main concepts of the book.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>MAKING IT HAPPEN</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To put a twist on Pasteur’s famous saying, chance favors the happy mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The truly essence of the book: how to achive more insights from change your habits to choose the good environ and what should do for start it NOW.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The music is like a mask; I don’t hear it.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You can tap these same principles to design your own personal technique to maximize your own creative potential. Just be sure to test its effectiveness on yourself so that you can optimize it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You could make your dream enviroment but test it if it really works best. TEST OFTEN</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In these common situations is better train your insight mode instead focus only in be more productive.. perfect time to improve crativity without too much effort!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What time can you repurpose for creativity? Any time in which you are engaged in no task, such as when you are waiting in line, or are doing a task that demands minimal attention, like housework or gardening, can be commandeered for creative work in this way. The classic example is the isolation of the shower. Meal times are another possibility. (After all, you have to eat.) Try taking your breakfast or lunch alone in a quiet, isolated environment. Start by priming yourself for a positive mood, psychological distance, and a promotion orientation, for example, by thinking of what long-range goals would make you happy. Then let the ideas flow while you unhurriedly nibble on your meal. Thinking about a problem while doing an easy task may not be particularly convenient. However, incubating a problem while doing a simple, unrelated task can help more than incubation during either a demanding task or no task.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>thoughts about our always connected world</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>constant attention to the environment. There is continuous pressure to produce, especially during economically uncertain times. Meanwhile, many people strive to be attentive parents, spouses, partners, relatives, or friends. Leisure time is hard to come by, and it’s difficult to resist expending what there is of it on the alluring social media platforms, games, videos, gadgets, podcasts, and television channels that are constantly clamoring for our attention. Our thoughts can be interrupted by a cellphone or text message anywhere and anytime. And when the cellphone isn’t ringing and there aren’t any new text or email messages, we think about when the next call or message will arrive. The twenty-first century is all about staying connected, staying on top of things, not missing anything. This is exciting and often productive, but we need to be aware of all of its effects on us. The truth is, we live in an environment on steroids, far removed from the more relaxed pace of life just one generation ago. We are slaves to the present moment, with little opportunity for quiet introspection and mental travel. The inner world</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>default brain state, the brain space ON when you rest</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All 24/7. All enemies of the (default brain) state.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Modern life can stimulate, as well as sap, one’s insightfulness. We’ve seen that alternating between the inner and outer worlds is the best way to enhance your creativity. The impediment to achieving this balance is that the outer world keeps its thumb on the scale. The only way to compensate is by giving extra weight to the inner world and by periodically banishing its enemies.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Create the state. It’s the empire of the future.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>A Mind For Numbers (Oakley, Barbara)</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-04-29-mind-for-numbers.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-04-29-mind-for-numbers.html</id>
    <published>2015-04-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2015-04-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#a-mind-for-numbers-how-to-excel-at-math-and-science-even-if-you-flunked-algebra">A Mind For Numbers: How to Excel at Math and Science (Even If You Flunked Algebra)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1575009552l/18693655._SY475_.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="a-mind-for-numbers-how-to-excel-at-math-and-science-even-if-you-flunked-algebra">A Mind For Numbers: How to Excel at Math and Science (Even If You Flunked Algebra)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>This relaxation can allow different areas of the brain to hook up and return valuable insights. Unlike the focused mode, the diffuse mode seems less affiliated with any one area of the brain—you can think of it as being “diffused” throughout the brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“What surprises me is that we all know that mathematical equations are encrypted messages, for which you need to know the key if you want to crack the code and know what is represented. Nevertheless, we wonder why higher math is difficult to teach, and often blame the educational system or bad teachers. I think that it is similarly a bit misplaced to blame evolution</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Einstellung effect (pronounced EYE-nshtellung). In this phenomenon, an idea you already have in mind, or your simple initial thought, prevents a better idea or solution from being found.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You have to unlearn your erroneous older ideas even while you’re learning new ones.10</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>For example, a little research, self-awareness, and even self-experimentation can prevent you from being parted with your money—or even your good health—on products that come with bogus “scientific” claims.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The harder you push your brain to come up with something creative, the less creative your ideas will be.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But be wary of the idea that some people are “left-brain” or “right-brain” dominant—research indicates that is simply not true.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Befuddlement is a healthy part of the learning process. When students approach a problem and don’t know how to do it, they’ll often decide they’re no good at the subject. Brighter students, in particular, can have difficulty in this way—their breezing through high school leaves them no reason to think that being confused is normal and necessary. But the learning process is all about working your way out of confusion. Articulating your question is 80 percent of the battle. By the time you’ve figured out what’s confusing, you’re likely to have answered the question yourself!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>there are more than three hundred different known proofs of the Pythagorean theorem. As we will soon learn, technical problems and their solutions may be considered a form of poetry.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Understanding how your mind works helps you better understand the creative nature of some of your thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We learn a great deal from our failures in math and science.9 Know that you are making progress with each mistake you catch when trying to solve a problem—finding errors should give you a sense of satisfaction. Edison himself is said to have noted “I have not failed. I’ve just found 10,000 ways that won’t work.”10</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Consistency over time is key!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>blinking is a vital activity that provides another means of reevaluating a situation. Closing our eyes seems to provide a micropause that momentarily deactivates our attention and allows us, for the briefest of moments, to refresh and renew our consciousness and perspective.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“sleeping on it” before making major decisions is generally a good idea,18 and why taking vacations is important.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Learning is often paradoxical. The very thing we need in order to learn impedes our ability to learn. We need to focus intently to be able to solve problems—yet that focus can also block us from accessing the fresh approach we may need. Success is important, but critically, so is failure. Persistence is key—but misplaced persistence causes needless frustration.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It takes time to move information from working memory to long-term memory. To help with this process, use a technique called spaced repetition. As you may have guessed, this technique involves repeating what you are trying to retain, like a new vocabulary word or a new problem-solving technique, but spacing this repetition out over a number of days.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you go even further and set it in mind that you want to dream about the material, it seems to improve your chances of dreaming about it still further.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Going without sleep the night before an examination can mean that even if you are perfectly prepared, your mind is simply unable to function properly, so you do poorly on the test.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Chunking the information you deal with helps your brain run more efficiently. Once you chunk an idea or concept, you don’t need to remember all the little underlying details; you’ve got the main idea—the chunk—and that’s enough.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a bottom-up chunking process where practice and repetition can help you both build and strengthen each chunk, so you can easily gain access to it when needed. And there is a top-down “big picture” process that allows you to see where what you are learning fits in.9 Both processes are vital in gaining mastery over the material. Context is where bottom-up and top-down learning meet.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Intention to learn is helpful only if it leads to the use of good learning strategies.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When marking up the text, train yourself to look for main ideas before making any marks, and keep your text markings to a minimum—one sentence or less per paragraph.13 Words or notes in a margin that synthesize key concepts are a good idea.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Underline Marking Sottolineare if so,how!?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You don’t want to wait too long for the recall practice, so that you have to start the reinforcement of the concept from scratch every time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Merely glancing at the solution to a problem and thinking you truly know it yourself is one of the most common illusions of competence in learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A student is unlikely to make creative discoveries in any subject without a comprehensive set of facts and concepts at his or her command. There is no necessary conflict in learning concepts and facts and in thinking creatively; the two are symbiotic.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Law of Serendipity comes to play: Lady Luck favors the one who tries.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What to Do If You Can’t Grasp It If you don’t understand a method presented in a course you are taking, stop and work backward. Go to the Internet and discover who first figured out the method or some of the earliest people to use it. Try to understand how the creative inventor arrived at the idea and why the idea is used—you can often find a simple explanation that gives a basic sense of why a method is being taught and why you would want to use it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In the same amount of time, by simply practicing and recalling the material, students learned far more and at a much deeper level than they did using any other approach,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the retrieval process itself enhances deep learning and helps us begin forming chunks</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when learning any new skill or discipline, you need plenty of varied practice with different contexts. This helps build the neural patterns you need to make the new skill a comfortable part of your way of thinking.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>recalling material when you are outside your usual place of study helps you strengthen your grasp of the material by viewing it from a different perspective.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Interleaving means practice by doing a mixture of different kinds of problems requiring different strategies.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You want your brain to become used to the idea that just knowing how to use a particular problem-solving technique isn’t enough—you also need to know when to use it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There’s evidence that writing by hand helps get the ideas into mind more easily than if you type the answer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The dread of doing a task uses up more time and energy than doing the task itself.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the better you get at something, the more you’ll find you enjoy it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Procrastination is like addiction. It offers temporary excitement and relief from boring reality. It’s easy to delude yourself that the most profitable use of any given moment is surfing the web for information instead of reading the textbook or doing the assigned problems. You start to tell yourself stories.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I often find that when I cannot bring myself to start something, if I go for a quick run or do something active first, when I come back to it, it is much easier to start.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>remember that the better you get at something, the more enjoyable it can become.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You can change your reality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you find yourself avoiding certain tasks because they make you uncomfortable, there is a great way to reframe things: Learn to focus on process, not product.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Multitasking is like constantly pulling up a plant. This kind of constant shifting of your attention means that new ideas and concepts have no chance to take root and flourish. When you multitask while doing schoolwork, you get tired more quickly. Each tiny shift back and forth of attention siphons off energy. Although each attention switch itself seems tiny, the cumulative result is that you accomplish far less for your effort. You also don’t remember as well, you make more mistakes, and you are less able to transfer what little you do learn into other contexts.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you feel muzzy or featherbrained as you’re trying to look away and recall a key idea, or you find yourself rereading the same paragraphs over and over again, try doing a few situps, pushups, or jumping jacks. A little physical exertion can have a surprisingly positive effect on your ability to understand and recall. Try doing something active now, before recalling the ideas of this chapter.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Generating (that is, recalling) the material helps you learn it much more effectively than simply rereading it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>THE LAW OF SERENDIPITY Remember, Lady Luck favors the one who tries. So don’t feel overwhelmed with everything you need to learn about a new subject. Instead, focus on nailing down a few key ideas. You’ll be surprised at how much that simple framework can help.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Highlighting should be avoided because, at least in my experience, it provides only an illusion of competence. Retrieval practice is far more powerful. Try to get the main ideas of each page you are reading cemented in your mind before you turn the page.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s normal to sit down with a few negative feelings about beginning your work. It’s how you handle those feelings that matters.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Writing the list before you go to sleep enlists your zombies to help you accomplish the items on the list the next day.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Eat your frogs first thing in the morning.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>like pulling weeds or sweeping the kitchen. These aren’t generally my favorite kinds of tasks, but somehow, because I’m using them as diffuse-mode breaks, I often look forward to them. Mixing other tasks up with your learning seems to make everything more enjoyable and keeps you from prolonged and unhealthy bouts of sitting.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Planning your quitting time is as important as planning your working time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s important to transform distant deadlines into daily ones. Attack them bit by bit. Big tasks need to be translated into smaller ones that show up on your daily task list. The only way to walk a journey of a thousand miles is to take one step at a time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“When I was younger, I thought that if I didn’t get something immediately, it meant I would never be able to get it, or I wasn’t smart. That isn’t true at all, of course. Now I understand that it’s really important to get started on something early, leaving time for it to digest. This leads to stress-free understanding that makes learning a lot more enjoyable.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We develop a passion for what we are good at. The mistake is thinking that if we aren’t good at something, we do not have and can never develop a passion for it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>(I’m not kidding about the “close your eyes” part—remember, that can help disengage you from your previous thought patterns.9</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s worth reemphasizing that world-class experts in a variety of disciplines reveal that their path to expertise wasn’t easy. They slogged through some tedious, difficult times to get to their current level of expertise where they can glide by and make it all look easy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But memorization of key facts is essential since it is these facts that form the seeds for the creative process of chunking! The important lesson is that we must continue jiggling and playing mentally with things we have memorized in order to form chunks.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>See Joshua Foer’s masterful TED talk for a demonstration of the memory palace technique for remembering speeches.6</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>They help remind you that meaning is important for remembering, even if the initial meaning is wacky. In short, memorization techniques remind you to make what you learn in your life meaningful, memorable, and fun.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Theories describe and deal with the world on its own terms and must stand on their own two feet. Models stand on someone else’s feet. They are metaphors that compare the object of their attention to something else that it resembles. Resemblance is always partial, and so models necessarily simplify things and reduce the dimensions of the world. . . . In a nutshell, theories tell you what something is; models tell you merely what something is like”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Metaphors are never perfect. But then, all scientific models are just metaphors, which means they also break down at some point.2 But never mind that—metaphors (and models!) are vitally important in giving a physical understanding of the central idea behind the mathematical or scientific process or concept that you are trying to understand. Interestingly, metaphors and analogies are useful for getting people out of Einstellung—being blocked by thinking about a problem in the wrong way. For</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The more you memorize using these innovative techniques, the more creative you become.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Just before you to go sleep, review something mentally that you are trying to learn. To boost this process, review it yet again when you first wake up.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Remember—people learn by trying to make sense out of information they perceive. They rarely learn anything complex simply by having someone else tell it to them. (As math teachers say, “Math is not a spectator sport.”)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As Albert Einstein noted, “There are only two ways to live your life. One is as though nothing is a miracle. The other is as if everything is.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we can make significant changes in our brain by changing how we think.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A synthesis—an abstraction, chunk, or gist idea—is a neural pattern. Good chunks form neural patterns that resonate, not only within the subject we’re working in, but with other subjects and areas of our lives. The abstraction helps you transfer ideas from one area to another.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>sometimes, things that look rough and messy—like clouds and shorelines—have a degree of order to them. Visual complexity can be created from simple rules,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>physicist Jeffrey Prentis compares how a brand-new student of physics and a mature physicist look at equations.6 The equation is seen by the novice as just one more thing to memorize in a vast collection of unrelated equations. More advanced students and physicists, however, see with their mind’s eye the meaning beneath the equation, including how it fits into the big picture, and even a sense of how the parts of the equation feel.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Symbols and equations, in other words, have a hidden text that lies beneath them—a meaning that becomes clear once you are more familiar with the ideas.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Einstein’s theories of relativity arose not from his mathematical skills (he often needed to collaborate with mathematicians to make progress) but from his ability to pretend. He imagined himself as a photon moving at the speed of light, then imagined how a second photon might perceive him. What would that second photon see and feel?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It may seem silly to stage a play in your mind’s eye and imagine the elements and mechanisms you are studying as living creatures, with their own feelings and thoughts. But it is a method that works—it brings them to life and helps you see and understand phenomena that you couldn’t intuit when looking at dry numbers and formulas.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Multitasking during the learning process means you don’t learn as deeply—this can inhibit your ability to transfer what you are learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Persistence is often more important than intelligence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>no matter how good your teacher and textbook are, it’s only when you sneak off and look at other books or videos that you begin to see that what you learn through a single teacher or book is a partial version of the full, three-dimensional reality of the subject, which has links to still other fascinating topics that are of your choosing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>students learn best when they themselves are actively engaged in the subject instead of simply listening to someone else speak.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Failures are better teachers than successes because they cause you to rethink your approach.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Take pride in who you are, especially in the qualities that make you “different,” and use them as a secret talisman for success. Use your natural contrariness to defy the always-present prejudices from others about what you can do.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“the left hemisphere maintains our current beliefs while the right hemisphere evaluates and updates those beliefs when appropriate. Belief evaluation is thus dependent on interhemispheric interaction.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you whiz through a homework or test problem and don’t go back to check your work, you are acting a little like a person who is refusing to use parts of your brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Good learners vet their work to ensure that it makes sense. They ask themselves what the equations mean and where they come from.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The first principle is that you must not fool yourself—and you are the easiest person to fool.”8 —Physicist Richard Feynman, advising how to avoid pseudo-science that masquerades as science</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As Alan Baddeley and colleagues (2009, pp. 148–149) note: “We are not lacking in ways of defending ourselves against challenges to our self-esteem. We readily accept praise but tend to be skeptical of criticism, often attributing criticism to prejudice on the part of the critic. We are inclined to take credit for success when it occurs but deny responsibility for failure. If this stratagem fails, we are rather good at selectively forgetting failure and remembering success and praise.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Friends and teammates can serve as a sort of ever-questioning, larger-scale diffuse mode, outside your own brain, that can catch what you missed, or what you just can’t see. And of course, as mentioned earlier, explaining to friends helps build your own understanding.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Feynman, you want to remember that criticism, whether you are giving or receiving it, isn’t really about you. It’s about what you are trying to understand. In a related vein, people often don’t realize that competition can be a good thing—competition is an intense form of collaboration that can help bring out people’s best.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Keep small talk to a minimum, get your group on track, and finish your work.14 If you find that your group meetings start five to fifteen minutes late, members haven’t read the material, and the conversation consistently veers off topic, find yourself another group.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>there are ways to work with others that require only minimal interaction if you don’t like working in groups.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>equations are NOT merely expressions you plug numbers into to get other numbers. Equations tell a story about how the physical world works. For me, the key to understanding an equation in physics is to see the underlying story. A qualitative understanding of an equation is more important than getting quantitatively correct numbers out of it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This approach works for some people, mostly because anything works for some people.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When the test is handed out to you, first take a quick look to get a sense of what it involves. (You should do this in any case.) Keep your eye out for what appears to be the hardest problem. Then when you start working problems, start first with what appears to be the hardest one. But steel yourself to pull away within the first minute or two if you get stuck or get a sense that you might not be on the right track.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“With my students, I talk about good worry and bad worry. Good worry helps provide motivation and focus while bad worry simply wastes energy.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you shift your thinking from “this test has made me afraid” to “this test has got me excited to do my best!” it can make a significant improvement in your performance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Don’t feel guilty if you can’t seem to get yourself to work too hard the day before a big examination. If you’ve prepared properly, this is a natural reaction: You are subconsciously pulling back to conserve mental energy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>While taking a test, you should also remember how your mind can trick you into thinking what you’ve done is correct, even if it isn’t. This means that, whenever possible, you should blink, shift your attention, and then double-check your answers using a big-picture perspective, asking yourself, “Does this really make sense?” There is often more than one way to solve a problem, and checking your answers from a different perspective provides a golden opportunity for verifying what you’ve done.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When you are checking your work, if you start more toward the back and work toward the front, it sometimes seems to give your brain a fresher perspective that can allow you to more easily catch errors.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>your desire to figure things out right now is what prevents you from being able to figure things out.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Reshaping your brain is under your control. The key is patient persistence—working knowledgeably with your brain’s strengths and weaknesses.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A central theme of this book is the paradoxical nature of learning. Focused attention is indispensable for problem solving—yet it can also block our ability to solve problems. Persistence is key—but it can also leave us unnecessarily pounding our heads. Memorization is a critical aspect of acquiring expertise—but it can also keep us focused on the trees instead of the forest. Metaphor allows us to acquire new concepts—but it can also keep us wedded to faulty conceptions. Study in groups or alone, start hard or start easy, learn concretely or in abstract, success or failure . . . In the end, integrating the many paradoxes of learning adds value and meaning to everything we do. Part of the magic long used by the world’s best thinkers has been to simplify—to put things into terms that even a kid brother or sister can understand. This, indeed, was Richard Feynman’s approach; he challenged some of the most esoteric theoretical mathematicians he knew to put their complicated theories in simple terms.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This work will pay off both for you and those you love!</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
