<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>condensō [en]</title>
        <link>https://jak3.github.io</link>
        <description><![CDATA[GM's e-notecard system]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/review-rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2017 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>2017-10-02-zen-bodhidharma</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-02-zen-bodhidharma.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#the-zen-teaching-of-bodhidharma-the-zen-teaching-of-bodhidharma">The Zen Teaching of Bodhidharma The Zen Teaching of Bodhidharma</a></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="the-zen-teaching-of-bodhidharma-the-zen-teaching-of-bodhidharma">The Zen Teaching of Bodhidharma The Zen Teaching of Bodhidharma</h1>
<p><img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1386924996l/238863.jpg" alt="image" /></p>
<p>Not an easy text as introduction to Zen teachings but definitely recommended. Like other old text, additional readings clarify concepts, inspire more and improve your understanding. You always find something to learn from them.</p>
<p>The teachings are essential and there are not useless words. Insights bring the reader to deeply understand sacred text and Sutra, in my humble opinion.</p>
<p>Often you must read carefully and you must pay attention and put lots of effort in order to get the idea.</p>
<p>Bodhidharma explains in the last few chapters the real meaning behind sages teachings. In order to reach enlightenment you do not focus on external practices. Sages use metaphors to facilitate beginners mind to understand the Way. Bodhidharma says that you must focus on your perceptions and your inner grow.</p>
<p>As others before me said, disciple must not be a repeater. He must renew the teachings and find new formulations that are right at the moment and in such new conditions. He must accomplish much more. Bodhidharma succeed on it and the reader must do the same.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Oct 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-02-zen-bodhidharma.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>2017-09-06-kombucha</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-09-06-kombucha.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#kombucha-healthy-beverage-and-natural-remedy-from-the-far-east">Kombucha: Healthy Beverage And Natural Remedy from the Far East</a></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="kombucha-healthy-beverage-and-natural-remedy-from-the-far-east">Kombucha: Healthy Beverage And Natural Remedy from the Far East</h1>
<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/71RrRHVrvnL.jpg" alt="image" width="250" /></p>
<p>The point of reference for Kombucha fans and lover.</p>
<p>The author was able to gather and share with readers tons of information such as: applications history details, hints for production, alternative recipes and He did it easily and in a comprehensible way.</p>
<p>References are from all the different cultures that have in common this special beverage in their daily lives.</p>
<p>Useful read to both beginners and experts. It is also helpful for inquiring minds that does not want to produce the tea by themselves.</p>
<p>I really appreciated quotes and the author’s philosophical thoughts that go along with the book.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-09-06-kombucha.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
