<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>condensō [en]</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/review-atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/review-atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Giacomo Mantani</name>
        <email>name.surname on gmail</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2019-04-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Purana Purusha</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2019-04-19-purana-purusha.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2019-04-19-purana-purusha.html</id>
    <published>2019-04-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-04-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="purana-purusha-yogiraj-sri-shama-churn-lahiree">Purana Purusha: Yogiraj Sri Shama Churn Lahiree</h1>
<p><img src="https://d3525k1ryd2155.cloudfront.net/h/441/008/856008441.0.m.jpg" alt="image" /></p>
<p>Every <em>Kriyaban</em> independent from his/her lineage find insights reading this book. Lots of paragraph (transliterated) have been taken directly from Shama Churn diaries and memories are reported as it is. I appreciate also the glossary, really well detailed. A true teaching in my humble opinion, even if sometimes it differs from my previous beliefs and precepts. You should be as much as possible open minded to changes and you should evaluate them deeply with your inner Self. Personally, while reading this book, I have done some changes to my <em>sadhana</em>. I write here some of the phrases that catch my attention:</p>
<h2 id="general-topics">General topics</h2>
<ul>
<li><em>Kriyayoga</em> is absolutely scientific.</li>
<li>Everyone should receive education.</li>
<li>Obeisance by touching His feet was not preferred by Him.</li>
<li>Still your mind by doing <em>PranaKarma</em>.</li>
<li>Parents are great gurus, they are worthy of reverence.</li>
<li>Merely try to know yourself, that is <em>sadhana</em>. Knowing oneself in this manner is the ultimate and supreme fulfillment of human life.</li>
<li>Everything in the universe is existent in this body.</li>
<li>What occurs mentally occurs physically also, when the mental illusion is removed, the physical illusion will gradually be removed.</li>
<li>Ten types of <em>Anahata</em> sound can be heard: chirr, continuous chirr, small bell, conch, lute, rhythm, snake-chamber-s flute, wooden tom-tom, concerted drum music, prolonged bell.</li>
<li>Perception is in accordance with mental disposition.</li>
<li>The kinetic mind has to be reposed in the triangle within <em>Kutastha</em>. The mind has to be mounted on the <em>Ajna</em> <em>Cakra</em>, then rotated from right to left. An extremely minute mustard seed-like dot could be envisioned within that triangle.</li>
<li>Regarding the offering of the mind, the tenth chapter of <em>Srimadbhagavata</em> has a remarkable narrative. While visiting <em>Bhagavan</em> Krishna, the <em>gopinis</em> desired to take some offerings along with them. But what offering should they take? He possesses everything. The <em>gopinis</em> contemplated that they have to offer Him such an object which He did not possess. Eventually, they discovered that <em>Bhagavan</em> has everything excepting the mind, which they possessed in abundance. Therefore they offered their minds completely to <em>Bhagavan</em>.</li>
<li>White does not pertain to the category of colour. It infers neutrality.</li>
<li>Sun and Moon merged into one.</li>
<li>All the forms which can be visualized while practicing <em>Kriya</em>, what those forms are, from where they emanate and in what manner they can be visualized, all these thoughts give rise to malice and for visualizing this attachment evolves. A perceptible object is destructible. <em>Kriya</em>’s transcendental state which is beyond the Brahma Who exists within all shapes in the form of <em>anu</em>, is the knowledge of essence.</li>
<li>If the present does not exist, past and future also do not exist. Therefore the past and future subsist on the present. Abandoning the present does not bring forth direct perception. The direct perception is within the fold of time; without time there cannot be direct perception. When direct perception occurs, then present exists, thus due to dearth of the present or of time, direct perception becomes a non-entity.</li>
<li>Recollection is not possible without symptoms, because it is symptom-dependant.</li>
<li>The essence of <em>Kutastha</em> is soul, soul’s essence in turn is the mind and mind’s essence is the senses.</li>
<li>Any visualization infers attachment. Even in the visualization of <em>Bhagavan</em> Krishna attachment is inherent but in the non-visualization detachment inheres.</li>
<li>Applying deceitful stratagem all material benefits can be acquired, but not soul-attainment.</li>
<li>None is a sinner or a saint.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="who-must-practice-yogasadhana">Who must practice <em>yogasadhana</em></h2>
<ul>
<li>Material world cannot be renounced. <em>Sadhana</em> is not for renouncers only.</li>
<li><em>Sadhana</em> has to be practiced and at the same time you have to earn your livelihood. It is improper to depend upon someone for your subsistence. You should maintain your family yourself.</li>
<li>There is no impediment to practice the <em>yogasadhana</em> for men belonging to any religion or for those adhering to any doctrine. The same soul prevails in all living beings. Therefore there is no impediment for practicing <em>Atmasadhana</em>.</li>
<li>Since everything originates from Brahma everyone can be termed as Brahmin.</li>
<li>Soul-introspection is the principal aim of life, and every sadhaka of the world, without exception can do it.</li>
<li>Shama Churn illustrate how man though by remaining in the vortex of material actions can direct his life towards the exalted ideals of the spiritual world and gradually reach the pinnacle of spiritualism. He merely did not stop at expressing these ideals verbally to everyone but completely executing this in His Own life, He set an example.</li>
<li>He would remark that the two requisites to practice this immortal <em>yogasadhana</em> are a human body and a true desire.</li>
<li>None is sinful or sinless. Everyone is equal. Since everyone is the son of God, everyone has the right to practice <em>sadhana</em>.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sadhana-hints"><em>Sadhana</em> hints</h2>
<ul>
<li>Five to six hours of sleep regularly is a must.</li>
<li>Pure food, easily digestible.</li>
<li>No bathe at dawn.</li>
<li>Not undertake a rigorous fast.</li>
<li>Not be awake till very late at night.</li>
<li>Do not practice <em>Kriya</em> when there is thunders.</li>
<li><em>Kriya</em> in the morning annihilates the sins of the night and <em>Kriya</em> in the evening annihilates the sins of the day.</li>
<li>Women should not practice kriya during menstruation.</li>
<li>Impart <em>Kriya</em> to married couples together.</li>
<li>It is better to practice <em>Atmasadhana</em> a couple of hours before dawn, for during this period nature being calm.</li>
<li>There is no rule pertaining to direction, place and time for practice <em>kriya</em>.</li>
<li><em>Sambhavi mudra</em>, <em>Kechari Mudra</em>, <em>Omkara kriya</em> and <em>Kevala Kumbhaka</em> are the main things to do. <em>Kumbhaka</em> will result autonomously, do not strive for it. If the two actions of <em>recaka</em> and <em>puraka</em> are internally practiced, an automatic <em>kumbhaka</em> will result.</li>
<li>Idol-worship was never practiced by Shama Churn.</li>
<li>He would ask people to abide by their respective faiths, would impart afflatus to them and advise them to practice <em>yogasadhana</em>.</li>
<li>There is no need to take a photograph (of a guru). Otherwise in the future you could abandon <em>sadhana</em> and start worshiping the photograph and you shouldn’t.</li>
<li>Yogiraj Himself would never do <em>japa</em> of any names or mantras and would not impart these to His devotees. He was never noticed to have observed fasting or performed gross worship. He would fast once in a year on <em>Sivaratri</em> day.</li>
<li>Where a devoted disciple’s ritual practice ends, a yogi’s spiritual practice begins.</li>
<li>Undertaking external pilgrimages does not cause soul-attainment. Until you are aware about the soul-pilgrimage, you cannot attain salvation.</li>
<li>Not practicing <em>sadhana</em> of any god separately, but by firmly existing in the fundamental soul-essence, all the deities have been effected to be in His <em>sadhana</em>.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="about-god">About God</h2>
<ul>
<li>God is not an Object or Someone Who has descended from the sky, God is a state of being.</li>
<li>There is only One Who can give and He gives through the medium of someone.</li>
<li>Name and form belong to the body or any object, by what name will you invoke God? He is beyond name and form. Who else is nearer to you than Him? He dwells within you, therefore how can you loudly invoke Him? Does any person call himself by his own name? It is not necessary.</li>
<li>Someone exists within you, repeatedly invoke Him.</li>
<li>A devotee prayed Shama Churn asking “What is God?”, Yogiraj enlightened thus “Do you know Who God is? The power by which you asked ‘What is God’”.</li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Kybalion</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2018-09-30-the-kybalion.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2018-09-30-the-kybalion.html</id>
    <published>2018-09-30T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2018-09-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1328305911l/8140605.jpg" alt="image" /></p>
<p>I can not review a book like this. Everyone interested in Hermetic Teachings and or in a path to self-knowledge, <em>should really</em> read it. It is written clearly and is really short, there is not a useless word.</p>
<p>Table of Contents:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Hermetic Philosophy</li>
<li><p>The Seven Hermetic Principles</p>
<blockquote>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The Principle of Mentalism</li>
<li>The Principle of Correspondence</li>
<li>The Principle of Vibration</li>
<li>The Principle of Polarity</li>
<li>The Principle of Rhythm</li>
<li>The Principle of Cause and Effect</li>
<li>The Principle of Gender</li>
</ol>
</blockquote></li>
<li>Mental Transmutation</li>
<li>The All</li>
<li>The Mental Universe</li>
<li>The Divine Paradox</li>
<li>“The All” in All</li>
<li>Planes of Correspondence</li>
<li>Vibration</li>
<li>Polarity</li>
<li>Rhythm</li>
<li>Causation</li>
<li>Gender</li>
<li>Mental Gender</li>
<li>Hermetic Axioms</li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Feeding Your Demons</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-25-feeding.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-25-feeding.html</id>
    <published>2017-10-25T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="feeding-your-demons-ancient-wisdom-for-resolving-inner-conflict">Feeding Your Demons: Ancient Wisdom for Resolving Inner Conflict</h1>
<p><img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1344270868l/2232663.jpg" alt="image" /></p>
<p>Lama Tsultrim Allione teaches you an ancient tibetan buddhism practice revisited for western people. It is a pragmatic exercise that can be done easily at home. A bit strange for everyone that meet this spiritual practice for the first time but definitely something to try or deepen.</p>
<p>It is a sort of self-guided meditation that light up <em>reasons</em> behind inner conflicts in order to solve them.</p>
<p>The book is really well written. Easy to understand and easy to read. There are summaries sections, case studies and a chapter dedicated to the original ancient practice.</p>
<p><strong>Even skeptics can learn something behind Tsultrim Allione’s words.</strong></p>
<p>The ancient practice name is Chöd, defined briefly and really well by Reprogramming Mind youtube channel as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Chöd (Tibetan: གཅོད, Wylie: gcod lit. ‘to sever’), is a spiritual practice found primarily in the Nyingma and Kagyu schools of Tibetan Buddhism (where it is classed as Anuttarayoga Tantra). Also known as “Cutting Through the Ego”, the practices are based on the Prajñāpāramitā or “Perfection of Wisdom” sutras, which expound the “emptiness” concept of Buddhist philosophy. According to Mahayana Buddhists, emptiness is the ultimate wisdom of understanding that all things lack inherent existence. Chöd combines prajñāpāramitā philosophy with specific meditation methods and tantric ritual. The chöd practitioner seeks to tap the power of fear through activities such as rituals set in graveyards, and visualisation of offering their bodies in a tantric feast in order to put their understanding of emptiness to the ultimate test. Interview is with, author and international teacher, founder and spiritual director of Tara Mandala. In 2009, Lama Tsultrim was selected by an esteemed committee of Buddhis.</p>
</blockquote>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Outer Limits of Reason</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-05-outer-limits.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-05-outer-limits.html</id>
    <published>2017-10-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-outer-limits-of-reason">The Outer Limits of Reason</h1>
<p><img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1381287623l/17841838.jpg" alt="image" /></p>
<hr />
<p><strong>The Outer Limits of Reason</strong> is as far as I remember one of the best research essay that I have read so far. I definitely recommend the book to all inquiring minds around and to anyone who is too much confident about him/her-self knowledge.</p>
<p>Noson S. Yanofsky confirmed his knowledge page by page and with astonishing clarity explain hard topic such as Chaos, Relativity Theory and Quantum Mechanics. As a graduate student of Computer Science and Engineering I have found really well written explanations about theoretical computer science. Not for nothing Yanofsky is Professor in the Department of Computer and Information Science at Brooklyn College and The Graduate Center of the City University of New York.</p>
<h2 id="awards">Awards</h2>
<p>Winner, 2013 American Publishers Award for Professional and Scholarly Excellence (PROSE Award) in Popular Science &amp; Popular Mathematics, presented by the Professional and Scholarly Publishing Division of the Association of American Publishers</p>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<p><em>Science is a human activity. It is created by finite, flawed human beings attempting to search for the ultimate truth.</em></p>
<hr />
<p><em>The mathematics becomes abstract and about nothing in particular. Because these concepts are about nothing, they are about everything.</em></p>
<hr />
<p><em>Rather than asking why the laws of physics follow mathematics, ask why there are any laws at all.</em></p>
<hr />
<p><em>When we talk about the limits of scientific reasoning, we must keep in mind how we are observing the universe…the way we look at the universe is the way it will present itself to us.</em></p>
<hr />
<p><em>Do not mistake the metaphor for reality.</em></p>
<hr />
<p><strong>SPOILER</strong>: Yanofsky conclusion thought</p>
<p><em>We human beings already live beyond reason. Real life has importance only when it includes ethics, values, and beauty. Reason is a powerful but nevertheless limited tool.</em></p>
<h2 id="table-of-contents">Table Of Contents</h2>
<ul>
<li>Introduction <code>1</code></li>
<li>Language Pradoxes <code>15</code>
<ul>
<li>Liar! Liar! <code>15</code></li>
<li>Self-Referential Paradoxes <code>19</code></li>
<li>Naming Numbers <code>26</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Philosophical Conundrums <code>31</code>
<ul>
<li>Ships, People, and Other Objects <code>31</code></li>
<li>Hangin’ with Zeno and Gödel <code>41</code></li>
<li>Bald Men, Heaps, and Vagueness <code>50</code></li>
<li>Knowing about Knowing <code>57</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Infinity puzzles <code>65</code>
<ul>
<li>Sets and Sizes <code>66</code></li>
<li>Infinite Sets <code>69</code></li>
<li>Anything Larger? <code>76</code></li>
<li>Knowable and Unknowable <code>85</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Computing Complexities <code>97</code>
<ul>
<li>Some Easy Problems <code>98</code></li>
<li>Some Hard Problems <code>109</code></li>
<li>They’re All Connected <code>121</code></li>
<li>Almost Solving Hard Problems <code>129</code></li>
<li>Even Harder Problems <code>131</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Computing Impossibilities <code>135</code>
<ul>
<li>Algorithms, Computers, Machines, and Programs <code>136</code></li>
<li>To Halt or Not to Halt? <code>139</code></li>
<li>They’re All Connected <code>146</code></li>
<li>A Hierarchy of the Unknown <code>152</code></li>
<li>Minds, Brains, and Computers <code>157</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Scientific Limitations <code>161</code>
<ul>
<li>Chaos and Cosmos <code>161</code></li>
<li>Quantum Mechanics <code>175</code></li>
<li>Relativity Theory <code>214</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Metascientific Perplexities <code>235</code>
<ul>
<li>Philosophical Limitations of Science <code>235</code></li>
<li>Science and Methamatics <code>252</code></li>
<li>The Origin of Reason <code>272</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Mathematical Obstructions <code>297</code>
<ul>
<li>Classical limits <code>298</code></li>
<li>Galois Theory <code>304</code></li>
<li>Harder Than Halting <code>309</code></li>
<li>Logic <code>320</code></li>
<li>Axioms and Independence <code>331</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Beyond Reason <code>339</code>
<ul>
<li>Summing Up <code>339</code></li>
<li>Defining Reason <code>345</code></li>
<li>Peering Beyond <code>349</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Notes <code>355</code></li>
<li>Bibliography <code>379</code></li>
<li>Index <code>393</code></li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Zen Teaching of Bodhidharma</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-02-zen-bodhidharma.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-02-zen-bodhidharma.html</id>
    <published>2017-10-02T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-zen-teaching-of-bodhidharma">The Zen Teaching of Bodhidharma</h1>
<p><img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1386924996l/238863.jpg" alt="image" /></p>
<p>Not an easy text as introduction to Zen teachings but definitely recommended. Like other old text, additional readings clarify concepts, inspire more and improve your understanding. You always find something to learn from them.</p>
<p>The teachings are essential and there are not useless words. Insights bring the reader to deeply understand sacred text and Sutra, in my humble opinion.</p>
<p>Often you must read carefully and you must pay attention and put lots of effort in order to get the idea.</p>
<p>Bodhidharma explains in the last few chapters the real meaning behind sages teachings. In order to reach enlightenment you do not focus on external practices. Sages use metaphors to facilitate beginners mind to understand the Way. Bodhidharma says that you must focus on your perceptions and your inner grow.</p>
<p>As others before me said, disciple must not be a repeater. He must renew the teachings and find new formulations that are right at the moment and in such new conditions. He must accomplish much more. Bodhidharma succeed on it and the reader must do the same.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Kombucha</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-09-06-kombucha.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-09-06-kombucha.html</id>
    <published>2017-09-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-09-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="kombucha-healthy-beverage-and-natural-remedy-from-the-far-east">Kombucha: Healthy Beverage And Natural Remedy from the Far East</h1>
<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/71RrRHVrvnL.jpg" alt="image" width="250" /></p>
<p>The point of reference for Kombucha fans and lover.</p>
<p>The author was able to gather and share with readers tons of information such as: applications history details, hints for production, alternative recipes and He did it easily and in a comprehensible way.</p>
<p>References are from all the different cultures that have in common this special beverage in their daily lives.</p>
<p>Useful read to both beginners and experts. It is also helpful for inquiring minds that does not want to produce the tea by themselves.</p>
<p>I really appreciated quotes and the author’s philosophical thoughts that go along with the book.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
