<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>condensō [en]</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/review-atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/review-atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Giacomo Mantani</name>
        <email>name.surname on gmail</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2017-10-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>2017-10-05-outer-limits</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-05-outer-limits.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-05-outer-limits.html</id>
    <published>2017-10-05T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-outer-limits-of-reason">The Outer Limits of Reason</h1>
<p><img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1381287623l/17841838.jpg" alt="image" /></p>
<hr />
<p><strong>The Outer Limits of Reason</strong> is as far as I remember one of the best research essay that I have read so far. I definitely recommend the book to all inquiring minds around and to anyone who is too much confident about him/her-self knowledge.</p>
<p>Noson S. Yanofsky confirmed his knowledge page by page and with astonishing clarity explain hard topic such as Chaos, Relativity Theory and Quantum Mechanics. As a graduate student of Computer Science and Engineering I have found really well written explanations about theoretical computer science. Not for nothing Yanofsky is Professor in the Department of Computer and Information Science at Brooklyn College and The Graduate Center of the City University of New York.</p>
<h2 id="awards">Awards</h2>
<p>Winner, 2013 American Publishers Award for Professional and Scholarly Excellence (PROSE Award) in Popular Science &amp; Popular Mathematics, presented by the Professional and Scholarly Publishing Division of the Association of American Publishers</p>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<p><em>Science is a human activity. It is created by finite, flawed human beings attempting to search for the ultimate truth.</em></p>
<hr />
<p><em>The mathematics becomes abstract and about nothing in particular. Because these concepts are about nothing, they are about everything.</em></p>
<hr />
<p><em>Rather than asking why the laws of physics follow mathematics, ask why there are any laws at all.</em></p>
<hr />
<p><em>When we talk about the limits of scientific reasoning, we must keep in mind how we are observing the universe…the way we look at the universe is the way it will present itself to us.</em></p>
<hr />
<p><em>Do not mistake the metaphor for reality.</em></p>
<hr />
<p><strong>SPOILER</strong>: Yanofsky conclusion thought</p>
<p><em>We human beings already live beyond reason. Real life has importance only when it includes ethics, values, and beauty. Reason is a powerful but nevertheless limited tool.</em></p>
<h2 id="table-of-contents">Table Of Contents</h2>
<ul>
<li>Introduction <code>1</code></li>
<li>Language Pradoxes <code>15</code>
<ul>
<li>Liar! Liar! <code>15</code></li>
<li>Self-Referential Paradoxes <code>19</code></li>
<li>Naming Numbers <code>26</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Philosophical Conundrums <code>31</code>
<ul>
<li>Ships, People, and Other Objects <code>31</code></li>
<li>Hangin’ with Zeno and Gödel <code>41</code></li>
<li>Bald Men, Heaps, and Vagueness <code>50</code></li>
<li>Knowing about Knowing <code>57</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Infinity puzzles <code>65</code>
<ul>
<li>Sets and Sizes <code>66</code></li>
<li>Infinite Sets <code>69</code></li>
<li>Anything Larger? <code>76</code></li>
<li>Knowable and Unknowable <code>85</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Computing Complexities <code>97</code>
<ul>
<li>Some Easy Problems <code>98</code></li>
<li>Some Hard Problems <code>109</code></li>
<li>They’re All Connected <code>121</code></li>
<li>Almost Solving Hard Problems <code>129</code></li>
<li>Even Harder Problems <code>131</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Computing Impossibilities <code>135</code>
<ul>
<li>Algorithms, Computers, Machines, and Programs <code>136</code></li>
<li>To Halt or Not to Halt? <code>139</code></li>
<li>They’re All Connected <code>146</code></li>
<li>A Hierarchy of the Unknown <code>152</code></li>
<li>Minds, Brains, and Computers <code>157</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Scientific Limitations <code>161</code>
<ul>
<li>Chaos and Cosmos <code>161</code></li>
<li>Quantum Mechanics <code>175</code></li>
<li>Relativity Theory <code>214</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Metascientific Perplexities <code>235</code>
<ul>
<li>Philosophical Limitations of Science <code>235</code></li>
<li>Science and Methamatics <code>252</code></li>
<li>The Origin of Reason <code>272</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Mathematical Obstructions <code>297</code>
<ul>
<li>Classical limits <code>298</code></li>
<li>Galois Theory <code>304</code></li>
<li>Harder Than Halting <code>309</code></li>
<li>Logic <code>320</code></li>
<li>Axioms and Independence <code>331</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Beyond Reason <code>339</code>
<ul>
<li>Summing Up <code>339</code></li>
<li>Defining Reason <code>345</code></li>
<li>Peering Beyond <code>349</code></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Notes <code>355</code></li>
<li>Bibliography <code>379</code></li>
<li>Index <code>393</code></li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>2017-10-02-zen-bodhidharma</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-02-zen-bodhidharma.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-10-02-zen-bodhidharma.html</id>
    <published>2017-10-02T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-zen-teaching-of-bodhidharma-the-zen-teaching-of-bodhidharma">The Zen Teaching of Bodhidharma The Zen Teaching of Bodhidharma</h1>
<p><img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1386924996l/238863.jpg" alt="image" /></p>
<p>Not an easy text as introduction to Zen teachings but definitely recommended. Like other old text, additional readings clarify concepts, inspire more and improve your understanding. You always find something to learn from them.</p>
<p>The teachings are essential and there are not useless words. Insights bring the reader to deeply understand sacred text and Sutra, in my humble opinion.</p>
<p>Often you must read carefully and you must pay attention and put lots of effort in order to get the idea.</p>
<p>Bodhidharma explains in the last few chapters the real meaning behind sages teachings. In order to reach enlightenment you do not focus on external practices. Sages use metaphors to facilitate beginners mind to understand the Way. Bodhidharma says that you must focus on your perceptions and your inner grow.</p>
<p>As others before me said, disciple must not be a repeater. He must renew the teachings and find new formulations that are right at the moment and in such new conditions. He must accomplish much more. Bodhidharma succeed on it and the reader must do the same.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>2017-09-06-kombucha</title>
    <link href="https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-09-06-kombucha.html" />
    <id>https://jak3.github.io/mica/review/en/2017-09-06-kombucha.html</id>
    <published>2017-09-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2017-09-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="kombucha-healthy-beverage-and-natural-remedy-from-the-far-east">Kombucha: Healthy Beverage And Natural Remedy from the Far East</h1>
<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/71RrRHVrvnL.jpg" alt="image" width="250" /></p>
<p>The point of reference for Kombucha fans and lover.</p>
<p>The author was able to gather and share with readers tons of information such as: applications history details, hints for production, alternative recipes and He did it easily and in a comprehensible way.</p>
<p>References are from all the different cultures that have in common this special beverage in their daily lives.</p>
<p>Useful read to both beginners and experts. It is also helpful for inquiring minds that does not want to produce the tea by themselves.</p>
<p>I really appreciated quotes and the author’s philosophical thoughts that go along with the book.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
