<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>condensō [en]</title>
        <link>https://jak3.github.io</link>
        <description><![CDATA[GM's e-notecard system]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Penetrating Wisdom</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2025-03-07-penetrating-wisdom.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1174504687i/408934.jpg" /></p>
<h1 id="penetrating-wisdom">Penetrating Wisdom</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>Through thegradual intensification of habit Sequential entry into samsdra began.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Dualism is doubt.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>faith, faith without any questions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is devotion and trust in the inconceivable truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The biggest obstacle in the path of Tantra, in the paths of Vajrayana, Mahamudra, and Dzogchen, is completely and utterly trusting these ordinary perceptions. The truth is out there and it cannot be experienced by these low-tech perceptions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The basic meaning here begins with faith in this inconceivable truth. In Vajrayana, that is the fundamental faith.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is trust and faith in the fruition of the path as well as in the teachings that lead us to the fruition of enlightenment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Vajrayana goes beyond logic. This is a very important point. Vajrayana is like asking someone to wake you up in the morning. You are not relying on an alarm clock. You are relying on this person, the Vajra master, to wake you up.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Devotion involves wisdom and knowledge.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So you see, two seemingly ordinary and unimportant things can be very important in Tantra. You can never tell what is not important. Only the Vajra master can tell.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>there is a big difference between individual understanding and individual interpretation. That is why Buddha taught three yanas. Although Buddha gave many teachings, we only hear what we want to hear.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes we may misunderstand and say there is no space at all in the Vajrayana for any kind of doubt. That’s not true. It is very very dangerous to say that we must not have any doubts! Buddha said doubt is wisdom. He said that inquisitive mind is wisdom. We are more than welcome to have doubts and inquisitive mind about the path and practices. At the same time, we must not go so far with these doubts that we get caught up and carried away by them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>These problems of selective practice, selective hearing, and selective guru become our major obstacles on the path.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>called “the great perfection.” To convey fully the meaning of Dzogchen in English, the expression “full stop” is quite good. Full stop. Period. This period is a little but very powerful dot called the full stop. There is the sense of being full in that this dot has a circular form that is complete and full. At the same time, everything stops here: it doesn’t go beyond this period. Dzogchen has a similar meaning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Vajrayana path is known as the path of fruition because we are not working with causes to produce the result. Instead, we are taking the result as the path.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>there’s a saying in the Dzogchen literature, “The happiness Kuntuzangpo or the suffering Kuntuzangpo.” Happiness is utterly pure and suffering is utterly pure. In the ultimate space of Kuntuzangpo, there are no differences between happiness and suffering, just as there are no differences between inside and outside.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Milarepa said that between two conceptual discursive thoughts, you experience nonconceptual wisdom. There is a moment of nonconceptual wisdom in between thoughts. We don’t realize that, we just miss it all the time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One problem with our human mind is that we like complexity, we are addicted to it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>group karma, beings in each of the different realms experience a common world.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when the motivation is pure, the benefit is greater.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If there are no people who irritate you, then how can you perfect the paramita of patience? If there are no people to make you angry, how can you perfect the paramita of discipline? If there are no people or phenomena to distract your mind from the perfect samadhi, then how can you perfect the path of the paramita of discipline</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You have to go through the different stages of experiences and not get attached to them. Go continuously on the path. Eventually, that will lead to realization.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One is free from these five poisons if one’s sensory perceptions simply experience what they are without labeling thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“You are not bound to samsara by appearances, you are bound to samsara by conceptual attachment. Therefore my son, Naropa, cut the root of this attachment.” The appearances of the world outside, which are the experiences of the five sensory perceptions, are not a problem. The problem here is the labeling process that follows it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whatever sensory experiences we go through, if we go through them with mindfulness and awareness, there is no limit to how far we can go. The limit is mindfulness and awareness. Even if we don’t enjoy the experience, that itself becomes a trip.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Neither alayavijnana or alayajnana matters at first, just get the stillness. In that stillness, the alayajnana arises naturally and without struggle.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We identify our guests, “Oh, my visitor is Mr. Anger” or “This time my visitor is Mr. Jealousy” or “This visitor is Mr. Ignorance.”Then, with the great Mahayana compassion and the Vajrayana fearlessness,you open the door. We won’t leave our guest outside, we will invite him in. Be with it, that’s the reality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a nightmare, or has some painful illusion in a dream, a person with clairvoyance can see that.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Tantric teachings are said to really benefit those who have very strong poisons, very strong emotions. For that reason, the wrathful deities play a stronger role on the path of awakening in Tantra.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But at a certain point, some kind of very unpleasant situation comes up that really gets us into that state. That unpleasant situation really clicks us into the state of truly understanding and appreciating impermanence. It clicks us into understanding shunyata and appreciating the notion of emptiness. That happens all the time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are making the aspiration that they obtain the ultimate wealth and the ultimate joy, which is the recognition of primordial buddha mind. That is our aspiration here. But our aspiration is not only to recognize this primordial ground of buddhahood. Once we have recognized this ground, we aspire that such wisdom then expands and shines out. We aspire that by recognizing this ground, the boundless wisdom of beings grows to the infinite space of the universe.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“May all sentient beings, including ourselves, be in the state of our fundamental buddhahood that is the primordial buddha Samantabhadra.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you want to do an aspiration to benefit others, this is a beautiful aspiration for all beings of the six realms.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In the beginning, you should put some effort into your postmeditation practice. For example, you should try to remember to watch your mind, watch your thoughts, at least once every hour. That’s very good practice already. If you do it every hour, it is already a great achievement. Later, that effort will bring the sense of effortless awareness in everyday life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The five elements manifest from these five lights. The water element manifests from white light. The earth element manifests from yellow light. The fire element manifests from red light. The wind element manifests from green light, and the space element manifests from blue light. These are the five elements.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is important to identify the emotion in which we are engaged, even though it is often mixed. Passion, aggression, jealousy, and so on are all mixed at certain points. Identifying them is the process that naturally takes us to mindfulness, to awareness. There is no other way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first step is just simply to observe it. Simply recognize the emotion and then watch it as it grows or as it continues. Just simply watch it. In the beginning, just to have an idea that it’s coming is very important and very effective. In the Vajrayana sense, the way to watch these emotions is without stopping them. If we recognize the emotion and say,“Yes, it is passion,” and then try to stop it, that’s a problem. Rejecting our emotions is a problem in Vajrayana.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Just being mindless itself is a distraction. That’s the most subtle distraction we ever experience in our meditation path. Usually, we think of distraction as being something very active. We think of it as a dualistic interaction between an outside object and one of the six sensory perceptions. But distraction here is simply being unmindful, being unaware.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The labeling process is a very subtle way of planting and growing this seed of ignorance in our mindstream.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the most gross element of this ignorance is the division between self and other. The labeling process has matured to the stage where we can clearly see the dualistic barrier.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>With diligence and exertion, we can reach a point where effort becomes effortless. However, at the beginning we need to exert ourselves. In order to exert ourselves, we need discipline. That’s why the paramita practices are so practical. The paramita practices are common to both Tantra and Sutra. We can begin with discipline, which is the cause of diligence, and discipline enforces our diligence. Diligence doesn’t come without renunciation and without seeing the possibility of freedom. Therefore, they are all connected.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In the beginning, it’s just the mechanism. We are just starting the movement, which itself has a subtle craving. A subtle attachment is developed in that subconscious move.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Attachment is actually the greatest suffering of all sentient beings.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is nothing called beautiful outside. Even in our mundane wisdom, we have the saying that beauty lies in the eye of the beholder.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we have one good master, another one always looks kinder. The other one always looks much more skilled, much more intelligent, and so on. Then we flip back and forth with our teachers, the same as we do with everything else. That is the totally chaotic path called the hungry ghost realm.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In classical Buddhist paintings, the hungry ghosts are sitting right next to a beautiful lake while, at the same time, they are burning inside with thirst. Even while they burn inside with thirst, they have this stinginess. They think that the water will be completely consumed if they drink, so they never drink. It is said that even if the hungry ghosts drink, they burn inside even more because they worry about losing this wealth of water. If we are not mindful, this hungry ghost psychological state can happen to us at any time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whenever lust, passion, attachment, or desire arises, the method given here is not to reject these emotions. It is to let them come, let them arise. There is no need to suppress this emotion. There is nothing wrong with its appearance. The raw energy of lust and passion is in the state of buddha wisdom. The Prayer says that whenever they arise, we should not go under the power of the labeling process, the power of conceptualizing the raw energy of lust and passion. We go through this experience of tremendous energy called passion. What usually happens is that we conceptualize it later. That conceptualization leads us into an endless chain of thoughts and an endless chain of labeling. That endless chain of thoughts and labeling leads us to all sorts of different emotions, such as anger and jealousy, that become problematic.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Just simply experience the emotion, neither reject it nor accept it. The raw energy is simply experienced without any thought, without any labeling process. Just simply be in that space. The Prayer says that this brings the wisdom of perfect discernment, discriminating wisdom, which corresponds to the wisdom of the western buddha field of Amitabha.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The problem here is not the passion. It is not the lust nor is it the desire. The problem is that we are not leaving them alone. We are not letting them be what they are. We are disturbing them with the labeling process, the thought process. We are not letting lust be lust, we are not letting desire be desire, we are not letting passion be passion. Therefore, the mind becomes agitated.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are the creator of these states as well as the experiencer of these states.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The pain that we see in the hell realm is the creation of our mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But if you conquer just one enemy, your aggression, it is like conquering all the objects of this anger.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you want to destroy an object, look inside and find the true enemy, which is aggression. Conquer that. Shantideva said that anger is very destructive. He said that one moment of hatred or anger can destroy the virtue of many eons.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Similarly, one moment of anger, aggression, or hatred can wipe out the data of all the virtuous actions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it would be harmful to have thoughts of hatred toward those surrounding you, but it is much more harmful to yourself than to any other person.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Mahayana and Vajrayana views say that whatever we experience, whatever we perceive, is basically our own creation. There is no outer creation and no outer creator. The creator is right here. If we are seeing nice beautiful scenery, it is our own creation. If we are seeing a horrible world outside or a horrible experience inside, it is also our creation. It is our mind’s experience. This is a very important element in these teachings.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In Buddhism, when we talk about mind-only, it doesn’t mean that the other person doesn’t exist. What we are saying is that the way we perceive, the way we relate, the way we see phenomena, is very much our mind only. It is our creation. We are projecting outside and we are perceiving that projection. It’s very much our perception only. It is our conception only. In the same way, this hell realm is a creation of our mind. We are projecting all these weird things outside and going through tremendous unnecessary pain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>this emotion called pride. It is very dangerous and destructive because it causes us to refrain from learning. It blocks us from improving ourselves. Having pride means the end of our growing, the end of our development.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If the pot is upside down, no matter how much water you try to pour in, you can’t fill it.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That is the definition of pride; an attitude of superiority to others. We get into the suffering of disputation because we feel superior.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The main thing that we need to learn is how to be in whatever state we are in. We need to learn to be in that state completely, honestly, and without trying to pretend to be something better or something different.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We learn to be in the raw state of the emotion itself, without altering it, without trying to be something else.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The main problem of jealousy is lack of appreciation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That’s what we call competitiveness, always wanting more than what we have.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We go through a painful experience of praising and denigrating. Praising oneself directly or indirectly, and denigrating others directly or indirectly, is the continual process of struggle.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Buddha said that if you rejoice in the merit arising from whatever positive actions others may be involved in, you get the same merit.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>For example, we’re attached to sleep so we don’t take delight in waking up, and so forth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Anger has the same kind of quality. It’s very awakening in its nature but we usually paint it more than it requires or needs. We have to simply experience it. When you experience it, just experience it. Just rest in it. Don’t hate it and don’t follow it with any more thoughts, any more paintings. Just be. Just sort of let it be. It comes close to the end of words at a certain point.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As for the method, we have a tradition in Mahayana practice of reviewing the whole day. Every evening in our last session of meditation, we review the whole day. We try to think about the major emotional events that occurred during the day. We recollect whether we had a major anger, a major passion, or a major experience of hatred during that day. Then we really try to see it and we try to see how we handled it. Maybe we were somewhat successful, maybe we failed. We also try to see how many positive thoughts we had. See how many good thoughts that we had, such as thoughts of compassion. If we do that in our last meditation, we can see our ignorance pretty clearly. We can see our ignorance in these experiences of screwing up our opportunities to recognize rigpa. By reflecting, we can try to recognize ignorance.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2025-03-07-penetrating-wisdom.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Long Pilgrimage</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2025-03-03-long-pilgrimage.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1697513254i/806945.jpg" /></p>
<h1 id="long-pilgrimage-the-life-and-teaching-of-sri-govindanda-bharati-known-as-the-shivapuri-baba">Long Pilgrimage: The Life and Teaching of Sri Govindanda Bharati, Known As the Shivapuri Baba</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>You should write about my teaching, not about me.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you believe in God, then your search must be for God; but even if you believe in nothing, you must still have some conviction that there is a meaning behind this visible world. You must be determined to seek out that meaning and understand it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Practice those twenty-six qualities or virtues described.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Put up a routine of your day’s work with fixed duties and go ahead. Then see your success and failure in the evening.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first stage he calls Self-Realization, the second Soul-Realization, and the last God-Realization.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There was a bird which was as tiny as a nut living by a sea coast. And it used to lay eggs on the beach close to the sea. But every time it discovered that its eggs had all been washed away by the ocean in high tide. And anger was born in the heart of the bird. One day, in order to recover its lost eggs, the bird thought out a plan to dry up the ocean. Forthwith with a firm determination the bird started to work out its plan. It dipped itself in the ocean and flew back to the beach to dry itself up in the sand which it did repeatedly. When this process was being repeated another of its kind came and asked, “What is this that you are doing and what for?” “I’m going to dry up the ocean to recover my eggs which now it has hidden in its bosom.” “Are you really? I must recover mine as well. I must join you in this effort.” So saying the second bird also did the same thing. Presently other birds too came on the scene and all joined in the attempt. Soon the number grew up to millions and billions and the terrific process was on. Soon the ocean was full of mountains. Fear was created in the heart of the ocean. At long last the ocean had to yield. What a great force it is to make a strong determination however insignificant a man may be.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Teaching with bringing flowers (page 42 and 43)</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first thing is to reach God. By seeing God, everything is known. Think of God alone. Dismiss every thought from your mind. You will see God. It is difficult, but not impossible. It is difficult—I do know. But if you will take enough trouble to remove that difficulty, all other difficulties of life will vanish. Unless we see God, we cannot know anything Before the sun comes, we can see nothing on the ground. When the sun comes, we see everything. So the Presence of God. When we know God we know everything. Before that, a simple explanation is no explanation at all.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Let the thought of God be alone in your mind, destroy every other thought. You will see God before you and all your problems are solved. This is the first business. Now, unless you live a disciplined life, this meditation is not possible. There is this body; you should know the requirements of this body. You will have to hear, you will have to see, you will have to sleep, you will have to taste, you will have to spit, you will have to breathe. One thousand activities are there in this body. All these activities are to be controlled and commanded. How much to eat, how much to sleep, what to see, what to hear ? All this should be controlled and commanded. This is one duty. Another duty is towards home, society, nation, etc. Find out what we have to do. A third duty concerns material needs. Without material wealth, we cannot do these things. For that we have a professional duty. These are the duties one has got to do. They should be found out and practised properly, without any failure, without commission or omission. Then life becomes steady. In the steady life, meditation is very easy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we are covered by consciousness. God is beyond consciousness. Forget this consciousness a moment; you will see God. In a flash! First, what we have got to do is: discipline this life, then meditate on God. When you see God, every problem is solved.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Man has three duties: <strong>Physical duty</strong>—the obligations he was born to; earning a living, acquitting himself and his talents in the world, looking
after his dependents and so on. <strong>Moral duty</strong>—to be aware of the obligation towards oneself to seek the Truth for twenty-four hours of the day. <strong>Spiritual duty</strong>—Worship of God—but this we will appreciate only later. Attention to the first two duties—taken very simply, will take us far along the way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You must not cease working at these two duties even for one minute. A minute’s lapse will cause emotions, passions, thoughts to invade your mind… If you don’t entertain them they will drop you and go elsewhere…Put a barbed wire fence round your mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>He gave me some personal advice: ’Decide how much you want. Decide how many friends, how many people you want to see; how much money you need to earn to live with your family, how much time you will give to thinking and talking about things like journalism, politics and other things; how much food and drink and entertainment you feel you need. Then stick to this regimen as best you can. Don’t let yourself be carried beyond these limits.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There must be neither joy nor suffering in meditation, only an intense desire to see God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The highest purpose is served by the simple performance of our duties. That is Dharma. This is no easy matter. The duties cannot be recognized and performed properly, unless there is a keen intelligence. Then it is necessary to have a strong mind in order to meditate without wavering upon God. In order to acquire a strong mind there must be moral discipline. Therefore, all three are necessary: duty, discipline and devotion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You must not allow the relative to overcome the absolute in you.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>God doth not need either man’s work or His own gifts.” And yet He requires of us that we should not be hearers only, but doers of the Word. The enigma of the finite and the infinite is always with us. The Vedanta does not remove it. No one has preached a more thoroughgoing monism than Shankara. No one practised a more thoroughgoing dualism. The Shivapuri Baba cuts the Gordian knot in the simplest way by saying that both are right, but neither is right without the other.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Be sure that if you ask enough, God will come.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You see that for maintaining body, you have to discharge certain duties towards nature, towards family, towards society, towards government and towards profession. All these should be planned and done with dexterity. Then for making your mind strong you have to cultivate virtues, charity, self-control, fearlessness, patience, together with the rest of the twenty-six virtues described in the sixteenth chapter of the Gita. This is discrimination. The rest of the time you should devote to thinking of Truth in various ways without feeling monotonous. This is Devotion. The most important thing is to see that you do not waste your time on any other work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>How can we best help the world? <strong>S.B.</strong> By living the Right Life and practising charity; mental, verbal, bodily, and pecuniary. Mentally, we should wish well even to our so-called enemies. We should not speak words likely to hurt others. We should, when possible, try to serve others physically. Then at least ten per cent of our income should be devoted to charity. This, again, should be divided into three parts. One part should go to poor spiritual aspirants and institutions for spiritual life. Another part should go to deserving cultural people and institutions. The third part should go to poor people and institutions for helping them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is this <strong>body (1)</strong>. It has many requirements. You should know the right activities for each part of the body. These right activities are to be selected and performed without any commission or omission. Another thing is <strong>mind (2)</strong>. Mind is ruled by emotions. Mind should be ruled by reason. Calmness must prevail in the mind. The third thing is: the rest of the time should be utilized for meditating on <strong>God (3)</strong>, to know the meaning of Life, or to see God personally. This is Right Life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Parents and teachers should prepare the way. They are the agents of the Self.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>these duties should be performed in such a way as not to hinder your search for God. Little by little, you will be able to diminish them. First professional duties are to be reduced to what is necessary, then family duties. Finally, there remains only the duty to preserve the existence of your body. Nevertheless, even now you can meditate upon God and the meaning of life. Every day you must set aside as much time as you can for this, and you will come to it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>From experience, by experience, reason comes. Now. Suppose I tell you to prepare tea. You prepare it. There may be some mistakes—the real taste will not come. There may be more sugar, or more tea. Or the art of boiling may be wrong, the ingredients may be wrong. Today, you make, you taste it, and the right thing has not come. Find out the mistake today, and remedy it tomorrow. Another mistake may come. Remedy it the day after tomorrow. In this way, go on preparing that one thing for a long time. You will get the correct taste one day, then maintain the correct taste. This is reason.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>By the observation of yesterday, you can change today. By changing today, tomorrow will be different.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we should care for neighbours also. We should be very helpful to them, never be harmful to them. They will always be eternal friends. Whenever we are in difficulty, they will come and help us. It is the same With society and nation and with all human beings. That is right life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One should not live for pleasure; but, if it comes, it should not be rejected also. Pleasure will give satisfaction if it is accepted without being sought for.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That God is to be seen, then only life will be all right. The meaning of life is to be known. Then only one can be happy here. To know that meaning or to see God, his thoughts should always centre round that one subject. Every other subject must vanish from the mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Moral perfection must be essential. One should not yield to liking and disliking. One should not have any other desire, other than living this life or finding out God. Then this lower nature should not play in the mind; anger and various other things.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Opposite nature should be eliminated from the mind. Simply by seeing our behaviour. If behaviour is wrong, one should determine now that such behaviour should not be. Today anger came, tomorrow it should not come.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><em>La disciplina non deve essere limitata a parole e azione ma anche ai pensieri</em>. In thought, word and deed; <strong>G.B.</strong> You mean that one has to conquer anger in one’s thoughts, it is no use to try and conquer it by one’s actions. <strong>S.B.</strong> No, it will not be. <strong>G.B.</strong> If I have angry thoughts, it is not enough to stop my angry words? The thoughts are still there, the thoughts come before the actions. <strong>S.B.</strong> Yes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One should cultivate all the Creation as the Image of God, the Manifestation of God—one should always be humbled, humiliated before that. When such thoughts are established, anger will not come.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The second discipline is of the Mind. Mind is wild. Various passions, various thoughts are playing in the mind. Now these passions, these thoughts are all to be removed from the mind. One should not yield to liking and disliking. In that way, the mind will become strong. One should cultivate the higher nature. One should destroy the lower nature. This is moral discipline. Then the mind becomes very strong. In that strong mind, when you have finished these duties for a time, you can meditate upon God. Either your mind should remain with these duties, or it should remain with God. It should have no other place. That is the right way of life today.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>reduce the love for life. Love of God will automatically increase.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>let pains come or pleasures come; we should be indifferent to both. if we live this right life, with these disciplines, sufferings will be very, very much less. Many sufferings will go away. But still some sufferings will remain, that one should not mind. One should have a law of the mind to follow.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Angoscia, nostalgia, tristezza, rabbia -&gt; BE INVOLVED IN THE WORLD, DO NOT STAY TOO MUCH WITH THESE THOUGHTS.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>what is needed is simple faith in God, not reason. There is a God—if I meditate on Him every day, I will see Him. This simple faith is all we need.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Who am I?, it is beyond reason. When we pursue this beyond reason, we reach God. When we pursue this reason, we reach pleasure.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Fear and temptation, these are the two beginnings of human troubles.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Yes. Yes, patience, even the whole oceans will be drowned within patience. It will come. Yes, there is the story of a young boy Dhruva. His stepmother turned him out, he was very sensitive, he went to the forest. Then he sat under a tree, and he wanted to see God. Then a Saint going by said: ‘You are very young, you won’t get to God.’ Then the boy said: ‘No, no, don’t say like that. Tell me where to see God.* The Saint said: ’I shall go and ask God and will give you his answer.’ So the Saint went to see God and told him what the boy was asking. Then God said: ‘I will not go to him, it will take a long time for me to go to him. He is sitting under a tree. Tell him to count the number of leaves in that tree. So many lives he should finish, then only will I go to him.’ The Saint came back and told him: ‘No use of your sitting here. So many lives you will have to pass, then only you will see God.’ The boy said: ‘All right, if I will pass all those live?, he will see me, that assurance he has given. I am satisfied.’He sat there. Then God wanted to test him. He took the form of a lion, and began to roar very fiercely, and He came near his side. The boy saw that lion, and then he said: ’Oh, Lion come up very soon and eat me away. One life is over. I am nearer God.’ No fear, nothing in him. He wants only God; then at once, God revealed Himself before him. This is determination. Fear should be driven out. With all his insistence upon the need for an uncompromising determination in the pursuit of Truth, the Shivapuri Baba is well aware of the dangers of a literal interpretation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Once a snake was lying on the way. It used to bite everybody. A Yogi was passing. The snake went to bite him also. He (Yogi) said: ‘No, there is sin, don’t bite me.’ He (the snake) said: ‘What is sin?’ The Yogi explained. The snake was frightened. ‘What must I do?’ said the snake. The Yogi said: ‘Now, you don’t bite anybody, keep quiet in your place, and take the Name of God.’ He said this and went away. That snake remained in that place, and began to take the Name of God. Some children were passing by that way. They saw the snake. They took stones, and threw at it, and some mischievous children caught it by the tail, and threw it away. It was about to die. The Yogi was returning, then the snake called him. ‘What a man you are. What you taught me? Now I am about to die. Why you taught me this nonsense?’ The Yogi said: ‘No, no. It is your own mistake. Why you remain in that particular place? Why did you not go and stay in your hole there? Nobody would have seen you. I told you not to bite people. When people come to trouble you, why do you not rear your head and frighten them? I told you not to bite them, that is all. They will run away. You could not use your intelligence, so that is why you came into trouble.’</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One’s own Dharma must be fulfilled. What we do for the Dharma of others is part of the total Dharma, and it cannot be separated from our own. Thus Right Living has three aspects; cosmic, social and personal. It is the Universal Law or Will of God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mind is filled with various impressions, passions and thoughts. All these should be emptied from the mind. God- thought alone should roam in the mind with one desire to see God or to have His blessings, or in other words, there is a Truth behind this life. That is to be known. The thought of this Truth alone should occupy the mind, no other thought. By performing the three duties life will prosper but that will not create this moral and spiritual discipline. Moral discipline is to create peace in the mind. Without peace prosperity becomes meaningless. Meditation on God becomes impossible when there is no peace in the mind. When any desire remains, meditation is not possible. One’s sole concern in life should be God-Realization. Life should become secondary. My teaching is that one should know what is life, why is life and how is life. Without knowing these things life can never be lived properly. To know these things we should know God first. So one’s aim should be to see God. To know God one should be possessed by that one idea of God exclusive of all other ideas. Therefore, one should always meditate on God. Now, in an impure mind meditation becomes impossible or distracted. For that moral discipline is essential. But again without a purified body, purification of mind also becomes impossible. To have a purified body one should do simple essential things. One should regulate all his duties and these regulated duties should be done with complete success. Hence disciplined actions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is no such special form of meditation to be recommended.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Man has a threefold structure: <strong>Body</strong> with its various functions and powers, his <strong>Manas</strong> with its impulses, desires and qualities; <strong>Purusha</strong>: freedom to choose between the different influences that act upon him, both from without and from the different sides of his own nature. Purusha is helpless until the mind grows strong enough and wise enough to <em>‘pierce the veil of consciousness’</em>. Three destinies:
<strong>World-Realization</strong>; <strong>Soul-Realization</strong>; <strong>God-Realization</strong>.
Body; Manas; Purusha
Energy; Understanding; Will
Duty; Morality; Worship
One cannot change one’s own will by force, God-Realization comes by grace (gratuitous character of the supreme good). Nevertheless, we have our own necessary part to play and that is to be single-minded in our waiting for God. <strong>This Single-Minded, patient waiting for God with loving insistence, is meditation.</strong> This is complete worship, that must be distinguished from devotion which is only one of the form of worship.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The guiding principle for <em>duty</em> is <strong>intelligence</strong>, for <em>morality</em> <strong>discrimination</strong>, and for <em>worship</em> <strong>spiritual longing</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The sole purpose of this human life is to find the Ultimate Truth or God, and for this we must accept a certain code of life which means that we should put our life in right order. There are three different orders we should look into. They are (1) Spiritual order; (2) Moral order; and (3) Intellectual order.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The First Discipline of Duty: for a good life (Sukha) here on
earth (body): 1. Personal 2. Obligatory 3. Professional
<strong>(1) Personal</strong>: To keep the body fit we have to use our external organs and we should use them wisely; that is, we should use them as much as is necessary. Seeing, hearing, speaking, touching, eating, etc., should be done only to the proportion required for the body and mind; no extra use should be made.
<strong>(2) Obligatory</strong>: Since we cannot live alone and need the help of others, society is required. We have our duties to society, parents, family and other people.
<strong>(3) Professional</strong>: Since we have to maintain ourselves, we must earn something and must take to some profession according to individual taste and capacity. But we should spend on our own account only as much as is necessary and use the balance for other purposes. Spend what is absolutely necessary, nothing more, nothing less.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Those who desire to realize the Truth should make the moral and physical disciplines of the three duties secondary, and the spiritual discipline, namely Meditation, primary. But in no case should any of these duties be omitted. Only this Right Life and Meditation for Truth in a direct method lead to realization of the Absolute.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All is useless and a waste of time unless God chooses to reveal Himself to the soul.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a sharp and material distinction between the stage of going beyond consciousness and the stage of senseless stupor, which in other words is called ’Nirvikalpa Samadhi*</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Are you strong enough to resist pain or temptation in the external and worries in the internal world? Every one must response to such question before looking only towards God without life-adjustment. Every one must look to it. But, as a rule, both are to be prescribed, that is, God plus life- adjustment. This is the royal road as prescribed by the Gita. But as a short cut for the man in question, this importance attributed to Knowledge and Intellect may be disregarded, according to his capacity for resisting or ignoring the reactions produced by wrong Knowledge and wrong Intellect. But beware of strong reactions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The foundation of the <strong>first discipline is <em>Discrimination</em></strong>. Careful attention to detail. It is an obligation for man to study the peculiarities of his own body so as to know exactly how it should be treated. The inner working parts of the instrument are just as important as its outward appearance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Meals, sleep and bath should be taken in exactly the right amount. At every stage of life one must know exactly when to sleep, how long to sleep and how to sleep.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All the different functions as a whole should tend towards the ultimate goal. They are like motives tending towards the Master Motif which is our ultimate goal. By daily observation, we come to know where the functions have been going wrong and improve our efficiency, till a time comes when we get a definite standard of life. We shall then have no inferiority in anything. Observe cleanliness. Bedding should be neat and clean. No agitation, nothing should disturb when going to bed. Do not give way to speculation. Have calmness and concentrate on om (🕉️). Burn incense for good smelling.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Think only good thoughts of others.</strong>
<strong>Speak only good words of others.</strong>
<strong>Do only good deeds to others.</strong>
<strong>Give of your substance to help others.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The strong <em>Manas</em> is the link between the two worlds in which man has to live. It enables him, on the one hand, to face his duties with serenity; and, on the other, to enter upon his search for God with peace and faith. The <em>Manas</em> is thus the link between the spiritual and the material sides of man’s nature, and also between the inner and the outer worlds in which we must live. In order to fulfil its task, the <em>Manas</em> must be strong enough to withstand the assaults and pressures of the material world, and yet pure enough to recognize the delicate and subtle qualities of the spirit. The transformation of the <em>Manas</em> is thus the central problem for those of us, and they are almost the totality of all human beings on earth, who were not born, like Ramana Maharshi, with a <em>Manas</em> strong enough and pure enough to embark without preparation or training upon the spiritual quest.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sampadam daivim (Gita 16th Chapter) Fearlessness, Purity of Mind, Stability of Character, Charitableness,Self-Mastery, Readiness to make Sacrifices, Studiousness, Ability to make Efforts, Straightforwardness, Non-Violence, Truthfulness, Freedom from Wrath, Renunciation (of the fruits of action), Tranquillity, Aversion to Slander, Compassion towards Living Beings, Non-Covetousness, Gentleness, Sense of Shame in doing evil actions, Strength of Mind, Energy, Forgiveness, Endurance, Chastity, Absence of Malice, Aversion to Praise. <strong>They are contents of the mind (Manas), not attributes of the man himself (Purusha) who is within or behind the mind (Manas)</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The mind itself is a living, sensitive and even conscious organ. As such, it is capable of undergoing transformation. This transformation comprises three distinct actions:
(1) The Mind must be purified, so that its contents consist wholly and solely of the daivic elements. This is a sattwic mind.
(2) It must be strengthened and expanded, so that it can withstand the influences of the external world and give the Purusha a place for tranquil meditation. These are serenity and peace.
(3) It must commit itself wholly and irrevocably to the search for God. For this, it must lose itself. This self-losing is described by the Shivapuri Baba as piercing the veil of consciousness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Morality</strong> (Manas): differences between morality and duty is that the former concerns the inner life, the letter the outer life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Actions in themselves cannot be described as moral or immoral unless we know the inner state from which they proceed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What do we do? We try to regain our previous position, thinking that this is the only course left open to us in order to preserve that peace of mind we were enjoying previously. Here, we are mistaken. We overlook the fact that our effort to regain our previous status is quite futile because in this ever-changing world what has happened will never return. Instead, if we are wise we should try to adjust ourselves to the new status in which we find ourselves.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Everywhere there are exceptions to every rule. - Author, not Shivapuri Baba quote</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Manas, Buddhi and Ahamkara are all mind. Manas does, Buddhi knows and Ahamkara ascertains. A strong mind is possible through practice of the virtues.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Right morality (that is with no liking or disliking) is the tongs with which we should deal with this existence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When useless or harmful actions are not done, no reactions come to us. We then are left free to meditate upon God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The foundation of true morality, as distinct from artificial or imitative morality, is discrimination. This is the second and most precious possession that man can have—the first is insatiable hunger for Truth, that is God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Discrimination is an active power that goes beyond knowledge. We cannot discriminate rightly and act wrongly. If we see what has to be done and do not do it, we must admit that we do not discriminate. Discrimination is a property of the mind—or, as we should say in the West, of the soul—which determines our actions. True discrimination is true morality. Morality without discrimination can always fall into error.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You cannot teach Faith. Faith comes from God. You must teach them discrimination. From discrimination, faith will come by itself.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Do not allow anything from the external to make you desist or refrain from your duties.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Third Discipline—The Spiritual Life is the supreme task, the fulfilment of which is the very purpose of man’s existence, and for which all the others are but a preparation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Man can never find God, but, as in the story of the boy Dhruva, he can bring God to him if he has the required qualities of mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>With <strong>Intellect</strong>, we conquer this world and achieve earthly happiness, sukha. By <strong>Manas</strong>, we conquer ourselves and achieve serenity, santosh, and the assurance of eternal bliss. By <strong>Faith</strong>, we allow ourselves to be conquered by God, and in losing all to find all, that is Shanti. World-Realization, Soul-Realization and God-Realization are three distinct end-points of three distinct processes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Think of God alone. Put every other thought from your mind. When all else disappears you will see God. In a flash. Since few mortals have the strength of mind to follow this precept literally from the start, we must go by stages. There are three of these, conveniently described by the Sanskrit words dharana, dhyana and samadhi, or steadiness, meditation and diffuse contemplation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Samadhi is concentration on Truth. Dhyana is thinking of any one particular object for a long time. Dharana is thinking of Truth historically. In another sense, meditation is profound thinking. It makes our health better, gives extremely helpful ideas, and is quite essential for our spiritual progress. Meditation is a mad man’s business.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Dhyana</strong>: There is consciousness of both external and internal world
<strong>Dharana</strong>: there is consciousness of internal world only</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Conceptions of morality differ according to time and place. For maintaining the Right Life, we can break any rule of morality. The universal morality is to commit no act of omission or commission (do something wrong). We must not be dogmatic about other forms of morality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>teachings found in books are only general. Particular aspirants need the guidance of a teacher, who is a realized soul.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Right Life and Meditation is a path not denying life, but making it. By accepting life and leading it in the right path, we are able to establish life and make ourselves capable of realizing the Truth by Meditation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A person may meditate while performing his duties, or in a forest. But even in leading a life in a forest, one has to perform the threefold duties. A life in the forest is not a life of penance or yogavyas. The person seeking Truth in a forest, has to make his life by practising the ’Right Life* and having direct meditation on God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Each action of the external senses must be measured, and no commission or omission should be made.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>First Stage: DHARANA.</strong> Its purpose is to produce an orientation of the mind that facilitates the next stages. This means literally the act of holding in the mind, and also of memorizing and keeping the mind collected.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Second Stage: DHANYA.</strong> Meditate on Him with as much reverence and love as you can on His manifested form in the beginning. Imagine Him as standing just in front of you. Meditate on this Form repeatedly. Forget all except Him. Speak to Him, <em>‘O God, bless me.’</em> Speak, cry, laugh, dance, do anything, let flow your ecstatic tears. From Him is this all. Without Him there is nothing. Have a posture so as to make your mind steady on this Form. If the entire form is not possible for you to imagine within a single sweep of your vision, imagine Him in parts from head to foot. Practise like this repeatedly. Devote as much of your time as possible. Offer Him flowers, incense and bow down to His gracious feet. When your concentration on this Form fails, come down to dharana, let your imagination play in His sportful Lilas, in such studies as pertain to Him alone. Then again a fresh assault of concentrating on Him. Come down to dharana again, a fresh assault again. Go on like this for years and years. <strong>Imagine Him standing close to you as your shadow in all your thoughts and doings.</strong> Then a time will come when you will actually see Him before you. Your joy will know no bounds. Your ignorance, all this pleasure and pain will vanish. Your whole outlook will be changed. The sole purpose of this human life is nothing but the realization of God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Third Stage: SAMADHI.</strong> This means to be established in the identical, that is, the state of unity of subject and object: in this case the individual Purusha and the Supreme Reality. Beware here again. Do not stop here alone. This is not all. Again there is Samadhi, the question as to whence is this Being. Stop here and seek beyond—the Unknown Source. This Being is but the assumed Form by that Unknown Source. Go and know That. There a real peep into the Vacuum happens. Then all is over. The Ultimate Goal is reached. This realization can be had only by the Grace of God. Only such a man who works along this line of Swadharma, i.e. along these three principles, and yet does not get involved in enjoying the fruits thereof, and dedicates all to God, and always remains for the most part of his time in deep hankering after God, is the person who deserves this Grace. In Samadhi itself there are different degrees, and the seeker after ultimate Truth must beware of the temptation to remain at some intermediate stage which, by its intense bliss and sense of liberation from all earthly ties, may appear to be the end. <strong>But</strong> Nirvikalpa Samadhi also, one day, it dissolves with the dissolution of the world. SO there is no permanent happiness there also. There, in that utter helplessness, he gets stirred. If not, while in Nirvikalpa Samadhi, he remains completely at rest and enjoys supreme bliss. This stirring, but no coming back, must necessarily drive him beyond where he is, in that utter despair. Consequently one-pointed attention is taken to the climax and the Flash happens. He gets the Vision. He sees himself. Only then the real life of the man begins.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This, of course, is in everybody’s case in the beginning stages. <strong>Do not get disheartened.</strong> Remain in Dharana, Dhyana and Samadhi. What is Dharana? Think of Christ, for instance, remember His teachings His personality, His life-activities and all that you know of Him. Also think of the Sun, the Moon or the stars or rivers, mountains, lakes, etc., which are the creation of God. Read Scriptures and the like. Say prayers. Tell the beads. Thus go on thinking of the glories of God in one way or another, so that you spend your time on God and nothing else. This is Dharana, where you remain, as if in a bigger circle. This too is a form of meditation. Go on and think what is the meaning of life. By thus doing you try to penetrate into the mysteries of God. This is Dhyana, where you get more concentrated. Then again when you make such inquiries as ‘Who am I ?’ you come to concentrate as if on a point (from the bigger circle of Dhyana and Dharana). This process of Dharana, Dhyana and Samadhi is to be repeated times without number. By thus doing your mind is forcibly made to stay on God and in course of time, say, in months or years your mind must get tamed and become steady. In Samadhi, of course, one’s mind cannot at present stand even for a fraction of a second; only in course of time you will succeed. Distaste for life and continued practice of meditation on God is the only qualification needed. Mind’s desire is to be curbed. <em>External duties should be planned definitely and critically observed. Avoid every work outside this. Successfully do what is planned.</em> <strong>Without God-Realization nothing is possible. The only object should be that!</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Knowledge itself is not the realization of it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Three eternal questions Why? How? and What?
<strong>Why?</strong>—To attain bliss: <strong>Ananda</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This has three forms:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Sukha pleasure which belongs to the body, Kshetra.</li>
<li>Santosh which is serenity of mind, Manas.</li>
<li>Shanti or peace of the inner self, that is, Purusha.</li>
</ol>
<p>The why of all activity consists in the attainment of one of the
three forms of bliss.</p>
<p><strong>How?</strong>—By purified awareness: <strong>Citta</strong>.</p>
<p>This also has three forms:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Physical Discipline which brings pleasure</li>
<li>Moral Discipline which brings serenity</li>
<li>Spiritual Discipline which brings peace</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>What?</strong>—That which is: <strong>Sat</strong>.</p>
<p>This has three categories:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Transcendental: God, Purusha and Maya.</li>
<li>The Modes: Unmanifest (Avyakta) Manifest (vyakta) Mind (manas)</li>
<li>Intellect and the rest of the 24 principles, namely [Intellect, 1 — feeling, 5 inner senses, 5 outer senses, 5 objects of sense, the 5 great elements.</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>All the things we see in this universe, men, and materials, all nature and its different phenomena, are simply bewildering. We cannot make out what they are. The reality behind them, the secret of secrets is quite hidden to our view and, as it were, hermetically sealed. The earnest inquirer is times without number repelled from his activity, thrown back into despair and anxiety as he cannot come to a right solution of all this bewildering complexity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we do not lose heart and patiently continue our searching, our earnest inquiry will naturally have a right direction, we find a real Guru who is self-realized.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There are different opinions as regards the number of the tattwas. But for our purpose, God or ‘this existence* is the only tattwa. This existence, which we see externally and internally as well, is nothing but God. This ’I* should go on inquiring ’What is this?’ This is meditation or God-Concentration. This is Atma- tattwas, or soul, of which we have our own awareness. This awareness is under the influence of the three gunas. Next there is our experience of existence. This experience is gained through Intellect. Now, what is imperative is that this intellect and the resultant experience is to be made limited, that is, to run on a particular channel. Unless we limit we cannot apprehend because this experience itself is infinite.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Gita comes forward and takes all these three as honourable gentlemen (Karma, Bhakti, Jnana). Each is taken full use of and advice is given to go through all of them. All three together produce a factor which tends to the one aim to which all had agreed before. When God is aimed at during these three processes, the different results particular to each of them drop off, and lose importance. They are all utilized, and in combination made to bear fruit in the shape of God attainment. Sarva Karma Phala Tyaga (every action gives fruit to be abandoned) i.e., we must never allow ourselves to be entangled in the enjoyment of the different results, before we reach our goal or realization.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>every new vantage ground reached becomes a prison if we seek to enjoy it beyond the moment it is reached. Thousands of aspirants to the highest Truth have lost their way through mistaking a milestone for the terminus.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Karma, Akarma and Vikarma are the three classes of our activities. Akarma or useless activities and Vikarma or harmful ones must be abandoned. Only Karma or useful ones are to be well attended to. If this is found too difficult, this work of eliminating these two activities may be accomplished only gradually, according as our strength of tyaga (or spirit of renunciation) permits. In doing Karma alone, which involves a daily repetition of almost the same items of work, we naturally acquire a dexterous hand in the long run. Our relation with the outside world, that is our physical or intellectual order, will be very well established. We shall then have no complaints against the external world, since by then we shall have achieved a smooth sailing as far as our life-demands are concerned. We shall then be freely allowed to think on, or ponder over, the Absolute Truth which is beyond. “Who am I?” is our question. “O God, reveal to me the secret.” Thus praying we go on with an agitated mind and spend all the rest of our time. We bow down to Him and ask for His grace and, as long as His grace does not descend upon us, we never leave this—our agitation. Quite a tedious business it is. But still we must go on, since there is no other way to be taken recourse to. We must go on with our original question as to “Who am I ?” As long as this Truth of truths is not revealed to us we must not stop our agitation or else we are doomed. Because there is an end to this world of blissful experience one day.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When there is Raga, or liking, and Dwesha, or hatred, in the lower sphere of our activity, we may either indulge more than what is required or less than what is necessary. In more indulgence we shall have to lose our stock of energy for nothing, and in less, too, we shall be pricked from the life-demands.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whatever we do in this world is through our Intellect. It is an instrument. We are solely guided by it. If we follow its lead blindly, and, if it is wrong, it will lead us to troubles. That is why the necessity arose to perform Gayatri daily, meaning thereby, to pray to this Intellect not to lead us astray. (“Let us meditate upon the glorious radiance of Savritri. May it enlighten our Intellect”).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our intellect should be in line with morality. Knowledge or the avoiding of the influence of the three gunas, and lastly with a careful avoidance of akarma and vikarma.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One should divide the day into two: one part for carrying out necessary duties; one part for worship of God. One should try not to do unnecessary things, and to do what was necessary for this reason, and not for the sake of gratifying desires. Eating, for instance: one should eat enough to give the body the energy it requires, and not more, and not because one is tempted by the taste of the food. Whatever one does, eating, walking, sitting, talking, writing, reading, thinking—everything should be done in this way, and <strong>done consciously</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>inwardly not to identify, and outwardly, to play one’s role consciously. You could behave angrily without any feeling of anger inside, the mind being in control and untouched, so to speak.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every function needs its own quality of energy and that what is not needed for use for a function can be transformed into a higher quality for a higher function.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we are able to look at the situation without interference from our ego-sense, then we can make sound judgments. The ego has no judgments of its own, but depends upon what it has seen and heard from others.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a wise man will not get himself involved in such controversial statements. He is concerned only with the state of complete freedom and happiness which is beyond this idea of perfection and imperfection. The common factor, that is this practice of Yajna, Dana and Tapas, only will be counted by him rejecting all speculative inquiries.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We come out of the darkness (avarana) and we go towards forms created by our own imagination (vikshepa). Beyond this darkness and these forms, lies the Truth that we are seeking. We must no longer dally with all this, but peep into the darkness (avarana) which breaks our patience. God may be in it or beyond it. So in Right Life, mind and intellect cannot play havoc. They are made use of only when required. At other times they are silent. They are caged like a lion and we shall not have to fear them. Promise or outside force makes us live the Right Life in the beginning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We live on our impressions. The background is God.We go from one to another of such impressions. This means that we are not dwelling on the meditation of God, Who is the Absolute Background of all these various impressions. Now the question arises as to how we can free ourselves from such impressions. We should know that these impressions are like pieces of understandings which rest on God, the Absolute Background behind. These are like parts only out of the Whole. We should here see that God, or the Absolute, is permeating each and every such impression of ours. We then penetrate into such impressions, and find that in essence all these pieces of impressions are One, not different. We find unity in diversity. In thus doing, we go from the vikshepa shakti of Maya to the avarana side. From there, we try to make out the underlying fundamental Unity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This world and its experience like this, is only the work of the mind. We create mind and then we have this world. Otherwise no world. Science has proved it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Right Life consists of three stages:</p>
</blockquote>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Simple observation</p></li>
<li><p>Detection</p></li>
<li><p>Elimination</p></li>
<li><p>This is the ABC of the business, the most painstaking part of it. If we get through it, the other two parts will be very easy. <strong>See what we do daily—Karma, vikarma or akarma. That is all.</strong> By doing this we retain our consciousness always with us, which is the most unavoidable preliminary for the other stages. We should keep this consciousness always in our ideal or Right Life which is two-fold.</p></li>
</ol>
<ol type="a">
<li>The lower life, viz. the <em>protection of life</em>.</li>
<li>The higher one, viz. the <em>thought on God</em>.</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Karma phala tyaga</em> - <strong>abandoning the fruits of action</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This soul is to be known and realized for better identification. This inquiry as to ‘Who am I ?’ should be our main concern.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Temptation and Fear are the two causes for deviation which is wrong. Love of God (the idea that we can have the highest pleasure or bliss which surpasses every other sense-pleasure) saves us from temptation, and Distaste for life (the idea that death is inevitable and let death come in the attempt) brings fearlessness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Imagining God in some way or other according to our preconceived notion is false. Yet it is to be sought simply to relax for some time and enter into God inquiry again with fresh vigour.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Knowledge is twofold. One which deals with ‘what’ and the other which is dealing with ‘how’, All the questions you have put come under this ‘what ?’ We can wait for this till we see God. But the question ‘how?’ should be solved today. We cannot wait till God comes. Hence be very strict and careful in this ‘how?’</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>build your life today and tomorrow you will have a good life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Morality is that which makes him capable to abide by this right Knowledge and right Intellect so to say, his spirit of self-surrender. Thought over God is equivalent to the thought over this Swadharma.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whenever we do our Karma we should do it without being impelled by desire (Ichchha), or by attachment (Raga), or by hatred (Dwesha). If we keep our mind away from their influences we are said to be keeping up morality. No liking or disliking we should have in doing our duties.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A man without attachment to anything, without feeling any sort of pride in his work, with a steadfastness of purpose, and without being affected in the least by the resultant success or failure, is a Sattwic person.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When the one thing is kept supreme, i.e. when God is aimed at at all costs, the three purifications come in automatically (though without a guru) to make the supreme one possible. Keen hankering after God drags in its train the required purifications even without our knowing to a certain extent, which is quite enough for our purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One who has dedicated his life to the pursuit of TRUTH need not dissipate his energies on questions of social laws. Because his main task lies in the journey towards the Absolute, performance of social obligations becomes the least troublesome for him and, since he has not to follow any dogma or so-called religious exercises, he will personally not have to face any conflict with social questions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In personal life, one must be watchful of his own actions. He should not perform a single unnecessary action. Same on seeing, hearing, speaking, eating and touching. He should conserve all his senses and must not waste any of them. In personal life one must be pure in action and in mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Meditation combined with Right Life can alone bring Realization. This method admits of no religion, no sect, no dogma, no theory. This is called Swadharma. Swadharma simply means fulfilling one’s three-fold duties and meditation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All problems arise because our minds are linked to sentiment. We should link our minds to reason, not sentiment. Our mind will always follow what is pleasant, even if it is not reasonable. It will avoid the unpleasant, even if it is clearly more reasonable. Pleasure and displeasure, liking and disliking <strong>should not be the business of the mind.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Discipline is not effort but surrender. Discipline gives strength. A bird gets its strength from air. A king from his army. A man from his sense of discipline. Discipline gives a plan and shape to man’s life. When he makes a start, already some problems become less. With each act of surrender, of discipline, it becomes easier to frustrate the mind’s tricks to drag you away from your purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A child must be trained to be first, efficient, second, responsible, and third, aware of questions of why are we living, truth, God. Efficiency is very essential. Even making a cup of tea must be perfected by practice—trial and error. Responsibility must be learnt because this leads to concern for duty. Concern for spiritual matters is needed because this is one’s duty—to find Truth and God. Children should be given daily duties—a daily plan for life. Simplify their lives for them. By simplifying yours. It is possible to do your work and reduce the complexity of your life and theirs. They will imitate your life. It is more than mere imitation but even imitation will do for a start.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Spend some time every day thinking of why we are living? Where did we come from ? Where are we bound ? When a start is made this becomes interesting, like reading a book. When it is interesting other thoughts become weaker and one is thinking only of the book. Another analogy: Look for the white screen of the cinema behind the moving, flickering pictures. Cut activity down to the minimum and do our duties.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Take only half belly full of food, quarter belly of water and one quarter of belly empty.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our troubles arise because we have been taught to hanker after Happiness. This is nonsense. Maya. The winter comes and the summer comes. We live through both. Pleasure and pain are like that. Life should not be spent seeking one and avoiding the other. Life must be lived according to one’s duty.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is possible to find enlightenment in the rest of your lifetime. Never mind yesterday, let yesterday be forgotten. Begin today. Now. That is the only way. This world is a painful place. What is the use of pleasure if it is replaced by pain ? This is a very dangerous world. We must find Truth in the time left to us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ugliness and beauty: both must vanish from the mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Let those needs wait (even the urge to lessen suffering of the world). First go to God. When one sees God, then one can take to these things (world service and so on). Remember: <strong>First seek to enter the Kingdom of God and everything can be added towards that.</strong> For the present, if one cannot help oneself what help can one give to another? That is it. Suppose, however, you still want to do some help. Here in these duties, there is a chance. In one’s obligatory duty towards home and society, one can give a little bit—according to one’s capacity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you want to do good for the whole of humanity, wait until the knowledge and the power come.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When the virtues will come, there will be peace of mind. Moral discipline -&gt; purification of the mind -&gt; peace of mind -&gt; power to meditate -&gt; knowledge of God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>First of all, you must see that like and dislike is a defect in man. You must recognize it as a defect and never justify it. You must understand that unless it is removed, one cannot see God. This understanding must come. <strong>Be patient and persevere</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When you know it today, try to practise it from today. It is possible.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Prepare for today. That is all. Prepare for today.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The only qualification essential for this is the desire for God. That is the only qualification.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are commanded to do our duty, to act morally, to perform the four charities and, beyond and above all, to love and worship God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>whenever we are considering the undertaking of some new activity we should ask ourselves whether it is an obligatory duty of one of the three kinds, or whether it is a ’choice duty* that we undertake because we want to, or whether it comes under the heading of useless (akarmic) or even harmful (vikarmic) activity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Life can and should be lived to the full in all its departments: but in this full living we must never lose sight of our goal which is God. For this we must learn to look for God in every action. There is God in the discipline of duty that leads to Self-Realization, there is God in moral discipline that leads to Soul-Realization, and there is God in spiritual discipline that leads directly to God Himself. Beyond all these is Liberation, Moksha, but this does not mean that life ceases to be lived until the chosen moment of release has come. All the duties and activities of life are to be performed, with the one essential condition that we must never take them as the final goal.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The sum and substance of my teaching is this: <em><strong>live the minimum life possible, subjecting body and mind to strict discipline. Again, how a very hungry man longs for meat, how a man suffering from intense cold longs for heat, so long for God, meditate on Him continuously. And this is the sum and substance of my teaching. That is for you, that is for them, that is for the whole world. It is by this that I saw the Truth, and I am happy. Yes.</strong></em></p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2025-03-03-long-pilgrimage.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Kashf Al-Mahjub, The Revelation of the Veiled</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-04-21-kashf-al-mahjub.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1572717238i/530671.jpg" /></p>
<h1 id="kashf-al-mahjub-the-revelation-of-the-veiled---an-early-persian-treatise-on-sufism">Kashf Al-Mahjub: The Revelation of the Veiled - An Early Persian Treatise on Sufism</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>O Lord, bestow on us mercy from Thyself, and provide for us a right course of action!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“To ask blessing” means “to commit all one’s affairs to God and to be saved from, the various sorts of contamination”.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The believer’s intention is better than his performance.” Great is the power of intention, through which a man advances from one category to another without any external change.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A good intention, therefore, is preliminary to the due performance of every act.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Everyone makes pretensions, none attains to reality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>knowledge should not be separated from action.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ḥátim al-Asamm said: “I have chosen four things to know, and have discarded all the knowledge in the world besides.” He was asked: “What are they?” “One,” he answered, “is this: I know that my daily bread is apportioned to me, and will neither be increased nor diminished; consequently I have ceased to seek to augment it. Secondly, I know that I owe to God a debt which no other person can pay instead of me; therefore I am occupied with paying it. Thirdly, I know that there is one pursuing me (i.e. Death) from whom I cannot escape; accordingly I have prepared myself to meet him. Fourthly, I know that God is observing me; therefore I am ashamed to do what I ought not”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a sect of heretics called Sophists (Súfisṭá’iyán), who believe that nothing can be known and that knowledge itself does not exist. I say to them: “You think that nothing can be known; is your opinion correct or not?” If they answer “It is correct”, they thereby affirm the reality of knowledge; and if they reply “It is not correct”, then to argue against an avowedly incorrect assertion is absurd.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Knowledge is of three kinds—from God, with God, and of God.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You must know enough to know that you do not know.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“True perception is to despair of attaining perception, But not to advance on the paths of the virtuous is polytheism.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the dervish is a place over which something is passing, not a wayfarer following his own will.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Prophet said, repeating the words thrice: “Thou knowest, therefore persevere.”]</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>renunciation is of two kinds: formal and essential. For example, if one renounces a pleasure, and finds pleasure in the renunciation, this is formal renunciation; but if the pleasure renounces him, then the pleasure is annihilated, and this case falls under the head of true contemplation (musháhadat).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“To-day Ṣúfiism is a name without a reality, but formerly it was a reality without a name,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if you wish to show to the people that you belong to God, should your claim be true, you are guilty of ostentation; and should it be false, of hypocrisy. The Ṣúfís are too great to need a special garment for this purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“A dervish must not have less than three things: first, he must know how to sew on a patch rightly; second, he must know how to listen rightly; third, he must know how to set his foot on the ground rightly.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when anything has become habitual to the soul it soon grows natural, and when it has grown natural it becomes a veil.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first year is devoted to service of the people, the second year to service of God, and the third year to watching over his own heart.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“He whose poverty is compulsory is more perfect than he whose poverty is voluntary; for if it be compulsory, he is the creature (ṣan‘at) of poverty, and if it be voluntary, poverty is his creature; and it is better that his actions should be free from any attempt to gain poverty for himself than that he should seek to acquire it by his own effort.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Do not let your wife and children be your chief cares; for if they be friends of God, God will look after His friends, and if they are enemies of God, why should you take care of God’s enemies?” This question is connected with the severance of the heart from all things save God, who keeps His servants in whatever state He willeth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Thou dost never turn away the beggar, and no creature in earth or heaven can prevent the true believer who implores Thee from gaining access to Thy court.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“When God wishes a man well, He gives him insight into his faults.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>true solitary is not disturbed by society, but he who is preoccupied seeks in vain to acquire freedom from thought by secluding himself. In order to be cut off from mankind one must become intimate with God, and those who have become intimate with God are not hurt by intercourse with mankind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Keep watch over thy heart” (’alayka bi-qalbika), i.e. “Guard thy heart from thoughts of ‘other’”.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>my asceticism in this world is desire for the next world, and this is the quintessence of desire. How excellent is he who takes no thought of his own interest! so that his patience is for God’s sake, not for the saving of himself from Hell; and his asceticism is for God’s sake, not for the purpose of bringing himself into Paradise. This is the mark of true sincerity.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The deed that I love best is sincerity in doing,” because an action only becomes an action in virtue of its sincerity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it is better to fulfil the duty which is owed to one’s mother than to make the pilgrimage. Return, therefore, and try to please her.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When a man is overcome with love for the Agent, he attains to such a degree that in looking at His act he does not see the act but the Agent only and entirely, just as when one looks at a picture and sees only the painter.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Practise what you have learned, for theory without practice is like a body without a spirit.” He who is content with learning alone is not learned, and the truly learned man is not content with learning alone.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is no knowledge without action, since knowledge is the product of action, and is brought forth and developed and made profitable by the blessings of action.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the more one loves, the more one is obedient, and love is increased by true knowledge.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“A moment’s reflection is better than sixty years of devotion,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The sleep of the sage is an act of devotion and the wakefulness of the fool is a sin,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kun lilláh wa-illá lá takun, “Be God’s or be nothing,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“O God, whatever punishment Thou mayst inflict upon me, do not punish me with the humiliation of being veiled from Thee,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When Thy beauty is revealed to our hearts, we take no thought of affliction</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Lust is of three kinds—lust in eating, lust in speaking, and lust in looking. Guard thy food by trust in God, thy tongue by telling the truth, and thine eye by taking example (’ibrat).”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is not lust when thou receivest food from Him and eatest by His leave, or when thou speakest of Him by His leave, or when thou seest His actions by His leave.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Fear and hope are the two pillars of faith. It is impossible that anyone should fall into error through practising either of them. Those who fear engage in devotion through fear of separation (from God), and those who hope engage in it through hope of union (with God).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Therefore Man cannot properly take or leave anything; it is God who in His providence gives and takes away, and Man only takes what God has given or leaves what God has taken away.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I left work and returned to it; then work left me and I never returned to it again,” because when anyone leaves a thing by one’s own act and effort, the leaving of it is no better than the taking of</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the marvels of Divine action are in nothing manifested more clearly than in human hearts.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Let him be occupied with himself in order that he may see learning everywhere, and let him turn from himself to God in order that he may see gnosis everywhere. Let him seek learning and gnosis in himself, and let him demand practice and reality from himself.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Those who regard things as determined by God turn to God in everything,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“A thing can be explained only by what is more subtle than itself: there is nothing subtler than love: by what, then, shall love be explained</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>His biographers relate that for forty years he never slept; then he fell asleep and dreamed of God. “O Lord,” he cried, “I was seeking Thee in nightly vigils, but I have found Thee in sleep.” God answered: “O Sháh, you have found Me by means of those nightly vigils: if you had not sought Me there, you would not have found Me here.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the heart is the seat of knowledge of God and is more venerable than the Ka‘ba, to which men turn in devotion. Men are ever looking towards the Ka‘ba, but God is ever looking towards the heart. Wherever the heart is, my Beloved is there; wherever His decree is, my desire is there; wherever the traces of my prophets1 are, the eyes of those whom I love are directed there.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Anyone who is ignorant of the nature of servantship (’ubúdiyyat) is yet more ignorant of the nature of lordship (rubúbiyyat),” i.e., whoever does not know the way to knowledge of himself does not know the way to knowledge of God, and whoever does not recognize the contamination of human qualities does not recognize the purity of the Divine attributes, inasmuch as the outward is connected with the inward, and he who claims to possess the former without the latter makes an absurd assertion. Knowledge of the nature of lordship depends on having right principles of servantship, and is not perfect without them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Presence (ḥuḍúr) is better than certainty (yaqín), because presence is an abiding state (waṭanát), whereas certainty is a transient one (khaṭarát),” i.e., presence makes its abode in the heart and does not admit forgetfulness, while certainty is a feeling that comes and goes: hence those who are “present” (ḥáḍirán) are in the sanctuary, and those who have certainty (múqinán) are only at the gate.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“At thy service” (labbayk),</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>On the other hand, when persons of true spirituality and insight have visions, they make no effort to describe them, and do not occupy themselves with self-admiration on that account, and are careless of praise and blame alike, and are undisturbed</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“speaking tongues are the destruction of silent hearts”. Such expressions are entirely mischievous. Expression of the meaning of reality is futile. If the meaning exists it is not lost by expression, and if it is non-existent it is not created by expression. Expression only produces an unreal notion and leads the student mortally astray by causing him to imagine that the expression is the real meaning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>God never leaves the earth without a proof (ḥujjat) or the Moslem community without a saint, as the Apostle said: “One sect of my people shall continue in goodness and truth until the hour of the Resurrection.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the name of dervish is applied to anyone whose heart subsists in the contemplation of God?’ i.e. those who contemplate God are rich in God» whereas dervishes (fuqará) are occupied with self-mortification.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Ṣúﬁism is the subsistence of the heart with God without any mediation.” This alludes to contemplation (musháhadat),</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whatever good or evil God creates, do not in any place or circumstance quarrel with His action or be aggrieved in thy heart.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>how wrong it must be to imitate a mere expression!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Station” belongs to the category of acts, “state” to the category of gifts. Hence the man that has a “station” stands by his own self-mortification, whereas the man that has a “state” is dead to “self” and stands by a “state” which God creates in him.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“O God, show us things as they are,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“When the morning-star of wine rises,
   The drunken and the sober are as one.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>one moment of this world is better than a thousand years of the next world, because this is the place of service (khidmat) and that is the place of proximity (qurbat), and proximity is gained by service.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>phlegm, blood, bile, and melancholy, which four humours correspond to the four elements of this world, viz. water, earth, air, and fire, while his soul (ján), his lower soul (nafs) and his body correspond to Paradise, Hell, and the place of Resurrection. Paradise is the effect of God’s satisfaction, and Hell is the result of His anger. Similarly, the spirit of the true believer reflects the peace of knowledge, and his lower soul the error which veils him from God. As, at the Resurrection, the believer must be released from Hell before he can reach Paradise and attain to real vision and pure love, so in this world he must escape from his lower soul before he can attain to real discipleship (irádat), of which the spirit is the principle, and to real proximity (to God) and gnosis.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Those who strive to the utmost for Our sake, We will guide them into Our ways” (Kor. xxix,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The result hangs on predestined grace (’ináyat), not on abundance of mortification. It is not the case that he who most exerts himself is the most secure, but that he who has most grace is nearest to God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One says, “He who seeks shall find,” and the other says, “He who finds shall seek.” Seeking is the cause of finding, but it is no less true that finding is the cause of seeking.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mortification will never turn a donkey into a horse or a horse into a donkey, because this involves a change of identity; and since mortification has not the power of transforming identity it cannot possibly be affirmed in the presence of God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“trust in God is a term denoting your conduct towards God and your spiritual excellence in regard to relying on Him: if a man spends his whole life in remedying his spiritual nature, he will need another life for remedying his material nature, and his life will be lost before he has found a trace or vestige of God”.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Although a man has no power over what is vicious in his constitution, he can get an attribute changed by Divine aid and by resigning himself to God’s will and by divesting himself of his own power and strength. In reality, when he resigns himself, God protects him; and through God’s protection he comes nearer to annihilating the evil than he does through self-mortification, since flies are more easily driven away with an umbrella (mikanna) than with a fly-whisk (midhabba).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The saint is annihilated in his own state and subsistent in the contemplation of the Truth: he cannot tell anything concerning himself, nor can he rest with anyone except God,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>to communicate one’s hidden state to another is to reveal the secret of the Beloved, which cannot be revealed except to the Beloved himself. Moreover, in contemplation it is impossible to regard aught except God:</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The saint hath no fear, because fear is the expectation either of some future calamity or of the eventual loss of some object of desire, whereas the saint is the son of his time (ibn waqtihi): he has no future that he should fear anything; and as he hath no fear so he hath no hope, since hope is the expectation either of gaining an object of desire or of being relieved from a misfortune, and this belongs to the future; nor does he grieve, because grief arises from the rigour of time, and. how should he feel grief who is in the radiance of satisfaction (riḍá) and the garden of concord (muwáfaqat)?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Fear and hope and security and grief all refer to the interests of the lower soul, and when that is annihilated satisfaction (riḍá) becomes an attribute of Man, and when satisfaction has been attained his states become steadfast (mustaqím) in vision of the Author of states (muḥawwil), and his back is turned on all states. Then saintship is revealed to his heart and its meaning is made clear to his inmost thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Do not covet anything in this world or the next, and devote thyself entirely to God, and turn to God with all thy heart.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is no “station” on the way to the Truth where any obligation of service is abolished.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>thou hast busied thyself with correcting thy exterior for the sake of God’s creatures, hence thou art afraid of them; but it has been my business to correct my interior for God’s sake, hence His creatures are afraid of me.’”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Abraham, in the beginning of his state, looked on the sun and said: “This is my Lord,” and he looked on the moon and stars and said: “This is my Lord” (Kor. vi, 76–8), because his heart was overwhelmed by the Truth and he was united in the essence of union.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In annihilation there is no love or hate, and in subsistence there is no consciousness of union or separation. Some wrongly imagine that annihilation signifies loss of essence and destruction of personality, and that subsistence indicates the subsistence of God in Man; both these notions are absurd.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I have no knowledge either of them or of myself.” This is an excellent indication of “presence”.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>faith is really the absorption of all human attributes in the search of God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Real faith is trust in God.’”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>outward and inward purification must go together; e.g., when a man washes his hands he must wash his heart clean of worldliness, and when he puts water in his mouth he must purify his mouth from the mention of other than God, and when he washes his face he must turn away from all familiar objects and turn towards God, and when he wipes his head he must resign his affairs to God, and when he washes his feet he must not form the intention of taking his stand on anything except according to the command of God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>They argue that the penitent is a lover of God, and the lover of God is in contemplation of God, and in contemplation it is wrong to remember sin, for remembrance of sin is a veil between God and those who contemplate Him.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Do not let any thought of ostentation (they say) enter your heart, and worship God wherever you will.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>in the Kitáb-i Maḥabbat1 that God created the souls (dilhá) seven thousand years before the bodies and kept them in the station of proximity (qurb) and that he created the spirits (jánhá) seven thousand years before the souls and kept them in the degree of intimacy (uns), and that he created the hearts (sirrhá) seven thousand years before the spirits and kept them in the degree of union (waṣl), and revealed the epiphany of His beauty to the heart three hundred and sixty times every day and bestowed on it three hundred and sixty looks of grace, and He caused the spirits to hear the word of love and manifested three hundred and sixty exquisite favours of intimacy to the soul,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Real love is neither diminished by unkindness nor increased by kindness and bounty,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To learn and obtain knowledge is an essential obligation, and to profess one’s self independent of knowledge is mere infidelity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the fast of David, which the Apostle called the best of fasts, i.e. they fasted one day and broke their fast the next day.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Once I came into the presence of Shaykh Aḥmad Bukhárí. He had a dish of sweetmeat (ḥalwá) before him, from which he was eating, and he made a sign to me that I should do the same. As is the way of young men, I answered (without consideration) that I was fasting. He asked why. I said: “In conformity with such and such a one.” He said: “It is not right for human beings to conform with human beings.” I was about to break my fast, but he said: “Since you wish to be quit of conformity with him, do not conform with me, for I too am a human being.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“When you fast, let your ear fast and your eye and your tongue and your hand and every limb;”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Four of the senses have a particular locus, but the fifth, namely touch, is spread over the whole body.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To abstain only from food and drink is child’s play. One must abstain from idle pleasures and unlawful acts, not from eating lawful food.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>he had tasted no food for eighty days and had not missed a single occasion of public worship.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>had not missed a single occasion of public worship.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I wonder at those who seek His temple in this world: why do not they seek contemplation of Him in their hearts? The temple they sometimes attain and sometimes miss, but contemplation they might enjoy always. If they are bound to visit a stone, which is looked at only once a year, surely they are more bound to visit the temple of the heart, where He may be seen three hundred and sixty times in a day and night.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Anyone who is absent from God at Mecca is in the same position as if he were absent from God in his own house, and anyone who is present with God in his own house is in the same position as if he were present with God at Mecca.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“O God, hide Paradise and Hell in Thy unseen places, that Thou mayest be worshipped disinterestedly.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our wishing is the greatest of the veils that hinder us from seeing God, because in love the existence of self-will is disobedience, and disobedience is a veil. When self-will vanishes in this world, contemplation is attained, and when contemplation is firmly established, there is no difference between this world and the next.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>contemplation is an attribute of the heart (sirr)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>not eat large mouthfuls, and should chew his food well and not make haste;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When he has finished eating, he should give praise to God and wash his hands.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Apostle, whom God chose and whom He raised to the highest rank, did not force himself either to sleep or to wake.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>speech is like wine: it intoxicates the mind, and those who begin to have a taste for it cannot abstain from it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You should live in the present, and let no thought of the morrow enter your mind, else you will incur everlasting perdition. You should not make God a springe to catch alms, and you should not display piety in order that more alms may be given to you on account of your piety.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The evils of celibacy are two: (1) the neglect of an Apostolic custom, (2) the fostering of lust in the heart and the danger of falling into unlawful ways. The evils of marriage are also two: (1) the preoccupation of the mind with other than God, (2) the distraction of the body for the sake of sensual pleasure.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>neither state (marriage or celibacy) should be regarded with predilection, in order that we may see what the decree of Divine providence will bring to light: if celibacy be our lot, we should strive to be chaste, and if marriage be our destiny, we should comply with the custom of the Apostle and strive to clear our hearts (of worldly anxieties).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Accordingly, a man is not ruined by marriage or by celibacy, but the mischief consists in asserting one’s will and in yielding to one’s desires.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the way of the elect is to see only the Causer, and not to see the cause.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“O Jesus, hast thou no fear of being cut off (from God)?” and Jesus used to say, “O John, hast thou no hope of God’s mercy? Neither thy tears nor my smiles will change the eternal decree of God.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I desire only that God should desire for me, and therein preserve me from the evil thereof and save me from the wickedness of my soul.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ṣúfís do not intend to blame the man for having acquired knowledge, they blame him for neglecting the practice of religion, because the ’álim depends on himself, but the ’árif depends on his Lord.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the Law without the Truth is ostentation, and the Truth without the Law is hypocrisy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Shaykh used to say that a novice without shurb is a stranger to (i.e. unacquainted with the duties of) the novitiate, and that a gnostic with shurb is a stranger to gnosis, because the novice must derive some pleasure (shurbí) from his actions in order that he may fulfil the obligations of a novice who is seeking God; but the gnostic ought not to feel such pleasure, lest he should be transported with that pleasure instead of with God: if he turn back to his lower soul he will not rest (with God).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>because speech is a sort of pride and hearing is a sort of humility.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Its lawfulness depends on circumstances and cannot be asserted absolutely: if audition produces a lawful effect on the mind, then it is lawful; it is unlawful if the effect is unlawful, and permissible if the effect is permissible.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“O God, let us see things as they are.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is necessary that thy audition should be continuous and uninterrupted.” This saying is a token of the concentration of his thoughts in the field of love. When a man attains so high a degree as this he hears (spiritual truths) from every object in the universe.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Give me wine to drink and tell me it is wine. Do not give it me in secret, when it can be given openly”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>let my eye see it and my hand touch it and my palate taste it and my nose smell it: there yet remains one sense to be gratified, viz. my hearing: tell me, therefore, this is wine, that my ear may feel the same delight as my other senses.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>wujúd is a thrill of emotion in contemplation of God, and emotion (ṭarab) cannot be reached by investigation (ṭalab).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the only finder is God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Junayd said, “He who seeks shall find.” Shiblí cried, “No; he who finds shall seek.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There are two ways: one of knowledge and one of action. Action without knowledge, although it may be good, is ignorant and imperfect, but knowledge, even if it be unaccompanied by action, is glorious and noble.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“without experience no knowledge.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>that He may preserve me both outwardly and inwardly from contamination, and I enjoin the readers of this book to hold it in due regard and to pray that the author may believe to the end and be vouchsafed the vision of God (in Paradise).</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-04-21-kashf-al-mahjub.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Living Presence</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-04-07-living-presence.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1309283839i/700483.jpg" /></p>
<h1 id="living-presence-a-sufi-way-to-mindfulness-the-essential-self">Living Presence: A Sufi Way to Mindfulness &amp; the Essential Self</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>the real Work is to serve, to pay attention to how other human beings can be helped toward freedom and love by being an example of those qualities without expectation of any recognition or reward.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Furthermore, what attracts us in the outer world is only putting us in touch with the hidden treasure within us. Through finding it in ourselves we are returned to the Being that we reflect. We are not the originators of qualities, but the reflectors of the infinite qualities of Being.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>that point where the horizontal force of active choice meets the vertical force of Being, a certain “something,” larger than life, will be activated. This “something” can be felt in anything produced by the hands and heart of a conscious human being—in works of art, in a well-tended garden, in food prepared with love.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In sacred art, performance is not a means of ego gratification but an offering to the Divine. What is offered is everyone’s attention, and yet everyone is elevated in this sacred alchemy and feels a change of consciousness through this quality of performance and the attention offered.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As much as we are the servants of Spirit, Spirit is our servant when we make our connection to it. This connection is made through presence, which is a receptivity to the energies of possibility.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a human being is whatever his or her attention is focused on.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Attention develops as the gatekeeper of all our impressions. We learn not to let the mind wander too far from the essential Self, even while we are open to outer things. More and more we work to keep our attention on Being itself. We can learn to call upon a very refined attention, to keep an awareness of the deepest truths in the most ordinary circumstances. This can be done only if our attention is not easily coerced and distracted.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>child to experience an environment of love, support, and trust.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>desire (eros), friendship (philia), or unconditional love (agape).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we can become nothing by limiting our habitual self-centered thoughts. This will cut at the root of our egotism, because ego exists in our thinking.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we could just be, we would be able to escape the anxiety of becoming something that we are not, getting something we don’t have, and trying to shape reality according to our own desires.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>what we most need is what we already are: our essential Self. There is no escape; there is only coming home.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Submission is to live for one’s Self—the eternal I—not for one’s ego.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>(Divani Shamsi Tabriz 120):</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The tamer of the ego is love. We must learn to love even the ego; then the ego can submit to that love. Perhaps we need to consider what the ego is and how to live with it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We need to establish a subtle balance—the ego in harmonious cocreatorship with the Spirit.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is essential to learn to relax within the tensions of life. We cannot escape conflict in this world, but we can learn to relax within it. This has nothing to do with running from conflict and certainly nothing to do with repressing it. This relaxation has aspects of trust, surrender, and submission. Balance is necessary.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>obstacles are the neurotic manifestations of ego that are produced by various kinds of physical, mental, and emotional tensions, whether aggressiveness, timidity, self-righteousness, self-doubt, arrogance, shame, hypocrisy, envy, jealousy, suspicion, or greed. In such states the ego will work overtime to maintain itself and its illusions. And we may not be aware how these tensions distort our features, and our souls.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We can be thankful for our faults, for they can keep us humble and aware of our dependence on a higher Reality, without which we would never be transformed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Let go of your worries and be completely clear-hearted, like the face of a mirror that contains no images. When it is empty of forms, all forms are contained within it. No face would be ashamed to be so clear.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Work is to bring the outer and the inner into harmony.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This requires attention to our intention. If our intention is clear and sound, and if it is periodically remembered and reaffirmed, there will be a mental, emotional, and practical integration in realizing the intention.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“There is a polish for everything,” said Muhammad, peace and blessings upon him, “and the polish for the heart is the remembrance of God”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Since in order to speak, one must first listen, learn to speak by listening.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Attention can be called the first act of the will.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>not really enjoying their company or giving them my real attention.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we live with a real question and a sense of purpose, the whole mind is more likely to function harmoniously and creatively. More and more we will also begin to have experiences of pure presence free of thought. Opening to life without preconception, without the veil of habitual thought, we will perceive Being.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Humility is the foremost act of worship”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If attention is not connected to will, a human is not fully a human being.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What can you do with will that you can’t do without it? A day later the answer came simple and clear: Be free.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We learn that awareness of our breath and physical presence can greatly assist this gathering. And we learn that to be identified with any single function, such as thinking or feeling, is to lose that comprehensive self-awareness we call “presence.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The secret to developing an integrated self is to intentionally extend awareness to more than one function at a time. Each function that comes into awareness adds another coordinate to our conscious existence. If, for instance, we are fully occupied with an emotion and become aware of our breathing or our physical sensations, we have generated more presence. If those of us who live mostly in our heads, in repetitive and limited thinking, both add an awareness of something physical such as our breathing and come into touch with our feelings, we have extended our presence greatly. We have more coordinates. Instead of a one-dimensional person we have suddenly become a three- or four-dimensional person.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>all outer things are reminders of Being itself: Wherever you look is the face of the Friend. Eventually this process can become circular—presence welling up inside us and moving outward, the outer world being consciously recognized and returned to its source through our awareness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we can use the body to develop greater presence</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Salaah is a form that integrates mindfulness, mental precision, affirmation, devotion, and stretching.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>unconscious theta state can be facilitated by increasing the length of time of exhalation, as in many forms of chanting or singing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>have faith means to have a center, an axis, a single point of reference. And yet this point of reference is not necessarily apparent from the start;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“We must not wish for the disappearance of our troubles but the grace to transform them.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every problem calls forth qualities from the hidden treasure within us. Accepting more responsibility and challenges brings a greater activation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>humility, gratitude, and love.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our essential will and presence stand outside time and space, relatively free and pure. This presence is more ourselves than the impulses with which we might identify. Some people may argue that to go with every impulse is natural and spontaneous; on the contrary, this response represents the depths of conditioning and mechanicality. It is not free will, but slavery. Freedom lies in the altogether different direction of conscious will that frees us from habit, conditioning, and reactive behaviors.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The secret of transformation is the moment-by-moment alchemy of impulse. This may manifest itself as restraint in action and speech, as courtesy, self-discipline, generosity, subtlety, or patience.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Weakness leads to weakness, just as strength leads to strength.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>An aim should be specific and attainable, and it should be consistent with the general aim of the Work, which is awakening.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To work on awakening is to extract attention or awareness from the stream of events, to cultivate an awareness that includes events, thoughts, and feelings but is not totally absorbed or identified with them. It involves an intention above all to be actively receptive, to be alive with sensitivity and attention, not to be thoroughly identified with one’s conditioning. Our intention to be awake is helped by deciding to interrupt our unconsciousness by setting intentional alarms for ourselves.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The more our sense of identity and well-being depends upon what we possess or what people think of us, the less we are aware of our own intrinsic worth and, consequently, the more we are enslaved to the fear of loss.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Presence provides space—spatial dimension around our experiences, both inner and outer. In a sense, what we really are is that spaciousness, even more than what fills the space. With this spaciousness we can allow transformation to happen.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>intimacy for me is here in service.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“A seeker would never offer fear as an excuse for anything. Fear is not accepted by one who has a quest.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>is God to be literally feared? In the Qur’an the word taqwa is often translated as “fear,” but it would be better translated as “vigilance,” “awe,” or “God consciousness.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The lover has only one fear, and that is the fear of offending the Beloved (which includes harming other people). The fear of God frees the lover of all other fears. This is the only kind of fear appropriate for one who is courting the Truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Stringency ultimately is in service to Mercy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Take refuge in My Mercy from My Wrath. Take refuge in Me from</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Presence allows us to open to the suffering of the world; compassion is being able to feel the world’s suffering without being drowned by it. Perhaps it is in accepting our servanthood, in opening to the suffering of the world, that we ourselves are further transformed and acquire the qualities of the Creative Power. Loving-kindness</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“the Friend speaks to us in many forms. We are all beloved here, and we are all receptive to the Truth and so the Truth can easily express itself. Know that the ‘you’ who felt special last night and the ‘you’ who felt diminished tonight are neither real. Prostrate them before the inner Friend if you want to find wisdom and be free of judging yourself.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whenever we think we are better than others or whenever we think, “I want,” we are thinking of ourselves in the wrong way. When we can think differently—“my family needs this, my body needs this, my work needs this, help me to meet these needs, help me to reflect your abundance”—we can open to the inflow of spiritual energy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>True service is giving of ourselves, of what we naturally are.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Presence is the empty center that attracts and manifests the qualities of Spirit.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The seeker [dervish or Sufi] stands at the threshold between freedom and slavery.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Make all your cares into a single care and God will see to all your cares. Be mindful of Him and He will be at your side”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Work informs us that freedom is found in surrender, trust, and friendship with the One. This freedom grows as we discover the qualities of the Friend within ourselves: generosity, patience, acceptance, truthfulness, and courage.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>your Lord wants you to know that your calling him is his answer to you.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What we contemplate we become.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It gives back to us what we give to it, only more</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What we love we will become</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>TWO QUALITIES THAT ARE SAID to be necessary to worship and prayer are recollection and humility. We begin by recollecting ourselves and</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We gather the whole of ourselves into a single sincere act, calling upon this slumbering spiritual essence within us</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If a human being consistently directs his attention, desire, will, thought, and feeling in the direction of Love, the Love thus realized becomes a vital power and capacity. When we do so, we are also preparing ourselves to remember this Love spontaneously at other times.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Worship may include conscious breathing, chanting, singing, and movement.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we must be in a state of worship always and everywhere. In addition to the traditional forms and rituals of our great sacred traditions, worship may yet take forms that are entirely new and creative, for what is of Spirit is creative.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Love brings together what needs to be brought together.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>service without presence is sleep, and if we are identified with service, if we expect thanks or some reward, it instead becomes a demand. It is good to do what is right and feel good about it. It is good to serve those whom we love. It is necessary to contribute to the general welfare through generous and public-spirited action. All of this is basic to a decent human life, but it is not yet at the level of spiritual practice. The service that is spiritual practice is beyond attraction and beyond the limited ego. This service depends on a shift of awareness. Through it we are lifted out of our egoism; in it we become motivated by unconditional love of the life around us. It is the Beloved loving through us and the Generous giving through us. Even anger and criticism can be welcomed when it is from the Beloved, while the help and praise of those who “serve” with arrogance or self-righteousness feels like poison to us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Any action without presence is mechanical, and any step outward requires a corresponding step inward. If we are to truly grow in service, we must simultaneously grow in presence. The more our inner faculties are engaged, the more service will come naturally.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What is worship? To realize Reality. What is the sacred law? To do no evil. What is Reality? Selflessness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Remembering God is the beginning of remembering ourselves.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-04-07-living-presence.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Awakening Guide</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-02-21-awakening-guide.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1400808900i/22299490.jpg" /></p>
<h1 id="the-awakening-guide-a-companion-for-the-inward-journey">The Awakening Guide: A Companion for the Inward Journey</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>Imagine yourself to be the spaciousness in the room you sit, instead of the object, your body. Then go within and be the spaciousness that sits within you, instead of the subtle objects, which are the thoughts and emotions of personal identity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>new perceptions and beliefs can become another cloud over the true nature if they become concepts about how things ought to be. In time, as the phenomena fade, the mind and emotions can react with a sense of loss, and many old conditioned patterns may return.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>development of a flexible mind, not so set in its ways, and willing to surrender itself into the unknown. We must trust emptiness when we encounter it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a quality called transmission that is not about the movement of energy so much as the resonance of pure consciousness, from itself to itself. That is, the consciousness that knows itself in the teacher, also knows itself as the other, you. It makes no distinction. To be seen this way through the body of an apparent “other” puts one at the threshold of realization.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>your true Self, which doesn’t want anything, ever. It can enjoy whatever is available, but it has no demands! You have a choice, you can suffer the wanting, or you can be free. This is the essence of surrender, to let go of wanting, to let go of the me.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>each movement of believing in thought is a movement away from the moment, where there is clarity and simple presence. When a condition is directly in front of you that obviously needs attention you are free to respond spontaneously and creatively.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You have to be very alert, or else your mind will play false with you. It is like watching a thief – not that you expect anything from a thief, but you do not want to be robbed. In the same way you give a lot of attention to the mind without expecting anything from it.” (Nisardagatta Maharaj (1994). I Am That, Acorn</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The key is always bringing what’s unconscious into consciousness. I suggest that people who have something they cannot get beyond go home and write down everything it believes until its exhausted itself.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To embody it is the practice.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it is best not to be attached to them, not to re-identify as the person with these skills, and to hold them lightly with wonder and gratitude rather than passion. If no “powers” emerge this is not a sign of a lack in your awakening.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>whatever he needs to know is there when he needs it, but not a moment before.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You simply become willing to live in the unknown, and listen to your deepest inclinations.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Whenever you see a great darkness, you can be certain at the core is a great light.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We need to know in our cells what it means, personally and individually, one by one, for the use of the Whole.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our purpose exists in the moment, rather than the future.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-02-21-awakening-guide.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Contemplative Prayer</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-02-07-contemplative-prayer.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1359986111i/351723.jpg" /></p>
<h1 id="contemplative-prayer">Contemplative Prayer</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>necessary to use many words. Only</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>For the monk searches not only his own heart: he plunges deep into the heart of that world of which he remains a part although he seems to have “left” it. In reality the monk abandons the world only in order to listen more intently to the deepest and most neglected voices that proceed from its inner depth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the monk’s chief service to the world: this silence, this listening, this questioning, this humble and courageous exposure to what the world ignores about itself—both good and evil.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>cannot fill a heart that has not previously been humbled and emptied by dread</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it is not only a means to an end, but also has something of the nature of an end.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a wordless and total surrender of the heart in silence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you love truth, be a lover of silence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the sunlight will illuminate you in God and will deliver you from the phantoms of ignorance. Silence will unite you to God himself. … More</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>More than all things love silence: it brings you a fruit that tongue cannot describe. In the beginning we have to force ourselves to be silent. But then there is born something that draws us to silence. May God give you an experience of this “something” that is born of silence. If only you practice this, untold light will dawn on you in consequence … after a while a certain sweetness is born in the heart of this exercise and the body is drawn almost by force to remain in silence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>conscious awareness of and dependence on God. Once again, the forms taken by this “awareness” are not defined or prescribed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The concept of “the heart” might well be analyzed here. It refers to the deepest psychological ground of one’s personality, the inner sanctuary where self-awareness goes beyond analytical reflection and opens out into metaphysical and theological confrontation with the Abyss of the unknown yet present—one who is “more intimate to us than we are to ourselves.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>in the Spirit of God we “see” God our Father without “seeing.” We know him in “unknowing.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We should not, however, judge the value of our meditation by “how we feel.” A hard and apparently fruitless meditation may in fact be much more valuable than one that is easy, happy, enlightened and apparently a big success.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When one is simply obeying God, a little effort goes a long way. When one is in fact resisting him (though claiming to have no other intention than that of fulfilling his will) no amount of effort can produce a good result.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The only trouble is that in the spiritual life there are no tricks and no short cuts. Those who imagine that they can discover special gimmicks and put them to work for themselves usually ignore God’s will and his grace. They are self-confident and even self-complacent. They make up their minds that they are going to attain to this or that, and try to write their own ticket in the life of contemplation. They may even appear to succeed to some extent. But certain systems of spirituality—notably Zen Buddhism—place great stress on a severe, no-nonsense style of direction that makes short work of this kind of confidence. One cannot begin to face the real difficulties of the life of prayer and meditation unless one is first perfectly content to be a beginner and really experience himself as one who knows little or nothing, and has a desperate need to learn the bare rudiments.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Those who think they “know” from the beginning will never, in fact, come to know anything. People who try to pray and meditate above their proper level, who are too eager to reach what they believe to be “a high degree of prayer,” get away from the truth and from reality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Acedia follows the enthusiasm of pride and spiritual vanity. A long course in humility and compunction is the remedy! We do not want to be beginners. But let us be convinced of the fact that we will never be anything else but beginners, all our life!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Meditation has no point and no reality unless it is firmly rooted in life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>more and more directed to an obedient and cooperative submission to grace, which implies first of all an increasingly attentive and receptive attitude toward the hidden action of the Holy Spirit. It is precisely the function of meditation, in the sense in which we speak of it here, to bring us to this attitude of awareness and receptivity. It also gives us strength and hope, along with a deep awareness of the value of interior silence in which the mystery of God’s love is made clear to us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the prayer of the heart has to be always very simple, confined to the simplest of acts and often making use of no words and no thoughts at all.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>love on a simply human plane, it does so in order to fill them with a higher and purer light which is “darkness” to sense and to reason. The darkening is therefore at the same time an enlightenment. God darkens the mind only in order to give a more perfect light.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the “dark night of faith,” one passes from meditation, in the sense of active “mental prayer,” to contemplation, or a deeper and simpler intuitive form of receptivity, in which, if one can be said to “meditate” at all, one does so only by receiving the light with passive and loving attention.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>in every action we beg from God the success of our labors and satisfy our debt of gratitude to him … and when we keep before our minds the aim of pleasing him.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>God works in us while we rest in him. Beyond all grasping is this work of the Creator, itself creative, this rest. For such work exceeds all rest, in its tranquility. This rest, in its effect, shines forth as more productive than any work. Therefore let this action or rest of our contemplation be fashioned so as to reproduce, even though only in faint or sketchy lines, one model (of work and rest which is in God). …</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We seek rather to gain a direct existential grasp, a personal experience of the deepest truths of life and faith, finding ourselves in God’s truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The dark night rectifies our deepest intentions. In the silence of this “night of faith” we return to simplicity and sincerity of heart.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>St. Augustine’s words: Noverim te, noverim me.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>purity of heart, an unconditional and totally humble surrender to God, a total acceptance of ourselves and of our situation as willed by him. It means the renunciation of all deluded images of ourselves, all exaggerated estimates of our own capacities, in order to obey God’s will as it comes to us in the difficult demands of life in its exacting truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>must use my freedom in order to love, with full responsibility and authenticity,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the “grace of meditation” (in the sense of “prayer of the heart”) is also a special gift. It should never be taken for granted.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a permanent disposition to humility, attention to reality, receptivity, pliability.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The sacrifices that are not chosen are often of greater value than those we select for ourselves.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the terrible experience of being apparently without faith in order to really grow in faith. For it is this testing, this fire of purgation, that burns out the human and accidental elements of faith in order to liberate the deep spiritual power in the center of our being.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Just as the light that shows us all has no need of another light in order to be seen, so God, who shows us all things, has no need of a light in which we may see him, for he is himself light by essence,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Only when we are able to “let go” of everything within us, all desire to see, to know, to taste and to experience the presence of God, do we truly become able to experience that presence with the overwhelming conviction and reality that revolutionize our entire inner life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>for us the mystery contains, within its own darkness and its own silences, a presence and a meaning which we apprehend without fully understanding them.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-02-07-contemplative-prayer.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Natural Liberation</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-01-26-natural-liberation.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1388340683i/604500.jpg" /></p>
<h1 id="natural-liberation-padmasambhavas-teachings-on-the-six-bardos">Natural Liberation: Padmasambhava’s Teachings on the Six Bardos</h1>
<blockquote>
<ol type="1">
<li>pondering the sufferings of the cycle of existence, (2) the difficulty of obtaining a human life of leisure and endowment, and (3) meditating on death and impermanence are the preliminary practices for subduing your own mind-stream. The preliminary practices for training your own mind-stream include: (4) guru yoga, (5) the hundred-syllable mantra, and finally (6) the spiritual activity of offering the maṇḍala.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Think of death, and bring your practice to its culmination.     There is no time to waste in life, and the circumstances that lead to death are beyond imagination.     Then if you fail to achieve the confidence of fearlessness,     What is the point of your being alive?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We should practice “until the experience of them arises</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Settling the mind in its natural state. In settling the mind in its natural state, there are also three parts: while keeping the body and speech as they were before, let your mind be lucid, without engaging any thoughts concerning earlier or later deceptive appearances of the three times; inwardly, settle the mind evenly without engaging in any good thoughts, such as deity meditation; secretly, settle the mind in its natural state by letting it be just as it is, steadily, clearly, and lucidly in the space in front of you, in the mind’s own mode of existence, without bringing to mind any of the mentally engaging thoughts of the view and meditation which entail mental grasping. Do that for three days.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>place in front of you a small object such as a stick or pebble. Gaze at it steadily without closing your eyes, and at the same time place your attention upon it steadily, clearly, and lucidly, without being distracted by anything else. Do not strenuously thrust your attention at it. Vividly settle your awareness simply on the unwavering meditative support without succumbing to any ordinary distractions. Remain clear, gently release into a sense of comfort, and relax a bit. Meanwhile, rest the mind naturally, unwaveringly, and steadily upon that meditative support, without entering into the dispersal of thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Rest your gaze simply so that you don’t lose your awareness of space.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it’s better to have as many sessions of short duration as we can throughout the day.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When bringing the session to a close, do not rise from it abruptly; rather, with a sense of conscientiousness, gently integrate it with your behavior and transform this into the path. Let all your conduct be like that of a person with a concussion who is afraid of getting bumped, and conscientiously lead your life in a meditative fashion. Do that for three days.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Next, place your body in the proper posture and so on, like before. For your meditative object, vividly direct your attention simply, without wavering, to a white, radiant, clear, limpid bindu at the point between your eyebrows. About the size of a white pea, it appears but is without an inherent nature. Gently release in clarity and joy, and settle your mind in its natural state. Do not be interrupted by thoughts. Meditate just like that, with many sessions of short duration, as before. Engage in that meditation for three days or as your own experience dictates. Whatever experiences occur from time to time, examine them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>gently recognize the thoughts. Even if you impede them, they will not stop. Without following after them, focus on the meditative object. By so doing, thoughts will become more and more subtle, and they will decrease in number.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Each time a thought arises, recognize it immediately and release it so that it naturally vanishes. If two thoughts arise, recognize them. Do not follow after anything that appears, but let it arise and be released. At times, focus on the meditative object; and at times, let thoughts arise and vanish. While not fabricating anything in their wake, relax and release. By alternately practicing like that, the chain of compulsive ideation will become disconnected, and thoughts will become fragmented. Thus, detrimental thoughts will become fewer and fewer, and fine stability will arise. Meditate in that way for three days or as your experience dictates.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Maintaining the body in the posture bearing the seven attributes of Vairocana, let the spine be erect and straight, and press the hands against the ground. While so doing, completely exhale three times, once through the right nostril, once through the left, and once from the middle. Simultaneously imagine that sins and obscurations are purified, and that the sins are discharged from your nostrils in the form of scorpions and are then incinerated in the roaring flames of the fire of primordial wisdom in the space in front of you. This expels the toxins of the vital energies. Then together with your inhalation, while swallowing your saliva once, scrunch down beneath the navel; and without thinking of any meditative object, rest your awareness in clarity. When you can do so no more, completely exhale. Do that for three days.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Expel the residual vital energy and position your body as before. Now when you inhale, imagine the physical blessings of all the buddhas of the three times being drawn in in the form of a white syllable OṂ. Then push the upper vital energy down, draw the lower vital energy up, and gather them together beneath the navel.         In the midst of the “closed amulet” of the upper and lower vital energies, imagine the essence of the speech of all the buddhas of the three times in the nature of a clear, empty, vivid red syllable ĀḤ, which appears but is without an inherent nature.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>vajra-recitations of the three syllables, so practice it continuously. Do that for three days, then do it constantly</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>alternate between intense concentration and relaxation. There are various ways to maintain mindfulness throughout the day, one of which is constantly to sustain the awareness of space. Another way to maintain mindfulness is the vajra-recitation. Whatever technique you follow, it’s very important that between sessions you don’t discard the practice altogether.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Alternate between observing who is concentrating inwardly and who is releasing. If it is the mind, ask, “What is that very agent that releases the mind and concentrates the mind?” Steadily observe yourself, and then release again. By so doing, fine stability will arise, and you may even identify awareness. Do that, too, for one day.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Let the awareness itself steadily observe itself. At times, let your mind come to rest in the center of your heart, and evenly leave it there. At times, evenly focus it in the expanse of the sky and leave it there. Thus, by shifting the gaze in various, alternating ways, the mind settles in its natural state.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In this particular technique, you are indeed resting your awareness in the space in front; but your awareness must be imbued with the three qualities of mindfulness, introspection, and conscientiousness</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if we’re following the Mahāyāna path and discern faults in others, then the appropriate response is compassion. If we’re following the Vajrayāna, engaging in the stages of generation and completion, then we must cultivate a pure view, seeing others in their divine aspects. In this case, others’ faults are not an issue, for this pure view saturates our entire awareness of the world. Furthermore, if we’re engaging in the practice of Atiyoga, our view is beyond the parameters of pure and impure. With this view, we experience an equality, or “equal taste,” of all phenomena. The very notions of purity and impurity don’t even arise. In terms of faults then, we should point to ourselves, for finding fault in others is our own disgrace.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Recognize your faults and let them be perfectly obvious to yourself.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>practice with a powerful sense that daytime appearances are dreams. Even the least of practitioners will apprehend the dream-state within one month.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As soon as novices recognize, “This is a dream!” they wake up and there is dispersal of that recognition.43 To dispel that, maintain your attention at the level of the heart</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To transform the fruit into the path, you practice without hope of accomplishing anything and without fear of not accomplishing anything.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>First practice in short sessions, and as you become accustomed to it, practice in longer and longer sessions. When you bring the session to an end, do not get up abruptly, but rise slowly without losing the sense of meditating; and proceed without losing the sense of awareness, without wavering, and without grasping. As you eat, drink, speak, and engage in every activity, do so without losing the sentry of unwavering mindfulness. If this happens in meditative equipoise but not afterwards, by integrating this with your spiritual practice and all activities of moving, walking, lying down, and sitting, whatever you do will appear as meditation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Without any manner of placing awareness anywhere, letting it be in its own state, without modification, is meditation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>too much effort and tension in your practice can create problems. You’re straining hard, trying to hold onto the object, which appears to be unstable. To counteract such excessive tension, lighten up. Ease up a bit in the meditation. Let your mind be more spacious.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The key to being free of the craving of samādhi is to release grasping. The best student is an “instantaneous person” who gains realization as soon as the nature of awareness is pointed out.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>your actions do have karmic consequences. It’s important to be extremely conscientious about the nature of our activities. Like the first person in the story, we need to be conscientious about our actions. It’s important that we do practice; it’s important that we do cultivate compassion; and it’s very important that we do not make a mistake.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Don’t try to cover up unpleasant subjects, face them. That’s the best response.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>mentally offer everything that you have, including not only your material possessions, but also your relatives and everyone around you. Release attachment for everything.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>lying on your right side the vital energies will move from the left nostril.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you have nothing physical to offer or no altar to put it on, this is no problem. Offer your body, speech, and mind and don’t be upset. That’s fine. This option of simply offering your body, speech, and mind is a good one.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If I am to die suddenly, I must focus on the crown of my head.” This resolve is of essential importance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s important to know the meaning of the object of your reverence and to be familiar with the excellent qualities of the objects of refuge.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Start with many short sessions, then gradually increase the duration of each one, and decrease the number of sessions per day.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>attachment, aversion, and delusion are to be banished, like a poisonous snake. Especially the poison of attachment is to be eliminated.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whether for hearing, thinking, or meditation, the motivation is paramount.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>by training in regarding all appearances as being like reflections in a mirror, appearing and yet devoid of an inherent nature, such that appearances and emptiness are indivisible, the deceptive appearances of the daytime will arise as pure visions. Due to that, one is free from clinging onto the true existence of dreams, and one either recognizes the dream-state as the dream-state, or it arises as the clear light.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>illusory nature of everything you experience. Becoming accustomed to that during the daytime places imprints upon your mind-stream; and these carry over into the dream-state, so this pure vision also occurs at night.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>These companions I meet today and this evening, relatives, and fellow travelers have also died and are wandering with me in the transitional process. They are not truly existent, and like a dream and an illusion, they have no objective existence, or true existence.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Resting the mind in its unstructured, originally pure state means that you do not follow after any thoughts that arise, be they virtuous or nonvirtuous. Thus, whatever comes up in the mind, you let it come up and let it be without reacting to it, without classifying it, and without responding to it or trying to modify it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whatever comes up, don’t block it. As soon as you try to block it, you’ve lost the nature of it; and you’re no longer doing this practice. If you feel that you must do something to make the thoughts go away, you’re not doing the practice. If you feel you need to sustain these mental events, again you’re not doing the practice. The practice here is to allow awareness to rest in its own natural state, originally pure.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The purpose of this meditation is to cultivate the constant awareness, day and night, of the lack of true existence of phenomena. In this way, we recognize the manner in which we are normally confused by our grasping onto the true existence of phenomena.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The most practical avenue is to implement these teachings as much as you can right now in your daily life. Let your practice flow into the present, rather than anticipating some future situation that you consider more ideal.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One may be ambitious, energetic, and hard-working in a worldly sense; but, from a Dharma perspective, that person who is working eighteen hours a day is said to be lazy. We are just part of the crowd if we show such stupidity as to waste this opportunity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Do not sleep like an animal,     But practice integrating sleep and direct perception!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The great thing about this practice is that you can sleep and practice at the same time, and in that way gain realization of the clear light. During the daytime, we have the opportunity to engage in hearing, thinking, and meditation and to experience the fruition of the path. And at nighttime, we have the opportunity to hear teachings, ponder them, and put them into practice through the night to gain the fruition of the practice while we’re sleeping.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To enter into the experience that is free of extremes, we must be free of the extremes of nihilism and eternalism.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is best to recognize your own nature. Then you will not need somebody else to liberate you from fictitious problems.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-01-26-natural-liberation.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Wonders of the Natural Mind</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-01-10-wonders-natural-mind.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348186153i/305337.jpg" /></p>
<h1 id="wonders-of-the-natural-mind-the-essence-of-dzogchen-in-the-native-bon-tradition-of-tibet">Wonders of the Natural Mind: The Essence of Dzogchen in the Native Bon Tradition of Tibet</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>The outer cycle is the path of renunciation (spong lain), the Sutra teachings. The inner cycle is the path of transformation (sgyur lam), the Tantric teachings, which use mantras. The secret cycle is the path of self-liberation (grol lam), the Dzogchen teachings. This division into Sutra, Tantra, and Dzogchen (mdo sngags sems gsum) is also found in Tibetan Buddhism.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Self-arising wisdom is the base. The five negative emotions are manifested energy. Seeing emotions as mistaken is an error. Letting them be in their nature is the method To find the non-dual state of Liberation. Overcoming hope and fear is the result.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Tapihritsa is depicted in Dharmakaya form, like Kuntuzangpo, naked and without ornaments.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The view is my master. I practice the nonconceptual state. I meditate on everything I see in the three dimensions (of existence). I am carrying thoughts in my bag. My behavior is to work as the servant of sentient beings. I am going nowhere.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Human or animal, in order to bring the cycle of samsara to an end, we must discover the source of suffering. This is the thinking mind that gives rise to the passions and to attachment. The only way to overcome the poisons of the five passions and their manifestations is to bring the mind under control. This can be done through practicing the teachings that bid us to observe ourselves in order to understand and, through practice, overcome our grasping mind. In this way the teachings guide us to know the underlying nature of the mind and integrate its true condition with our daily life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Defilements, or obscurations, are not in the nature of the mind (sems nyid) but in the moving mind (sems), so they can be purified.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we realize our innate purity but only integrate with it from time to time, we are not totally realized. Being in total integration all the time is final realization.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>even though it is a quality that is innate, we have to develop it. The traditional analogy is to the way the quality of butter already exists in milk: to get the butter we have to chum the milk.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The main point to bear in mind in relation to meditation is to avoid indulging in spiritual fantasies and to remember that the fundamental purpose of the practice is to acquire, maintain, and develop continuity of presence of awareness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>there is nothing spoken about in the teachings that we cannot find in ourselves, in our own experience.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>all that there really is left to do is to sit quietly;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Effort and commitment to practice are necessary. No obstacle that arises in zhine practice, such as laziness or mental agitation, should divert us and no kind of daily activity should distract us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we start to meditate, it is best to alternate short sessions of formal practice with rest periods, gradually increasing the duration of the sessions as we become more accustomed to relaxing in the calm state of mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Prepare a piece of indigo paper one inch square with the Tibetan letter A drawn as illustrated on page 89. The A should be enclosed in five concentric, colored circles. The central circle should be indigo. This should be surrounded by green, red, yellow, and white in that order. (If one feels uncomfortable with the Tibetan letter, an English “A” can be used in its place.) Place the paper on a stick high enough so that the square can rest about one and one half feet in front of your nose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We must not blink the eyes or inhibit the flowing of “the three waters”: saliva from the mouth, mucus from the nose, and tears from the eyes. These must be allowed to flow freely, because we must concentrate and not allow these reflex actions to distract us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we should concentrate as if we were putting a thread into the eye of a needle. As regards the mind, we should neither think of the past nor the future, nor should we try to change the present situation. We must simply maintain presence of awareness of the A, but without thinking about the A, and concentrate as intensely as possible. We must not lose awareness of the A even for a second. It is important to distinguish between simply maintaining presence of awareness of the A, that is, directing the attention continuously to the A without the stream of attention being distracted, and actively thinking about the A, which is merely creating another thought.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Thoughts cannot be liberated by other thoughts: “good” thoughts cannot liberate “bad” thoughts, just as blood cannot wash away blood from a hand. “Good” and “bad” thoughts are both obstacles to direct understanding of the natural state, which is beyond thought, and thought cannot understand what is beyond thought. Understanding of the natural state can only be direct understanding not mediated by thought; it is the empty nature of the mind understanding itself.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>thoughts are the movement of the mind and are of the same nature as the natural mind, just as waves are of the same watery nature as the sea. When thoughts arise during the state of contemplation, we are aware that they arise from emptiness and that their essence is of the nature of emptiness. We are not disturbed by them but let them go, remaining in the equanimity of contemplation. In this way the natural state of emptiness becomes clearer:</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What is important for us is to reach the condition in which we are no longer distracted or disturbed by thoughts. This is not a blank state in which thoughts are absent. In fact, the cultivation of the calm state without thoughts, if prolonged beyond the natural gap that exists between two thoughts, becomes a state of ignorance, not of presence, if in the forced absence of thoughts there is only emptiness without clarity, relaxation without presence. In the true state of contemplation we are relaxed and neither create nor block thoughts but remain present without distraction in the mind-moments of both presence and absence of thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we are present, we suffer just as all people suffer, but our way of suffering is different and the result is different, because although we have problems and suffering, these cannot distract us from presence in the natural state;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Dzogchen practitioners it is very important to work with presence, to develop it well and then to integrate it with our actions of body, voice, and mind in order to have total presence. But what is “total presence”? It is the continuity of presence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we see with our eyes in the state of contemplation what we are really seeing is our own wisdom. The eyes are the portals of wisdom according to Bon Dzogchen.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>once we have stabilized our contemplation, it is important not only to remain in tranquility but also to “practice with the movements of energy of secondary causes.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it is important to try to remain in the state of presence and overcome the subtle dualistic division between contemplation and everyday life, between thun and je thob, between formal practice sessions and “after practice,” and to integrate presence and contemplation with daily life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Integration means the coordination of presence with the movement of energy and consists of the application of the pure wisdom of contemplation to our senses, to our body, voice, mind, and actions in every moment of our life by remaining present in the primordial state and imbuing all the activities of body, voice, and mind in daily life with awareness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Bonpo Ati system of Dzogchen meditation, where the disciple is told to integrate first with virtuous actions, then neutral actions and finally nonvirtuous actions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Virtuous actions are those that do not distract us from the state of presence and that accumulate merit; nonvirtuous actions are those motivated by the five passions and that accumulate obstacles to spiritual development; neutral actions are those that have no karmic consequences and thus accumulate neither merit nor obstacles.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Initially we try to integrate the state of contemplation with activities of the body, which are easiest, then with activities of speech, and finally with activities of the mind, which are the most difficult.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the point of integrating with negative states is not to justify wrong action. It is, rather, the best way to minimize harm and, ultimately, to overcome negativity. If we all mastered the practice of integration, there would be no harm or injury since we would all be in the non-dual state and when we are in the non-dual state we cannot cause harm.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>five poisons. These are: attachment to people and to things; anger, which can manifest when simply seeing someone gives rise to an unpleasant sensation; pride, which can manifest not only by thinking oneself to be very important but also by thinking one is the worst kind of person; jealousy, which means all kinds of comparisons and competition; and ignorance, which means not understanding the real condition. So in relation to the mind we start by trying to integrate with virtuous actions, then gradually pass to neutral actions, and finally to the five poisons. In this way, the whole mind, all thoughts - good, bad, and neutral - are integrated with the state of presence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it is not the number of thoughts that arise that is important, but how we deal with them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is actually only one way to deal with them, and that is not to be distracted by them. This can be done in three ways: by remaining in presence; by not following after them or creating more thoughts (such as the thought not to follow them); and by not allowing them to influence us (in this case it is not a matter of not following the thoughts but of not allowing the thoughts themselves to lead us away).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it is easier to discover and realize self-presence through sense perception that is fresh and immediate than through thought that elaborates perception by conceptualization.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When there is more presence with greater sensation, there is more feeling of integration.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If your mind does make a judgment, do not grasp it as inherently existent; if you do grasp it, do not develop it into a gross passion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is the application of practice in daily life that is most difficult, working with our energy in every life situation, with every sense perception, with every person we meet, whether we</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is of great importance to have experiential, and not merely conceptual,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The traditional example is of a farmer that looks for a yak and cannot find it: what he finds is “no yak.” When we search for a “self” and do not find one, what we find is “no self”; this means finding our true self.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes symbols can be much more effective than clarification through intellectual descriptions because, although we learn through intellectual descriptions, we grow through symbols;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Do anything without any indecision or hesitation. Without expectations or doubts All actions are completely free. Behavior becomes like a peacock’s, Taking all negative obstacles and appearances as blessings. When unhappy, abide completely in unhappiness; When happy, abide completely in happiness; When ill, abide completely in illness; When hungry, abide completely in hunger; When afraid, abide completely in fear; When you don’t like something, abide completely in the state of not liking. This is the big wind. When vision is an obstacle, be careful; When vision becomes your friend, liberate yourself. Then everything becomes a benefit to your practice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the five pure lights develop and begin to appear. This process is represented by the five-colored tigle that surrounds the white A and which symbolizes the primordial natural condition. The pure lights of the five colors constitute the second step in the production of existence; they are the source of the five elements that are the underlying structure of both the external existence of the world and the internal existence of the individual.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>clear light energy resides in the heart, rises through the channels, and is projected through the eyes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>observing anger and seeing its inherent emptiness is the antidote to anger.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when anger arises, we can see the anger in ourselves, but when we try to examine it closely, we only find the inherent emptiness of anger,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Specific togel practices include the dark retreat in which we spend time practicing in complete darkness (the standard dark retreat lasts forty-nine days, although some Dzogchen practitioners have spent many years in dark retreat), or gazing at the sun, at the moon, or into the sky.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>everything is connected: external vision, the eyes, and the internal energy,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we have to discard as dualistic even the idea of practice and non-practice. We enter into the meditation of inner space and abandon this subtle dualistic concept.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>light that can transform itself into material objects.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>effortless spontaneity of remaining in presence in undistracted meditation. If no effort of concentration is required, this means there is no distraction.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Dharmakaya is emptiness; the Sambhogakaya is light and the internal manifestation of energy; the Nirmanakaya is the external manifestation of the energy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Dzogchen, in contrast, is a nongradual path, and from the very beginning the master teaches the practitioner to seek to understand emptiness directly without thought, through zhine practice. Through the application of mind beyond thought and concepts, we achieve undistracted presence and understanding of the inseparability of emptiness and clarity. The understanding of emptiness arises without the mediation of the thought-producing mind but directly by clarity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>According to Dzogchen, the best way of understanding emptiness is not by applying thought, because the understanding obtained in this way can never go beyond the conceptual level. The logical mind comes to understand the logical concept of emptiness, but the truth of emptiness is beyond thought and concept, beyond the logical mind. True emptiness cannot be understood by logical inference because thought, the conceptual mind, can only understand the concept or meaning generality of emptiness and cannot directly perceive emptiness itself.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we are able to maintain continuity of presence during our waking hours, we will eventually be able to maintain it through the moment of falling asleep and into our dreams.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>According to Dzogchen there is no beginning to samsara as such, but there is a beginning to individual samsara. The beginning of samsara is caused by ignorance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We must not only recognize that we are dreaming, but realize presence in the dream. Many people who don’t follow teachings also recognize when they are dreaming, but in our practice what we must do is to remain present and eventually direct and control the dream ourselves.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As mind’s last moment is the most important,</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2023-01-10-wonders-natural-mind.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Tibetan Yogas Of Dream And Sleep</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2022-12-08-tibetan-yogas-dream-sleep.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348186186i/199519.jpg" /></p>
<h1 id="the-tibetan-yogas-of-dream-and-sleep">The Tibetan Yogas Of Dream And Sleep</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>When things are seen from a higher perspective they tend to level out. From the perspective of non-dual wisdom there is no important and unimportant.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Do not think about the object, just let it be in awareness. This is an important distinction to make. Thinking about the object is not the kind of concentration we are developing. The point is just to keep the mind placed on the object, on the sense perception of the object, to undistractedly remain aware of the presence of the object. When the mind does get distracted—and it often will in the beginning—gently bring it back to the object and leave it there.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>thoughts arise without distracting the mind from the object.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You may find that drowsiness is actually a kind of movement of the mind that you can stop with strong concentration. If this does not work, take a break, stretch, and perhaps do some practice while standing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Regard the practice as something precious, which it is, and as something that will lead to the attainment of the highest realization, which it will. Strengthen the intention and automatically the wakefulness of the mind is strengthened.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>is not enough to simply repeat again and again that you are in a dream. The truth of the statement must be felt and experienced beyond the words. Use the imagination, senses, and awareness in fully integrating the practice with felt experience. When you do the practice properly, each time you think that you are in a dream, presence becomes stronger and experience more vivid.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This is the first preparation, to see all life as a dream. It is to be applied in the moment of perception and before a reaction arises.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whereas the first preparation is applied in the moment of encountering phenomena and before a reaction occurs, the second practice is engaged after a reaction has arisen.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When a reaction arises, remind yourself that you, the object, and your reaction to the object are all dream. Think to yourself, “This anger is a dream. This desire is a dream. This indignation, grief, exuberance, is a dream.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>try to actually feel the dream-like quality of your inner life. When this assertion is actually felt, not just thought, the relationship to the situation changes, and the tight, emotional grip on phenomena relaxes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The third preparation involves reviewing the day before going to sleep, and strengthening the intention to practice during the night. As you prepare for sleep, allow the memories of the day to arise. Whatever comes to mind recognize as a dream.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Then develop the strong determination to recognize the dreams of the night for what they are. Make the strongest intention possible to know directly and vividly, while dreaming, that you are dreaming.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“sending a wish.” We should have that sense here,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Keep building intention, using both successes and failures as occasions to develop ever stronger intent to accomplish the practice. And know that even your intention is a dream.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>during the morning period, generate a strong intention to remain consistent in the practice throughout the day</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>And pray with your full heart for success; prayer is like a magical power that we all have and forget to use.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Mother Tantra tells us that as we prepare for sleep we should maintain awareness of the causes of dream, the object to focus upon, the protectors, and of ourselves. Hold these together in awareness, not as many things, but as a single environment,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>imaginal senses: try to visualize it clearly and, even more importantly, feel it and let it affect the sensations in the body and energy, and the quality of the mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Let the object appear without effort, as if intention, lying below the surface of consciousness, binds the mind to the object, just as the mind stays connected to the need to wake for an early appointment or to a great joy. There is no need for exertion or concentration—the object just is and you are with it. You are no longer creating it, you are allowing it, observing</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The progression is to see it, feel it, and then be it. When you fully merge with the object, the visualization may cease, and this is all right.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Do not think this through—experience it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>anything that you cannot do, do not worry about. This is an important secret of practice! Worrying will not help your practice. But you also should not lose the force of your intention to do better. Just do the best you can.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The categories are: size; quantity; quality; speed; accomplishment; transformation; emanation; journey; seeing; encounter; and experiences.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>syllables are RA, which is yellow and is toward the front of your body. LA, which is green, is to your left. SHA, to the back, is red. And SA is to the right and is blue. If there is a problem with restless self-distraction, focus on the syllables one after the other as you fall asleep.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you find it difficult to calm the mind, it is sometimes helpful to do hard physical work, to tire the body or even exhaust it. Meditating on emptiness can also clear the mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Meaning does not exist until someone starts to look for it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Why expect great messages from a dream? Instead penetrate to what is below meaning, the pure base of experience. This is the higher dream practice—not psychological, but more spiritual—concerned with recognizing and realizing the fundament of experience, the unconditioned. When you progress to this point, you are unaffected by whether there is a message in the dream or not. Then you are complete, your experience is complete, you are free from the conditioning that arises from dualistic interactions with the projections of your own mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>simple and regular habits of reconnecting to ourselves, of becoming more present, must be cultivated. Every breath can be a practice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Appreciation for sensory experience reconnects mind and body.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>using bodily sensual experience to bring us to presence, to connect us to the beauty of the world, to the vivid and nourishing experience of life that lies under our distractions. This is the underpinning of successful dream yoga.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“May I have a clear dream. May I have a lucid dream. May I understand myself through dream.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Feel the A rather than focus on it, merge with it rather than remain separate from it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There are four successive domains of integration related to dream practice: vision, dream, bardo, and clear light.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>truth is that there is never an object separate from a subject; there is only an illusion of separation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Dzogchen teachings always stress the importance of knowing yourself, recognizing your capacities and obstacles, and using that knowledge to practice in the manner that will be most beneficial.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>bring the mind into rigpa if possible. If not, then bring the mind into the body, into the central channel, into the heart.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>strong intention is the foundation of the practice. Developing devotion will aid in making intention one-pointed and powerful enough to pierce the clouds of ignorance that mask the luminosity of the clear light.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Rather than relying on conceptual decisions to move from one tiglé to the next, and rather than trying to make the process happen, allow intention to unfold the process in experience.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sleep yoga is not only a practice for sleep. It is the practice of remaining in non-dual awareness continually, throughout the four states of waking, sleeping, meditation, and death. Thus, the obstacles addressed below are actually the single obstacle of being driven away from the clear light and into dualistic, samsaric experience.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>prayer has power but it is not in the words; it is in the feeling you put in the prayer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The practice begins with light and the perceiver of light, but the intent is to unify the two.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is good to see the light of the tiglé but more important to feel it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Experience still arises, but allow whatever arises to dissolve spontaneously in blue light. Let this happen without effort.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The mind plays tricks. Its main trick is to identify itself as the subject and then take everything else to be separate from that subject. In this practice, everything perceived as outside of yourself is dissolved on the exhalation. The perceiver is dissolved on the inhalation. Both outside and inside become luminous and clear and merge into one another, becoming indistinguishable.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Life needs to take some form; if we do not shape it, it will take a form dictated by karma, which we may not like very much.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we directly observe desire rather than becoming fixated on the object of desire, the desire dissolves. And if we can abide in pure presence, the desire, the desiring subject, and the object of desire will all dissolve into their empty essence, revealing the clear light.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When pleasure is used as a door to practice, the pleasure is not lost; we need not be anti-pleasure. When the subject and object dissolve in clear light, then the union of emptiness and clarity is experienced and there is joy. The approach to hatred or aversion is similar. If we observe anger rather than participating in it or identifying with it or being driven by it, then the dualistic obsession with the object of anger ceases and the anger dissolves into emptiness. If presence is maintained in that emptiness, then the subject, too, dissolves. The presence in that empty space is the clear light.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The more wisdom is present, the less thoughts there will be.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Wake, if possible, in the nature of mind rather than in the conventional mind. Observe without identifying with the observer. This can be a little easier in the first moments of waking because the conceptual mind is not totally awake yet. Develop the intention to wake in pure presence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The distraction of our daily life and the unconsciousness of sleep are two faces of the same ignorance. The only limits to practice are those we create. It is best not to compartmentalize practice into periods of meditating, dreaming, sleeping, and so on.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Dzogchen teachings often use a mirror to symbolize rigpa. A mirror reflects everything without choice, preference, or judgement. It reflects the beautiful and the ugly, the big and the small, the virtuous and the non-virtuous. There are no limits or restrictions on what it can reflect, yet the mirror is unstained and unaffected by whatever is reflected in it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Learn the form, understand the purpose of it, apply it in practice, and realize the result.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So take joy and peace as qualities to maintain, as supports in developing the continuity of awareness. Feel these qualities in the body, see them in the world, and wish them for others.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Continuity is the key to integrating life and practice. With awareness and intention, continuity can be developed.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2022-12-08-tibetan-yogas-dream-sleep.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Stilling the Mind</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2022-11-14-stilling-the-mind.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1388340186i/11491886.jpg" /></p>
<h1 id="stilling-the-mind-shamatha-teachings-from-dudjom-lingpas-vajra-essence">Stilling the Mind: Shamatha Teachings from Dudjom Lingpa’s Vajra Essence</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>The practice of Dzogchen brings one into direct contact with reality, unmediated by the individual personality or society.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Düdjom Lingpa was a lay practitioner, married, and the father of eight renowned sons,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the specific approach of taking appearances and awareness as the path, also known as settling the mind in its natural state. In brief, this consists of observing all arising mental phenomena without grasping on to them. Your thoughts, emotions, images, and so forth are observed closely with mindfulness, but you do not encourage, discourage, or involve yourself in any way with the arising mental phenomena.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The true value of the Dharma is as a vehicle to the enlightened state in order to be of greatest benefit in the world.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the transmission of Dzogchen can be mind to mind, it can be symbolic, or it can be verbal.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>developing our own discerning wisdom, our own discerning intelligence</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The Three Roots are the lama (or spiritual mentor), your yidam (or personal deity—Tara, Padmasambhava, Manjushri, or whomever it may be), and the dakini (the enlightened feminine principle).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What does it mean to grasp at a thought? What is the nature of grasping? The Sanskrit graha means “to hold on to,” “to grasp.” It’s exactly that.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>anything believed to exist by itself is a product of reification. This reification is the root of samsara, the cycle of existence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>by designating it as a cup you are not necessarily reifying it by grasping on to it as inherently real. It is possible to use language without being trapped by it, although generally we are unable to avoid it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>William James: “For the moment, what we attend to is reality.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>in the vastness of space attending to it, and remain there with your eyes open—very important, your eyes open—and simply maintain presence in space.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it is important to keep your eyes open and not grasp, not become attached to the phenomena that appear to your visual perception.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So gaze into the space in front of you and notice that there is no big deal here; let this be utterly ordinary. Don’t think you are doing anything special, because you are not. There’s the space in front of you. Just be present with it, that is, attend to it, notice it. Avoid involving yourself with details, such as labeling: “There’s a cushion. It’s on a red rug. The cushion is soft. The rug is hard.” If you slip into grasping like that, you’ve diminished the spaciousness of your meditation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a general rule of thumb when internal distractions arise in your meditation: Should your mind become excited, cast your gaze downward. If the mind loses energy or clarity—becomes dull, lax—then elevate your gaze. This advice also applies to visualization, as when you visualize a deity. In that case, when you feel dull you raise the imagined image, and when excitement disturbs your tranquility you lower it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So if you are still in the early stages of shamatha you might want to try this out. Choose something you would enjoy looking at for twenty-four minutes. Twenty-four-minute periods, or ghatikas, are recommended when you are just starting out in meditation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When discursive thoughts arise, let them go and return not only your visual gaze but your attention, your mental awareness, to the object. Continue like that for a week.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you can imagine one quite small, that’s great, but the size of a pea would be sufficient—something fairly small and round. It’s glistening with five colors—white, yellow, red, green, and blue—</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This practice of taking the mind as the path is a method for becoming lucid during the waking state with respect to the flow of thoughts. We recognize them for what they are—like becoming lucid in a dream—and in so doing, we break the chain of obsessions, compulsion, and delusion. Here is a direct path to freedom, which leads to greater and greater freedom both while awake and while asleep, and this freedom may lead to the infinitely greater freedom from samsara as a whole.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>by not engaging with them, thoughts will usually, over time, thin out.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you don’t grasp, the mind will self-heal and dissolve into its ground.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you are grasping, though, you are not doing this practice. Certainly to grasp on to such appearances would be enormously tempting.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In any of these cases if you grasp, you are not doing the practice. The practice is not grasping.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Settle your mind without distraction, without grasping.” If you are doing that while focusing single-pointedly on the space of the mind and its contents, that’s pretty much it. If you’re letting yourself be carried away, that implies distraction, so do your best to maintain unwavering mindfulness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when a mental image of delicious food arises, if you get carried away, thinking about enjoying such a treat, you’ve been caught up in distraction and grasping. If you focus on the mental image of the food, and you are holding on to it because you’re attracted to it, that’s grasping. If you are simply mindful of that image, without being drawn to it and without wanting it to go away, you are practicing correctly. When you feel attracted to a thought or image or even an emotion, you might tell yourself, “I’m not distracted; I’m right here, right in the moment. I really like this.” That too is grasping. So just be present, letting your awareness remain as still and as accommodating as space. It is very important to know clearly from moment to moment if you are practicing correctly or incorrectly.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Simply continue practicing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Having said that, in this practice, like in any other shamatha practice, there is a balance of neither falling into laxity nor being caught up in excitation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you’re meditating, you’re doing so with too much desire. When you’re practicing, don’t desire anything at all. Just do the practice—with no hopes and fears.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Between sessions, bring to mind all the aspirations and prayers you like. But when you are practicing, just do the practice.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>make sure you also practice when you’re lying down.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you’re doing this practice right, without grasping, even if a thousand maras rose up to attack you, whatever your maras are, they could not inflict any injury if you’re not grasping. And even if a thousand buddhas appeared to you, they couldn’t do you any good. They don’t need to. You don’t need anything from those thousands of images of buddhas. Just continue practicing.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Doing your best” is not “trying your hardest.” Given the balance of relaxation, stability, and vividness required, trying your hardest is trying way too hard. So in the course of the practice of shamatha, whatever technique you are following, the degree of effort you need to exert to practice correctly tapers off as you approach accomplishment, and then simply vanishes. You will have far greater stability and vividness than you started off with, but the effort to maintain and establish that vivid, steady apprehension vanishes of its own accord. “Such effort”—trying too hard—“makes the dissatisfied mind compulsively strive after mental objects.” You arrive at a point in the practice where, if you keep on exerting effort, keep on applying introspection to try to fix something, you’re actually cluttering up your practice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you shouldn’t expect your thoughts to vanish. What you could hope for would be to maintain your presence with them, without distraction, without grasping.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>On merely hearing about depression, or a blank, nameless dread, or apparitions coming up, or nightmares or insomnias, or crushing boulders, or terrible pain throughout your body, we might smile and say, “Gee, that sounds pretty awful.” When it starts happening to us, however, we may easily grasp at and reify it—not because we want to but because it seems overwhelming. The same goes for the more pleasant kinds of nyam</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“from now until your realization of rigpa, everything is nyam.” From the ordinary, or relative, point of view, we must practice in order to purify our minds of our personal, karmic influences, which often find expression as nyam.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>with every arising challenge, if it’s insomnia, great! Let your awareness become larger than the mental space occupied by insomnia. If it’s paranoia, let your awareness be larger than the paranoia. If it’s bodily pain, make your awareness bigger than that. Each time you do that you will discover that you are not just surmounting an obstacle, but that a transformation is taking place that was necessary for you to go further in your practice.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2022-11-14-stilling-the-mind.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
