<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>condensō [en]</title>
        <link>https://jak3.github.io</link>
        <description><![CDATA[GM's e-notecard system]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Davening (Schachter-Shalomi, Rabbi Zalman)</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2021-02-18-davening.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#davening">Davening</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1355843320l/15893573.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="davening">Davening</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>We need that skepticism for quality assurance, because fooling oneself is easy. This is why I so love the statement in Psalm 34:9, “Taste and see that God is good.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if an insight emerges for you, take a few quiet moments to daven it in. And may you, too, as so many holy ones have before, experience the vision of prayer in your mind’s eye, the living taste of prayer in your heart, and the deep and gentle glow of prayer in your soul.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Deuteronomy 26:17–18, which speak of a reciprocal relationship between us and God. The verb used to capture this relationship is aleph-mem-resh. In the simple form this means “to say,” but here—uniquely in Torah—it is used in a transitive form: he’emarta and he’emirkha. God “says” us, and we “say” God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Just as I heard it said to me in a whisper, so I told it to you in a whisper” (Genesis Rabbah 3:4).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The imaginal world is a real world. Real things happen in the imaginal world that affect this world in turn.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>prayer begins with kavanah. To daven with kavanah means to pray with focus, intention, meaning. It means praying from the heart, rather than prayer centered solely in the mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kavanah is not attained in a day. We start small and build patiently on every small success. But if we aim our actions and our davening toward a godly place, we will get there.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I can’t do this without Your help.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Dear God, please help me to let this thought go.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>), wisdom to yield ko’ach mah (), the power of “What?”—the wisdom of getting to know what a thing is. Wise Mind seeks to understand the mitzvah lifnai ve-lifnim, inside and out. He wants to do the mitzvah in a completely integrated and organic way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“duties of the heart,” in Bachya ibn Pakuda’s famous phrase,3 cannot be fulfilled without conscious and deliberate intention.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Saying the words without intent is clearly unsatisfactory; on the other hand, saying every word and syllable with full and true kavanah is close to impossible.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My entire life and everything I do are nothing but God Godding Godself as Zalman. The best thing I can do, then, is to make my life a good ride for God, to consciously devote my actions to that purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The awareness that we stand in the presence of the Living God is one of the most important realizations we can install in our operative consciousness. God is always present. The question is, how present are we? We want to stand in that Presence without opacity. Our work is to penetrate, in meditation and in action, to the very heart of being nokhach penei ha-Shem (Lamentations 2:19), of being truly present before God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Meister Eckhart was trying to express when he wrote, “The eye with which I see God is the same eye with which God sees me. My eye and God’s eye are one eye, one sight, one knowledge, and one love.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>meditating on the Tetragrammaton, the letters of God’s mysterious name, can open a channel to bring down the holy. As in Vipassana or pranayama, we can use our breathing to help us get there. Your lungs without breath are like the yud, the smallest letter, the vanishing point. Our inhalation forms the hey, letter of breath: hhhhhhh. At the top of the breath we form the vav, straight as an erect backbone. Then we breathe out—hhhhhhh—another hey. So we invite YHVH to come down and dwell within us. As Jews we are concerned about living in this world. Ours is not primarily an Ein Sof focus, a preoccupation with the world beyond the beyond, but a Gaia focus. Our fundamental kavanah is not to leave the world behind but to bring God into this world, to create the “Kingdom of heaven” in the life we live, right here and now.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Yir’ah, awe, is sometimes translated as fear, but neither completely captures the idea. The Hebrew root of yir’ah is yud-resh-aleph . The root of words meaning sight or to see is resh-aleph-hey . Yir’ah arises from the state of being seen for what we really are.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The awareness that we are being seen, that we do everything we do in the presence of that Witness—that is the true path to and meaning of yir’ah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The disciple says, “Master, I couldn’t find a place where no One can see me.” The awareness that we are being seen, that we do everything we do in the presence of that Witness—that is the true path to and meaning of yir’ah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If I ascend to heaven, there You are; if I make my bed in hell, You are there” (Psalm 139:8).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Proverbs 3:6, “Be-khol derakhekha da’eihu, Know God in all your ways.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>important forms of consciousness maintenance, of kavanah watching kavanah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If I knew it, I would be it; if I were it, I would know it.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>le-khaven el ha-matarah, to aim at the bull’s-eye. (Le-khaven is from the same root as kavanah, kaf-vav-nun.) This is a useful metaphor. When I finally embrace a matarah—a bull’s-eye, a target for my existence—and I say, “Yes, I will go with that, I will collaborate with that, I will invest myself in that,” then my embracing becomes a kavanah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>olam ha-ba—not “the world to come,” as the phrase is usually translated, but a world that is, at this very moment, becoming in us and around us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I come with a scroll-book on me,” says the psalmist, “in which there is one thing written”—like a journal, in which you declare its purpose on page one. This is what the scroll says: “My only desire is to do Your will. I want Your teaching in my very kishkes” (Psalm 40:8–9). This is my intent. This is what I want to do. I’m not there yet, but I’m on my way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>At the heart of kavanah lies the question: Why? Hebrew has two different words for why, madu’a and lamah, and each has a slightly different emphasis. Madu’a asks, “Mah yadu’a? What is known to us?” Philosophers might call this the what of etiology. It wants to know about origins and causes. Lamah asks, “Le-mah? What for?” This is the why of teleology. It asks: Where are we going with this? What is the goal? The why at the heart of kavanah is not only the madu’a of origins but the lamah of ultimate purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Every locksmith has a master key with which he can open many doors. Neginah is such a key, for it can unlock all doors.” Why? Because a niggun sung in the proper way is like doing teshuvah, like a moment of true repentance and turning to God. The wellsprings of niggun and teshuvah are the simple yearnings of the heart that we all share.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The word nusach can mean both text and melody.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>nusach can also mean the melody or musical mode of a given time and place, which is what I mean here. Nusach conveys information.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nusach also conveys emotion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The ga’agu’im or longing niggunim that raise up these unspoken questions can create a sacred space that all can share.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes the heart wants to daven, and the mind starts arguing. But, as the great cantor and educator Max Helfman said once, “you can’t argue with a song or a dance!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Maybe “the work is not upon you to finish” (Pirkei Avot 2:21). Someone else may complete your tune someday.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>with the emotions that you hear behind the words.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>emotional landscapes—sometimes within a single paragraph.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A niggun is a path to God, a “song of ascension.” But we must set out along that path! We must travel with that intention in mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>True prayer is like the iceberg: little that is visible on the surface, much that happens below.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the invitation to prayer says “come as you are.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>our souls accept only one outcome when it comes to prayer: transformation. We do not wish just to spin our mental wheels: We want to be changed. We want to be moved. We want to end in a better place than where we started. Our souls yearn for this. If we really mean the words we say, how can we help but be moved?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>prayers as a journey through four different landscapes, four distinct facets of human experience: physical, emotional, intellectual, and spiritual. Each facet has its own character; each communicates in its own language; each speaks to a different part of us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Asiyah is the realm of the practical and the sensible—the stuff we apprehend with our senses. We’re packing for our spiritual journey here, grounding ourselves in our physical bodies and in the here and now.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Yetzirah, on a human level, is the world of feelings, the world of passion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The language here is plural. In Yetzirah, the realm of emotions and love, the boundaries between ourselves and others begin to feel permeable</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I’m attracted to you in Asiyah! I love you in Yetzirah!” She’s saying, “Meet me in Beriyah.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In Beriyah, the language is no longer immanent but transcendent. Beriyah is the place of Wow, the place of wonder. We praise and give thanks for the constant and miraculous regeneration by a Creator who “renews, each day and always, the work of creation.” This is not the big bang understanding, in which a single event set the rest of the universe in motion. It is a mystical vision of the entire world being created anew in every instant. A person who sees the universe with such eyes can welcome each and every moment as a new opportunity for praise. In Beriyah, we are still in the group, but what the group does at this stage is to give you a matrix in which to do your individual work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>An important part of davening is to just sit be-nachat ru’ach, in serenity of spirit, and to allow for that to come in.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The word Atzilut refers to something that is noble, high, beyond. The world of Atzilut transcends our level of understanding. Boundaries are gone, definitions are gone. Individual words and thoughts are gone. We ourselves do not exist. Being as we know it has ceased.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kabbalistic tradition imagines us davening the Amidah in the world of Atzilut.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So never mind the achievements and attainments; just talk like a friend to God about what you are really concerned about. If a thought comes, turn it into a prayer. These heartfelt prayers are the ones that are really important; these are the prayers we save for Atzilut, sending them directly to the highest level. I start by saying the introductory verse: “Adonai sefatai tiftach u-fi yagid tehilatekha, Please God, open my lips and let my mouth declare Your praise.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When a concern comes up for anything, turn it into a bakashah, a request. Then set is aside and go back to stillness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Each dimension of ourselves—physical, emotional, intellectual, spiritual—has its own needs and speaks its own language. I don’t want to leave any part of me out. I want my davening, my spiritual life and practice, to integrate them all. How can this holy conversation be real unless my entire self is engaged?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We cannot think our way to God. We cannot reach God by a safe, step-by-step process.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we limit God to the ultimate abstraction, then whom are we praying to? But if instead we come at this from a Yetzirah heart space, that changes everything. If we attune ourselves to Yetzirah, the language of the davening makes sense, and all the stuff that we’re talking about here make sense. The feeling that we’re “doing the divine thing” makes sense—that’s why I like the term davening best, to describe what we’re doing at prayer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Where in this many-layered universe does compassion reside? Who is the You of God for you?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All we need are feelings that we want to share with the listening presence of the universe. If you are not yet used to praying, start by expressing yourself in your own words.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>how much time they had. I got some flak</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Voice arouses kavanah,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Daven so your heart can feel what your lips are saying!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Every breath will praise Yah” (Psalm 150:6). We can use this as a meditation with the YHVH, the Tetragrammaton. First empty your lungs and contemplate the yud, the smallest Hebrew letter, closest to emptiness. Then you breathe in, making a hhhhh sound; that’s the first hey. You hold the breath for a moment, sending it to all six directions in your body—that’s the vav, the sixth letter of the alphabet. Then you breathe out, hhhhh, to make the other hey. So we can use this prayer to scan our lung capacity and check in with our breath.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Barukh ha-Shem—thank God. At last! Now I am free just to sit and enjoy. I don’t need to run; I don’t need to make, do, fix, or change. For one day, I can just be.” If we pause from running through our day to offer a prayer, we find that we have created a little piece of Shabbos</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Throughout the centuries, the payyetanim—Jewish writers of spiritual poetry (piyyut, piyyutim)—have sought new ways of declaring their love for God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ashkenazi siddurim have “Ahavah rabbah ahavtanu” in the morning prayers and “Ahavat olam beit Yisrael amkha ahavtah” in the evening prayer. Chabad and some of the Sepharad siddurim, however, follow the Ari, who saw an important kavanah in the first letters of ahavat olam ahavtanu: aleph (1) + ayin (70) + aleph (1) add up to 72, a number the kabbalists saw as a permutation of YHVH: yud = 10; yud hey = 15; yud hey vav = 21; yud hey vav hey = 26. And 10 + 15 + 21 + 26 = 72.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we study Torah, may we see clearly what is meant for us to know. When we do Mitzvot, may all our feelings sit harmonious in our heart. Focus all our hearts’ longing on that moment, when we stand in Your Presence, in awe and adoration.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>harder to grasp than it sounds. The Tikkunei Zohar marvels, “You are One, but not in the sense of enumeration”—not “one” as an alternative to two, three, or four, but a Unity of infinite existence and infinite potential.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>asking for what we truly need is the hardest part of prayer. We throw up all sorts of obstacles.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whom am I praying to? I am praying to God, however I understand and experience that word right here and right now. I may not be praying to the God that is All, but simply sharing my tsuris with the face of God with which I am most intimate. Perhaps I am praying to whatever it is that listens in the universe. I don’t need to do any more than that. Who am I to ask for anything? I am a creation and manifestation of godliness. I am a wave in the ocean and a world unto myself. The infinite potential for creativity and love in the universe manifests in me and through me, as it does in every other creature. And will it help? We know some parents pray with all their hearts for a child to be cured of a life-threatening disease, and yet the little one dies. We pray daily for peace, yet we are still at war. Prayer is not a switch with which we can control the universe. But I do believe that we can, with our prayers, reach dimensions of existence that we do not otherwise have access to and that the openings in those higher worlds bring blessings down to us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A prayer truly prayed is the beginnings of its own answer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“O God, open up my lips, and let my mouth speak Your praise.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This first sentence reminds us that prayer begins with silence. Think back to the silence that follows the last, enlarged dalet of the Shema statement’s final ECHAD. This is not a silence of absence but a silence full of the presence of the One, a silence of infinite potential.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we want our prayers to be answered, we have to make sure not to hang up the phone too quickly.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>During the week, you can take a piece of notepaper and a pencil. Reflect for a few moments after your davening and see what comes down. “So what do I have to do today, Ribbono shel olam?” Write down what comes to you, and try to refer to it during the day or before you go to sleep at night.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I begin in Asiyah, putting on my tallis and tefillin first, creating the prayer space that I need. I check in with my body, and I say Asher Yatzar, acknowledging the miracle of the limbs and organs that sustain me. Then I look out of the window and see the world outside, the people and the buildings and the trees, the sun or the rain or the snow, and I say, “Thank You, Ribbono shel olam, all of these are wonderful, and I thank You.” I want to spend a little time in Yetzirah if I possibly can, giving my emotions a voice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I know that without help I’m not going to make it. I close with the Amidah’s final thought: “Oseh shalom, just as in the heavens everything works out as it should, so please, bring peace and tranquility upon us as well.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the first task before us is to empty ourselves of our expectations—to free ourselves of the hold they have over us. I always quote Swami Satchidananda, who would say, “Don’t make any appointments, you won’t have any dis-appointments!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Dear God, whatever jealousies and resentments I might harbor in my heart, please remove this judgment from me.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Reb Pinchas of Koretz, the great Hasidic master, wondered how we can pray for other people to become better. Are we not depriving that person of their choice and free will? The answer, he says, is that we are all part of each other. You are in me, and I am in you. Praying for the “you in me” to be better—the “you” that resides in my heart—somehow helps the “me in you” to do something good for you, and the “you in you” to become better. This is not a moral vision but an organismic vision. On a prayerful level, we are all part of each other and of the greater whole.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If I am not for myself, who will be? But if I am only for myself, what am I?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>aleph-mem-nun, meaning to be firm or trustworthy. Amen means “So be it. May your words come to pass.” It is prayer and affirmation in one.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2021-02-18-davening.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Sleep</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-08-16-sleep.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#sleep">Sleep</a><ul>
<li><a href="#pre-sleep-routine">Pre Sleep Routine</a></li>
<li><a href="#post-sleep-routine">Post Sleep Routine</a></li>
<li><a href="#nap">NAP</a></li>
<li><a href="#quotes">Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="sleep">Sleep</h1>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1471745675l/31566948.jpg" />

</div>
<ul>
<li>It is better to think about quality rather than quantity when dealing with sleep. Quality can be determined not only when your are asleep, your routine while you are awake is important too.</li>
<li>Try to improve one step at a time. Little progresses make big differences.</li>
<li>Our biological clocks are regulated by external stimuli such as:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>sunlight</li>
<li>temperature</li>
<li>meal time</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Circadian rhythms work also without external stimuli</li>
<li>Homeostatic pressure determine our need to sleep. This need start when we wake up and keep increase while we are awake.</li>
<li>During night we attain the more efficient sleeping time near 2-3am (twelve hours later there is a compensation time span, it is really common for most of us to feel drowsy.</li>
<li>Light stimulate seratonin production, a neurotransmitter that increase well being and which melatonin is a derivative.</li>
<li>Blue light, dring the day as beneficial effects such as increase performance and reflexes. It is also reduce melatonin levels. It is a bad habit use blue light during the night as you might expect. Professor Idzikowsky define consequences of that bad habit (blue light from monitors before going to sleep) “junk sleep”. It is self explanatory.</li>
<li><p>In literature exist <code>3</code> chronotypes:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>He who go to sleep and get up early (<strong>AM</strong>)</li>
<li>He who go to sleep and get up late (<strong>PM</strong>)</li>
<li>He who stay between <strong>1</strong> and <strong>2</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>Check out the online quiz and <a href="https://www.bioinfo.mpg.de/mctq/core_work_life/core/introduction.jsp">find what is your chronotype</a> (thanks to University of Monaco).</p></li>
<li>Melatonina is a hormone that is produced by the pineal gland. It regulate your need to go to sleep.</li>
<li>Caffeine is a central nervous system stimulant. It is the world’s most widely consumed psychoactive drug. Unlike many other psychoactive substances, it is legal and unregulated in nearly all parts of the world. It reversibly blocks the action of adenosine on its receptor and consequently prevents the onset of drowsiness induced by adenosine. Caffeine also stimulates certain portions of the autonomic nervous system. Optimal dose for athletes is <code>3-6</code> milligrams per kilograms of body mass. It is a half-life that can be arrive up to six hours. <em>Use caffeine as a power boost, not as a substance that you need in order to do the minimum.</em></li>
<li>Stop waking up late during the weekend, try to keep your morning routine as much as possible.</li>
<li>Is is proven that <code>90</code> minutes is the range needed to pass through each sleep phases. The more important are:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><strong>light sleep</strong>: in which information are consolidated and motor skills performance increase.</li>
<li><p><strong>deep sleep</strong>: brain produce delta wave, the least frequency wave emitted (where we are awake brain produce beta waves that have an higher frequency). More deep sleep the better. We have the most beneficial effects and one of them is the production of growth hormone.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>born new cells, fix tissue and leave a feeling of renewal.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><strong>REM (Rapid Eye Movement)</strong>: dreaming phase, here the mind trick us with dreams while the body is paralyzed. Studies report that <strong>REM sleep increase creativity</strong>.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>It is not possible to get back lost sleep. Try to go to bed early or sleep for too long is time wasted. Our body is able to adapt, if you want to recover something, focus on keep your routine without too much worrying.</li>
<li>Keep a fix time to wake up is the best method we have to increase our sleeping quality.</li>
<li>Focus on <strong>cycles</strong> per night. A cycle is <strong>90 minutes of sleep</strong>.</li>
<li>Try to find out how many cycles are best suite for us. If for example we have seen that we need <code>5</code> cycles per night, we must try to not have three consecutive nights with less cycles. It is really important to find out <strong>How many cycles we need to feel restful and increase our daily routine performance</strong>. We must be ready to feel our body and mind responses while change cycles per night. Try at least for a week before switch.</li>
<li>Do not think that sleep can only be done only monophasically. In a time window of 24 hours there are other opportunities to compensate a poor night sleep.</li>
<li>Our biggest problem is psychological. Common bias that we need <code>8</code> hours of sleep per night is a real beast. It is difficult now think that <code>4.30</code> is enough.</li>
<li>When we get older, our sleep habit shift one bit at a time from a monophasic to a polyphasic sleep.</li>
<li>Sleep on your side is the recommended position. Better if your slave side, because is the side least used so less sensible. In addition, the dominant side can be think as “the reactive” side that can help you defense against attacks while sleeping (in order to sleep well we need to feel secure).</li>
<li>Try to use your bedroom only for sleeping activities.</li>
<li>“<em>Mouth breathing increase the number of sleep apnoea as well as probability to snore.</em>” - Patrick McKeown <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26533127-the-oxygen-advantage">The Oxygen Advantage</a></li>
<li>You can find if you have a good mattress if while you are on your side, the distance between the mattress and your head is less than two fist.</li>
<li>Double bed, as the word say <strong>must</strong> be at least <code>180</code> centimeters (width). Lesser the space we have higher is the probability to disturb our or our partner sleep. Sleep with someone else have benefits <strong>pre</strong> and <strong>post</strong> sleep. In an ideal world, we only [pre/post]sleep together.</li>
<li>Duvet optimal values: <code>13,5</code> tog during winter, <code>4,5</code> tog during summer, <code>9,0</code> tog during autumn and spring. In hot summer obviously we can use only a duvet cover or nothing at all.</li>
<li>Bedroom best practices:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>minimal forniture, cleaned space and color neutral.</li>
<li>can be totally overshadowed (use a night mask can be bothersome, we must be as free as possible).</li>
<li>temperature should be between <code>16-18</code> celsius degree.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Use your bed only for sleeping.</li>
<li>Try to avoid a bottle of water near the bed. Think: why do you need it? If you wake up with a dry throat probably is because you are breathing with your mouth while sleeping. If you wake up in order to go to the bathroom, maybe you have drink too much before sleep. In addition keep a bottle of water near your bed, let your mind think about it during night, with higher probability to think you need a sip.</li>
<li>The best alarm clock is a sunrise simulator. A device useful not only for whom suffering SAD (Seasonal Affective Disorder) but for everyone that try to wake up with a “sunrise”. A sunrise simulator has beneficial brain and body effects in addition to emotional feelings and well being.</li>
<li>Benefits that come with <strong>R90 program</strong> (all tips mentioned above and below) become effective only in addition to good nutrition and body exercises. Tackle these three problems together and each one enhance benefits to the rest. Your life surely will be better.</li>
<li>Tryptophan is an α-amino acid that is used in the biosynthesis of proteins. It is essential in humans, meaning the body cannot synthesize it and thus it must be obtained from the diet (fish, banana, dried fruit). Tryptophan is also a precursor to the neurotransmitter serotonin and the hormone melatonin. Sport athletes use <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1082898/">Montmorency’s cherry</a> as bio-hacking supplement. Glyn Howatson professor of Northumbria University has lead numerous studies that prove his beneficial effects and his efficiency after an intensive physical activity. In addition Glyn proved that these black berry increase melatonin production.</li>
<li>Oregon State University stated that <code>150</code> minutes of physical training per week, enhance sleep quality by <code>65%</code>.</li>
<li>Sleeping pills can give addiction, memory loss and sleepwalking</li>
<li>Think about your sleep in a time window of <code>7</code> days. One night is not enough to draw conclusions</li>
<li><p>Usually it is more problematic to <strong>travel</strong> eastward rather than westward. Good tips are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Go to bed and get up early some days before your departure.</li>
<li>Expose to sunlight early each day and avoid it during the evening</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sunlights</strong> is a lot of more effective rather than caffeine to keep you awake and sleeping pills to make you sleep.</p></li>
<li>An unbalanced sleep, typical to shift workers can lead to different problems such as depression, immune system imbalance, increase risk for cancer, cronic cardiopathy and metabolism disorders (type 2 diabetes). It is proven that being under these changes has severe health consequences. A study done to a sample of <code>70.000</code> nurses with a time window of 22 years has proven that after 5 years of shift work, probabilities to early death increase. Play with our internal clock has consequences. Always.</li>
<li><strong>winter blues</strong>: winter tendency to slow down mood and wants. You can try to avoid winter blues trying to go out and get direct sunlight between 11am to 16pm</li>
<li>National Sleep Foundation recommend for newborns from 14 to 17 sleep hours per day. A quantity that decrease while children grow. 9 to 11 when they start to go to school and 8 to 10 at the age of fourteen.</li>
<li>Help your children to sleep well using pre and post routines and avoid/banish stimulant substances such as sugars.</li>
<li>Teenagers sleep more because is your body that need more sleep.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="pre-sleep-routine">Pre Sleep Routine</h2>
<ul>
<li>A pre-sleep routine enhance your sleeping quality. Sometimes is better to reduce sleeping time in order to do your routine. Remember that it is a way much better <strong>quality</strong> rather than <strong>quantity</strong> in sleep.</li>
<li>Keep your bedroom with fresh air (not cold) is really important.</li>
<li>Have a warm shower rise your body temperature. When you get into bed, a little colder than you, works as naturally thermal excursion. In addition a lot of people feel comfortable getting into bed clean. It is not indispensable having a full shower, a rinse is enough.</li>
<li>Intensive training during afternoon or even evening increase bloody pressure (already at his maximum levels at that time) and for that reason it is not recommended before sleep, above all for the erderly. However going for a walk, yoga, stretching or low intensive exercises are recommended because as we said earlier rising your body temperature before sleeping can help.</li>
<li>Soften all surroundings is another tip. Switch off lights or keep them low, if possible choose lights with a warm color temperature.</li>
<li><p>Recommended activities:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Have a shower</li>
<li>Tidy up</li>
<li>Writing (thoughts, appointments, TODOs for the next day, stoic diary, …)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote></li>
<li>You might eat at least <code>3</code> hours before going to sleep. It is possible to have a snack but only before your pre-sleep routine (that is around <code>90</code> minutes).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="post-sleep-routine">Post Sleep Routine</h2>
<ul>
<li>Post sleep routine enhance our efficiency during the day.</li>
<li>If you wake up and your mouth is dry probably you breath throughout your mouth while asleep. Conversely if your mouth is wet, you are using your nose to breathe.</li>
<li>Cortisol (steroid hormone released in response to stress and low blood-glucose concentration) has his maximal level soon after your wake up time. It is useful start your day with relaxing activities, such as meditation, yoga, daily journal, reading…</li>
<li>When you wake up, get direct sunlight, it enhance our clarity of mind, it balance our biological clock and it prepare our body to switch from melatonin production to serotonin production.</li>
<li>Avoid un-healthy snacks (with too much sugar or difficult to digest).</li>
<li>If it is possible, have breakfast outdoor or at least in a room with a lot of sunlight. If outside the sun is not rise yet, switch on an artificial natural light.</li>
<li>It is a good habit doing some exercises, both high or low intensive. Having a walk, yoga, Taiji..</li>
<li>Easy mental activities such as listen to the radio, iron some clothes, tidy up, read and fix something are welcome.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="nap">NAP</h2>
<ul>
<li><em>Nap with steroids</em>: assume caffeine before having your nap boost results. <strong>NB</strong> (the desired effects arise approximately <code>30</code> minutes after consumption).</li>
<li>It is not necessary to have perfect conditions. You can make a nap while you are in a sitting position.</li>
<li>It is not important if you fall asleep or not. It is important that you take advantage of this resting time, <em>“switching off”</em> your brain.</li>
<li>Find a way to rest. Rest improve your efficiency and concentration, it is scientifically proven.</li>
<li>In addition, switching off your brain reduce stress and keep your productivity high during all day.</li>
<li>If you sleep (<code>1</code> cycle, <code>90</code> minutes, or more) during the day, it is preferred to choose between (<code>13-15</code>, <code>1pm-3pm</code>) and (<code>17-19</code>, <code>5pm-7pm</code>). The first one is better because is like the night period between <code>2am</code> and <code>3am</code> where the circadian stimulus is at his higher rate.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>We do not really know what sleep is. This may be upsetting for outsiders. - <a href="https://profiles.stanford.edu/philippe-mourrain?tab=bio">Philippe Mourrain</a></p>
<p>Breakfast is the most important meal. Period.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://sleepspecialist.co.uk/site-info-old/chris-idzikowski-1">Chris Idzikowski</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26533127-the-oxygen-advantage">The Oxygen Advantage</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1082898/">Montmorency’s cherry</a></li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-08-16-sleep.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>La Grande Via</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-05-29-grandevia.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#la-grande-via">La Grande Via</a><ul>
<li><a href="#diet">Diet</a></li>
<li><a href="#exercise">Exercise</a></li>
<li><a href="#meditation">Meditation</a></li>
<li><a href="#other-hints">Other hints</a></li>
<li><a href="#quotes">Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="la-grande-via">La Grande Via</h1>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://www.lagrandevia.it/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/lagrandevia-berrino-fontana.jpg" style="width:50.0%" />

</div>
<h2 id="diet">Diet</h2>
<ul>
<li>Stop eat before being full.</li>
<li>Fasting is a good habit. Do not eat few and often. Stomach needs to rest.</li>
<li>Eat until 3/4 full.</li>
<li>People can live eating 1/4, with other 3/4 live doctors.</li>
<li>TRF (Time Restricted Feeding) is lowering by 30% Kcal income per meal.</li>
<li><p>Fast 2 or 3 times a week. It is considered fasting:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Eat raw/cooked vegetables (avoid potatoes) with dressing such as olive oil (1 tbs per meal a day), lemon or vinegar No cereals, fruits or proteins.</li>
<li>Keep your stomach at rest at least 14 to 16 hours a day.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Have a bit of hungry is good, our body produces an hormone called Ghrelin. Ghrelin gene products have several actions on acute and chronic inflammation and autoimmunity.</li>
<li>Best breakfast time slot is between 7am to 9am</li>
<li>Buckwheat can be used to make cornmeal mush</li>
<li>Rye has lower glycemic load</li>
<li>Soybean has more proteins than parmigiano</li>
<li>Legumes raise HDL levels, you must eat them at least 2 or 4 times a week</li>
<li>Raw rice and lentils is a balance dish</li>
<li>Use malts and almond/hazelnut/sesame cremes together. Malts have high glycemia index but do not have fructose. Eat them with healthy fat as almon/hazelnut/sesame cremes decrease glucose absorption time. It useful eat them with legumes also.</li>
<li>Daily salt upper bound: 2,4g</li>
<li>Do not give sugar (in every form) to babies until 2 years old. White sugar if possible NEVER.</li>
<li>Mother feeding during pregnancy will be liked to her baby too</li>
<li>Eat fish 1 or 2 times a week</li>
<li>Eat fruits or jasmine Tea as dessert</li>
<li>Cultivate enhance health, Okinawa people are a living example</li>
<li><em>Nan kuru nai sa</em> - Everything will be OK</li>
<li>Pesco-vegetarians have much higher health levels (stats)</li>
<li>Calcium, tea, coffee, cocoa inhibits iron and zinc assimilation. Food with high levels of iron and zinc are grain cream, tahin, soy, azuki beans. Fermentation, sprouting and long leavening are practices that keep nutrients more assimilable</li>
<li>Vitamin D help calcium absorption. Calcium can be found in high quantities into turnip greens, cabbage (40-60% in comparison to only 30% in cow milk), legumes (eg: soy), figs.</li>
<li>In order to assimilate as much as possible nutrients from lettuce, use olive oil as dressing and add wild herbs such as lemon balm, mint, marjoram.</li>
<li>Pan-fry (with olive oil) vegetables in order to better assimilate carotenoids. Carotenoids:
<ul>
<li>alpha e beta carotene: green leaf or yellow vegetables</li>
<li>lycopene: tomatoes, peanuts</li>
<li>beta criptoxantina: pumpkin</li>
<li>lutein: cabbage</li>
<li>capsanthin: chili pepper, red pepper, paprika</li>
<li>crocin: saffron</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Vegetables must be eaten both raw and cooked (pan-fry or in hot water or steamed) Pan-fry cabbage enhance his nutrients, same with onion.</li>
<li>Garlic is better squashed. It releases chemical nutrients as defense mechanism.</li>
<li>Olive oil is useful to prevent thrombosis</li>
<li><p>Almonds and hazelnuts both raw or toasted reduce LDL</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="exercise">Exercise</h2>
<ul>
<li>Aerobic exercises for heart and lungs are walking, jogging, running, cycling, dancing, swimming and skiing</li>
<li>Doing exercises increase mitochondria levels (power and speed)</li>
<li>Benefits from exercises shade after 24-48 hours, keep your training session inside this time slot</li>
<li>Exercises and weight loss increase HDL levels</li>
<li>Exercises produce catepsina B useful in cognitive functions and memory</li>
<li>Heart rate upper bound is: 220 - age</li>
<li>HIT(High Interval Training) = switch between high intensive exercises (60s 90/85% max heart rate) with resting periods (60s). Do it 10 times per row Do not exceed 5/10 minutes of work. Metabolic effects are the same as long training sessions of aerobic exercises (100 minutes)</li>
<li>Exertion, feeding, alcohol, sleep and sex need caution</li>
<li>Exhale while lifting</li>
<li>Do not stay too much seated, change your posture often</li>
<li>Stretching! After some time passed seated and before exercises. It increase muscle grow, oxygenation and movement awareness</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="meditation">Meditation</h2>
<ul>
<li>“OM” vibes inhibit limbic system, it is responsible in controlling emotions</li>
<li>You don’t need to be in a temple or have particular things, nothing will follow you up</li>
<li><p>Yoga stages (by Patañjali):</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>External
<ul>
<li>Yama (passions)</li>
<li>Niyama (emotions)</li>
<li>Asana (know and keep healthy your body)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Breathing
<ul>
<li>Pranayama</li>
<li>Pratyahara</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Meditation (dharana, dhyana, samadhi)</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>Yoga and martial arts are good for kids:</p>
<ul>
<li>enhance ideas and planning</li>
<li>inhibit irrelevant informations and suppress their impulses</li>
<li>change and adapts behaviours</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Ataraxia = imperturbable spirit</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="other-hints">Other hints</h2>
<ul>
<li>Vitamin D is really important. During summer 5-15 minutes of direct sunlight are enough. For a much longer exposure sunscreen is needed. During winter before 10am and after 4pm UVB ray can’t go beyond ozone layer. It is useful sunbathing between 10am and 4pm. A dietary supplement of 800-1000 UI per day can be helpful (in winter).</li>
<li>Amory Lovins, expert in energy efficiency. He also wrote an interesting book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/12742309-reinventing-fire">Reinventing Fire</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Eat breakfast like a king, lunch like a prince, and dinner like a pauper.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Breakfast is for you, lunch to be shared and dinner gifted.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Fasting is the best cure, our doctor inside- Filippo Paracelso</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Meditation must start with the body. The body is the vehicle of himself, you need to control it in order to really meditate - Iyengar</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>A life without research is a life wasted</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Sky roads can be seen without looking out the windows</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Only in finite is expressed infinite and in time the eternal.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Watch your thoughts, they become words; watch your words, they become actions; watch your actions, they become habits; watch your habits, they become character; watch your character, for it becomes your destiny. - Frank Outlaw</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Happiness is also a way of interpreting the world, since while it may be difficult to change the world, it is always possible to change the way we look at it. - Matthieu Ricard</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>If something make you angry, think about what is more important: that thing or your health? In a moment, if you are wise enough, angry vanished. - Cao Tingdong</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>In cultivating body, mind and spirit it is necessary to keep in mind: be friendly, loyal and with broadminded. Not too much happy for praises nor too much angry for blames.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.lagrandevia.it/la-grande-via/">La grande via</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52036.Siddhartha">Siddharta</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/67896.Tao_Te_Ching">Tao te chin - Lao Tzu</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2340397.The_Philosophy_of_Spinoza">The philosophy of spinoza - Ratner J</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Longevity-Life-Preservation-Chinese-MING/dp/753772606X">Gong Ting Xian - Longevità e preservazione della vita</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun_Simiao">Sun Simiao</a></li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-05-29-grandevia.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Thinking, Fast and Slow</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-12-07-thinking-fast-slow.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#thinking-fast-and-slow-kahneman-daniel">Thinking, Fast and Slow (Kahneman, Daniel)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1317793965l/11468377.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="thinking-fast-and-slow-kahneman-daniel">Thinking, Fast and Slow (Kahneman, Daniel)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>“The situation has provided a cue; this cue has given the expert access to information stored in memory, and the information provides the answer. Intuition is nothing more and nothing less than recognition.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Overconfidence is fed by the illusory certainty of hindsight. My views on this topic have been influenced by Nassim Taleb, the author of The Black Swan. I hope for watercooler conversations that intelligently explore the lessons that can be learned from the past while resisting the lure of hindsight and the illusion of certainty.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The gorilla study illustrates two important facts about our minds: we can be blind to the obvious, and we are also blind to our blindness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you know that the lines are equally long. If asked about their length, you will say what you know. But you still see the bottom line as longer. You have chosen to believe the measurement, but you cannot prevent System 1 from doing its thing; you cannot decide to see the lines as equal, although you know they are.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Not all illusions are visual. There are illusions of thought, which we call cognitive illusions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As a way to live your life, however, continuous vigilance is not necessarily good, and it is certainly impractical. Constantly questioning our own thinking would be impossibly tedious, and System 2 is much too slow and inefficient to serve as a substitute for System 1 in making routine decisions. The best we can do is a compromise: learn to recognize situations in which mistakes are likely and try harder to avoid significant mistakes when the stakes are high. The premise of this book is that it is easier to recognize other people’s mistakes than our own.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the pupil was a good measure of the physical arousal that accompanies mental effort, and we could go ahead and use it to understand how the mind works. Much like the electricity meter outside your house or apartment, the pupils offer an index of the current rate at which mental energy is used.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Any task that requires you to keep several ideas in mind at the same time has the same hurried character. Unless you have the good fortune of a capacious working memory, you may be forced to work uncomfortably hard. The most effortful forms of slow thinking are those that require you to think fast.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The psychologist Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi (pronounced six-cent-mihaly) has done more than anyone else to study this state of effortless attending, and the name he proposed for it, flow, has become part of the language. People who experience flow describe it as “a state of effortless concentration so deep that they lose their sense of time, of themselves, of their problems,” and their descriptions of the joy of that state are so compelling that Csikszentmihalyi has called it an “optimal experience.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>People who are cognitively busy are also more likely to make selfish choices, use sexist language, and make superficial judgments in social situations.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The nervous system consumes more glucose than most other parts of the body, and effortful mental activity appears to be especially expensive in the currency of glucose. When you are actively involved in difficult cognitive reasoning or engaged in a task that requires self-control, your blood glucose level drops. The effect is analogous to a runner who draws down glucose stored in her muscles during a sprint. The bold implication of this idea is that the effects of ego depletion could be undone by ingesting glucose,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if you have had to force yourself to do something, you are less willing or less able to exert self-control when the next challenge comes around. The phenomenon has been named ego depletion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when people believe a conclusion is true, they are also very likely to believe arguments that appear to support it, even when these arguments are unsound. If System 1 is involved, the conclusion comes first and the arguments follow.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Intelligence is not only the ability to reason; it is also the ability to find relevant material in memory and to deploy attention when needed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Those who avoid the sin of intellectual sloth could be called “engaged.” They are more alert, more intellectually active, less willing to be satisfied with superficially attractive answers, more skeptical about their intuitions. The psychologist Keith Stanovich would call them more rational.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As cognitive scientists have emphasized in recent years, cognition is embodied; you think with your body, not only with your brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This remarkable priming phenomenon—the influencing of an action by the idea—is known as the ideomotor effect.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>being amused tends to make you smile, and smiling tends to make you feel amused.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“act calm and kind regardless of how you feel” is very good advice: you are likely to be rewarded by actually feeling calm and kind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>reliable way to make people believe in falsehoods is frequent repetition, because familiarity is not easily distinguished from truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All this is very good advice, but we should not get carried away. High-quality paper, bright colors, and rhyming or simple language will not be much help if your message is obviously nonsensical, or if it contradicts facts that your audience knows to be true.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>performance was better with the bad font.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Zajonc argued that the effect of repetition on liking is a profoundly important biological fact, and that it extends to all animals. To survive in a frequently dangerous world, an organism should react cautiously to a novel stimulus, with withdrawal and fear. Survival prospects are poor for an animal that is not suspicious of novelty. However, it is also adaptive for the initial caution to fade if the stimulus is actually safe. The mere exposure effect occurs, Zajonc claimed, because the repeated exposure of a stimulus is followed by nothing bad. Such a stimulus will eventually become a safety signal, and safety is good.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mood evidently affects the operation of System 1: when we are uncomfortable and unhappy, we lose touch with our intuition.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the connection makes biological sense. A good mood is a signal that things are generally going well, the environment is safe, and it is all right to let one’s guard down. A bad mood indicates that things are not going very well, there may be a threat, and vigilance is required. Cognitive ease is both a cause and a consequence of a pleasant feeling.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We have norms for a vast number of categories, and these norms provide the background for the immediate detection of anomalies</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a large event is supposed to have consequences, and consequences need causes to explain them. We have limited information about what happened on a day, and System 1 is adept at finding a coherent causal story that links the fragments of knowledge at its disposal.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we are born prepared to make intentional attributions: infants under one year old identify bullies and victims, and expect a pursuer to follow the most direct path in attempting to catch whatever it is chasing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when System 2 is otherwise engaged, we will believe almost anything. System 1 is gullible and biased to believe, System 2 is in charge of doubting and unbelieving, but System 2 is sometimes busy, and often lazy. Indeed, there is evidence that people are more likely to be influenced by empty persuasive messages, such as commercials, when they are tired and depleted.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The tendency to like (or dislike) everything about a person—including things you have not observed—is known as the halo effect.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Gilbert proposed that understanding a statement must begin with an attempt to believe it: you must first know what the idea would mean if it were true. Only then can you decide whether or not to unbelieve it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>simple rule can help: before an issue is discussed, all members of the committee should be asked to write a very brief summary of their position. This procedure makes good use of the value of the diversity of knowledge and opinion in the group.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Jumping to conclusions on the basis of limited evidence is so important to an understanding of intuitive thinking, and comes up so often in this book, that I will use a cumbersome abbreviation for it: WYSIATI, which stands for what you see is all there is. System 1 is radically insensitive to both the quality and the quantity of the information that gives rise to impressions and intuitions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is the consistency of the information that matters for a good story, not its completeness. Indeed, you will often find that knowing little makes it easier to fit everything you know into a coherent pattern.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Here we encounter a new aptitude of System 1. An underlying scale of intensity allows matching across diverse dimensions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>assessment. You do that automatically whether or not you</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you often have answers to questions that you do not completely understand, relying on evidence that you can neither explain nor defend.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>How to Solve It: “If you can’t solve a problem, then there is an easier problem you can solve: find it.” Pólya’s heuristics are strategic procedures that are deliberately implemented by System 2.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The dominance of conclusions over arguments is most pronounced where emotions are involved.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“people are not adequately sensitive to sample size.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we are prone to exaggerate the consistency and coherence of what we see. The exaggerated faith of researchers in what can be learned from a few observations is closely related to the halo effect, the sense we often get that we know and understand a person about whom we actually know very little.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if you follow your intuition, you will more often than not err by misclassifying a random event as systematic. We are far too willing to reject the belief that much of what we see in life is random.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>anchoring effect. It occurs when people consider a particular value for an unknown quantity before estimating that quantity. What happens is one of the most reliable and robust results of experimental psychology: the estimates stay close to the number that people considered—hence the image of an anchor.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The conclusion is clear: anchors do not have their effects because people believe they are informative.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My advice to students when I taught negotiations was that if you think the other side has made an outrageous proposal, you should not come back with an equally outrageous counteroffer, creating a gap that will be difficult to bridge in further negotiations. Instead you should make a scene, storm out or threaten to do so, and make it clear—to yourself as well as to the other side—that you will not continue the negotiation with that number on the table.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>general, a strategy of deliberately “thinking the opposite” may be a good defense against anchoring effects, because it negates the biased recruitment of thoughts that produces these effects.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You are always aware of the anchor and even pay attention to it, but you do not know how it guides and constrains your thinking, because you cannot imagine how you would have thought if the anchor had been different (or absent). However, you should assume that any number that is on the table has had an anchoring effect on you, and if the stakes are high you should mobilize yourself (your System 2) to combat the effect.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kunreuther also observed that protective actions, whether by individuals or governments, are usually designed to be adequate to the worst disaster actually experienced.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The world in our heads is not a precise replica of reality; our expectations about the frequency of events are distorted by the prevalence and emotional intensity of the messages to which we are exposed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Slovic has challenged the foundation of their expertise: the idea that risk is objective. “Risk” does not exist “out there,” independent of our minds and culture, waiting to be measured. Human beings have invented the concept of “risk” to help them understand and cope with the dangers and uncertainties of life. Although these dangers are real, there is no such thing as “real risk” or “objective risk.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every parent who has stayed up waiting for a teenage daughter who is late from a party will recognize the feeling. You may know that there is really (almost) nothing to worry about, but you cannot help images of disaster from coming to mind. As Slovic has argued, the amount of concern is not adequately sensitive to the probability of harm; you are imagining the numerator—the tragic story you saw on the news—and not thinking about the denominator. Sunstein has coined the phrase “probability neglect” to describe the pattern. The combination of probability neglect with the social mechanisms of availability cascades inevitably leads to gross exaggeration of minor threats, sometimes with important consequences.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>mechanism through which biases flow into policy: the availability cascade.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Anchor your judgment of the probability of an outcome on a plausible base rate. Question the diagnosticity of your evidence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>individuals feel relieved of responsibility when they know that others have heard the same request for help.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Changing one’s mind about human nature is hard work, and changing one’s mind for the worse about oneself is even harder.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Subjects’ unwillingness to deduce the particular from the general was matched only by their willingness to infer the general from the particular.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You are more likely to learn something by finding surprises in your own behavior than by hearing surprising facts about people in general.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>rewards for improved performance work better than punishment of mistakes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>correlation and regression are not two concepts—they are different perspectives on the same concept. The general rule is straightforward but has surprising consequences: whenever the correlation between two scores is imperfect, there will be regression to the mean. To</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In order to conclude that an energy drink—or any other treatment—is effective, you must compare a group of patients who receive this treatment to a “control group” that receives no treatment (or, better, receives a placebo).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>general limitation of the human mind is its imperfect ability to reconstruct past states of knowledge, or beliefs that have changed. Once you adopt a new view of the world (or of any part of it), you immediately lose much of your ability to recall what you used to believe before your mind changed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In other words, people who spend their time, and earn their living, studying a particular topic produce poorer predictions than dart-throwing monkeys who would have distributed their choices evenly over the options. Even in the region they knew best, experts were not significantly better than nonspecialists. Those who know more forecast very slightly better than those who know less. But those with the most knowledge are often less reliable. The reason is that the person who acquires more knowledge develops an enhanced illusion of her skill and becomes unrealistically overconfident.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first lesson is that errors of prediction are inevitable because the world is unpredictable. The second is that high subjective confidence is not to be trusted as an indicator of accuracy (low confidence could be more informative).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Several studies have shown that human decision makers are inferior to a prediction formula even when they are given the score suggested by the formula!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The situation has provided a cue; this cue has given the expert access to information stored in memory, and the information provides the answer. Intuition is nothing more and nothing less than recognition.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>intuition cannot be trusted in the absence of stable regularities in the environment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when a project ends reasonably well: once you understand the main conclusion, it seems it was always obvious.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>how can we evaluate the probable validity of an intuitive judgment? When do judgments reflect true expertise? When do they display an illusion of validity? The answer comes from the two basic conditions for acquiring a skill: an environment that is sufficiently regular to be predictable an opportunity to learn these regularities through prolonged practice</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the likelihood that something will go wrong in a big project is high.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>people who have information about an individual case rarely feel the need to know the statistics of the class to which the case belongs. When we were eventually exposed to the outside view, we collectively ignored it. We can recognize what happened to us; it is similar to the experiment that suggested the futility of teaching psychology. When they made predictions about individual cases about which they had a little information (a brief and bland interview), Nisbett and Borgida’s students completely neglected the global results they had just learned. “Pallid” statistical information is routinely discarded when it is incompatible with one’s personal impressions of a case. In the competition with the inside view, the outside view doesn’t stand a chance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Bent Flyvbjerg, now at Oxford University, offered a forceful summary: The prevalent tendency to underweight or ignore distributional information is perhaps the major source of error in forecasting. Planners should therefore make every effort to frame the forecasting problem so as to facilitate utilizing all the distributional information that is available.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>for failing to allow for difficulties that they could not have anticipated—the unknown unknowns.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>call it theory-induced blindness: once you have accepted a theory and used it as a tool in your thinking, it is extraordinarily difficult to notice its flaws. If you come upon an observation that does not seem to fit the model, you assume that there must be a perfectly good explanation that you are somehow missing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You just like winning and dislike losing—and you almost certainly dislike losing more than you like winning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The slope of the function is steeper in the negative domain; the response to a loss is stronger than the response to a corresponding gain. This was the explanation of the endowment effect that Thaler had been searching for. And the first application of prospect theory to an economic puzzle now appears to have been a significant milestone in the development of behavioral economics.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>paper titled “Bad Is Stronger Than Good,” summarized the evidence as follows: “Bad emotions, bad parents, and bad feedback have more impact than good ones, and bad information is processed more thoroughly than good. The self is more motivated to avoid bad self-definitions than to pursue good ones. Bad impressions and bad stereotypes are quicker to form and more resistant to disconfirmation than good ones.” They cite John Gottman, the well-known expert in marital relations, who observed that the long-term success of a relationship depends far more on avoiding the negative than on seeking the positive. Gottman estimated that a stable relationship requires that good interactions outnumber bad interactions by at least 5 to 1.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Loss aversion refers to the relative strength of two motives: we are driven more strongly to avoid losses than to achieve gains.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Animals, including people, fight harder to prevent losses than to achieve gains. In the world of territorial animals, this principle explains the success of defenders. A biologist observed that “when a territory holder is challenged by a rival, the owner almost always wins the contest—usually within a matter of seconds.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>von Neumann and Morgenstern introduced in 1944. They proved that any weighting of uncertain outcomes that is not strictly proportional to probability leads to inconsistencies and other disasters.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My experience illustrates how terrorism works and why it is so effective: it induces an availability cascade.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The psychology of high-prize lotteries is similar to the psychology of terrorism. The thrilling possibility of winning the big prize is shared by the community and reinforced by conversations at work and at home. Buying a ticket is immediately rewarded by pleasant fantasies, just as avoiding a bus was immediately rewarded by relief from fear. In both cases, the actual probability is inconsequential; only possibility matters. The original formulation of prospect theory included the argument that “highly unlikely events are either ignored or overweighted,” but it did not specify the conditions under which one or the other will occur, nor did it propose a psychological interpretation of it. My current view of decision weights has been strongly influenced by recent research on the role of emotions and vividness in decision making. Overweighting of unlikely outcomes is rooted in System 1 features that are familiar by now. Emotion and vividness influence fluency, availability, and judgments of probability—and thus account for our excessive response to the few rare events that we do not ignore.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>People overestimate the probabilities of unlikely events. People overweight unlikely events in their decisions. Although overestimation and overweighting are distinct phenomena, the same psychological mechanisms are involved in both: focused attention, confirmation bias, and cognitive ease.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The common feature of these poignant stories is that they involve unusual events—and unusual events are easier than normal events to undo in imagination.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>An abnormal event attracts attention, and it also activates the idea of the event that would have been normal under the same circumstances.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Losses are weighted about twice as much as gains in several contexts: choice between gambles, the endowment effect, and reactions to price changes. The loss-aversion coefficient is much higher in some situations. In particular, you may be more loss averse for aspects of your life that are more important than money, such as health. Furthermore, your reluctance to “sell” important endowments increases dramatically when doing so might make you responsible for an awful outcome.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You can also take precautions that will inoculate you against regret. Perhaps the most useful is to be explicit about the anticipation of regret. If you can remember when things go badly that you considered the possibility of regret carefully before deciding, you are likely to experience less of it. You should also know that regret and hindsight bias will come together, so anything you can do to preclude hindsight is likely to be helpful. My personal hindsight-avoiding policy is to be either very thorough or completely casual when making a decision with long-term consequences. Hindsight is worse when you think a little, just enough to tell yourself later, “I almost made a better choice.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the emotion evoked by a word can “leak” into the final choice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But the experience was not actually ruined, only the memory of it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What we learn from the past is to maximize the qualities of our future memories, not necessarily of our future experience. This is the tyranny of the remembering self.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Tastes and decisions are shaped by memories, and the memories can be wrong.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>story is about significant events and memorable moments, not about time passing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Duration neglect is normal in a story, and the ending often defines its character. The same core features appear in the rules of narratives and in the memories of colonoscopies, vacations, and films. This is how the remembering self works: it composes stories and keeps them for future reference.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“You seem to be devoting your entire vacation to the construction of memories. Perhaps you should put away the camera and enjoy the moment, even if it is not very memorable?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Csikszentmihalyi calls flow—a state that some artists experience in their creative moments and that many other people achieve when enthralled by a film, a book, or a crossword puzzle: interruptions are not welcome in any of these situations.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>focusing illusion, which can be described in a single sentence: Nothing in life is as important as you think it is when you are thinking about it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We believe that duration is important, but our memory tells us it is not.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Humans, unlike Econs, need help to make good decisions, and there are informed and unintrusive ways to provide that help.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The way to block errors that originate in System 1 is simple in principle: recognize the signs that you are in a cognitive minefield, slow down, and ask for reinforcement from System 2.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-12-07-thinking-fast-slow.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Power of Full Engagement</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-08-15-fullengagement.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#the-power-of-full-engagement-managing-energy-not-time-is-the-key-to-high-performance-and-personal-renewal-loehr-jimschwartz-tony">The Power of Full Engagement: Managing Energy, Not Time, is the Key to High Performance and Personal Renewal (Loehr, Jim;Schwartz, Tony)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1431760957l/68985._SY475_.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="the-power-of-full-engagement-managing-energy-not-time-is-the-key-to-high-performance-and-personal-renewal-loehr-jimschwartz-tony">The Power of Full Engagement: Managing Energy, Not Time, is the Key to High Performance and Personal Renewal (Loehr, Jim;Schwartz, Tony)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>Human beings are complex energy systems, and full engagement is not simply one-dimensional. The energy that pulses through us is physical, emotional, mental, and spiritual.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We, too, must learn to live our own lives as a series of sprints—fully engaging for periods of time, and then fully disengaging and seeking renewal before jumping back into the fray to face whatever challenges confront us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As Nietzsche put it, “That which does not kill us makes us stronger.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The power of rituals is that they insure that we use as little conscious energy as possible where it is not absolutely necessary, leaving us free to strategically focus the energy available to us in creative, enriching ways.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Too much energy expenditure without sufficient recovery eventually leads to burnout and breakdown. (Overuse it and lose it.) Too much recovery without sufficient stress leads to atrophy and weakness. (Use it or lose it.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Cultures that encourage people to seek intermittent renewal not only inspire greater commitment, but also more productivity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are oscillatory beings in an oscillatory universe. Rhythmicity is our inheritance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Expanding capacity requires a willingness to endure short-term discomfort in the service of long-term reward.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“We can experience pleasure without any investment of psychic energy, whereas enjoyment happens only as a result of unusual investments of attention . . . ,” writes psychologist Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi, author of Flow. “The best moments [in our lives] usually occur when a person’s body or mind is stretched to its limits in a voluntary effort to accomplish something difficult and worthwhile.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the key to expanding capacity is both to push beyond one’s ordinary limits and to regularly seek recovery, which is when growth actually occurs.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The most important rhythms in our lives are the ones we typically take for granted—most notably breathing and eating.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>simplest antidotes to anger and anxiety is to take deep abdominal breaths.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>researchers found that a series of short doses of intense aerobic activity—each one sixty seconds or less—followed by complete aerobic recovery, had a profound positive impact on participants. In a period of just eight weeks, the subjects exhibited significant improvements in cardiovascular fitness, heart-rate variability and mood.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Rigorous training improves a person’s ability to perform on the battlefield. . . . The concept of stress inoculation is very much like the concept of preventing a particular disease through vaccination. Like immunization, which occurs only when the vaccine is given in the proper dosage, stress inoculation occurs only when the stress intensity is at the optimal level—high enough to activate a person’s psychological and biological systems, but low enough so as not to overwhelm them. If the stress level is not high enough, inoculation will not occur; if the stress level is too high, stress sensitization will occur, and the individual will probably perform less effectively when he is stressed again.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Snowden discovered that those nuns whose writing expressed a preponderance of positive emotions (happiness, love, hope, gratitude and contentment) tended to live longer and more productive lives.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Researchers such as Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi have found that prolonged television watching is actually correlated with increased anxiety and low-level depression. Conversely, the richer and deeper the source of emotional recovery, the more we refill our reserves and the more resilient we become. Effective emotional renewal puts us in a position to perform more effectively, especially under pressure.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To be fully engaged emotionally requires celebrating what the Stoic philosophers called anacoluthia—the mutual entailment of the virtues. By this notion, no virtue is a virtue by itself. Rather, all virtues are entailed. Honesty without compassion, for example, becomes cruelty. We are, in effect, the sum of our complexities and contradictions. Practically, we must focus on building emotional capacity wherever it is that we are most out of balance. The ultimate goal is to move more freely and flexibly between our own opposites.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The brain represents just 2 percent of the body’s weight, but requires almost 25 percent of its oxygen.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The greatest geniuses,” da Vinci told his patron, “sometimes accomplish more when they work less.” In his Treatise on Painting, da Vinci wrote, “It is a very good plan every now and then to go away and have a little relaxation. . . . When you come back to the work your judgment will be surer, since to remain constantly at work will cause you to lose the power of judgment.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Five stages are now widely recognized: first insight, saturation, incubation, illumination and verification.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The quantity of energy we have to spend at any given moment is a reflection of our physical capacity. Our motivation to spend what we have is largely a spiritual issue.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Some activities generate considerable spiritual renewal without demanding significant energy expenditure. These include walking in nature, reading an inspirational book, listening to music, or hearing a great speaker. Spiritual practices, by contrast, can be renewing and demanding at the same time. Meditation, for example, requires mobilizing highly focused attention to quiet the mind, but may also prompt a rejuvenating experience of expansive openness, connectedness and even joy. Like yoga, meditation is a practice that can cut across all dimensions, building spiritual capacity while also providing mental and emotional recovery.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>all service to others, which involves considerable effort and even inconvenience, but may also provide a profound source of meaning and deep satisfaction.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The irony is that self-absorption ultimately drains energy and impedes performance. The more preoccupied we are with our own fears and concerns, the less energy we have available to take positive action. Subordinating our self-interest to something beyond ourselves may feel threatening at first, but as Gary discovered, it can also be immensely rewarding—a means by which to experience a deeper sense of meaning and greater self-worth. The commitment to live according to our deepest values not only creates a more stable center in our lives but also helps us to better navigate the challenges we face along the way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nietzsche’s famous words, “He who has a why to live for can bear with almost any how.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we learned that visualizing a performance challenge in advance is a very effective way to allay anxiety and to perform without awkwardness or self-consciousness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Wade Roofs has defined spirituality as “knowing our deepest selves and what is sacred to us.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Arthur Ashe once put it: “From what we get in life, we make a living. From what we give, we make a life.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>emotions such as fear, anger and even hatred can be a powerful source of energy. The problem is the cost. As we saw earlier, negative emotions drain energy and prompt the release of hormones that are toxic to our systems over time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes it’s more important to stay connected with people than to be right.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we feel more passion for and derive more pleasure from doing what we freely choose and most enjoy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>capitolo <em>molto</em> bello. Deepest purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Purpose becomes a more powerful and enduring source of energy when its source moves from negative to positive, external to internal and self to others.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we aren’t investing energy in protecting our turf, we have the potential to see more of the truth and to continue to learn and grow.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We can derive as much value from studying and understanding our failures as we can from celebrating and reinforcing our successes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“What amazes me most,” Roger told us, “is that once my values became clear and I got the hang of building rituals, most of the changes I made weren’t that hard. My life acquired a certain rhythm. I can feel how much my energy has rubbed off on the people in my life. My challenge now is just to feel the pulse and keep the beat.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-08-15-fullengagement.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Eureka Factor</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-06-25-the-eureka-factor.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#the-eureka-factor-creative-insights-and-the-brain-kounios-johnbeeman-mark">The Eureka Factor: Creative Insights and the Brain (Kounios, John;Beeman, Mark)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1423184765l/23210114.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="the-eureka-factor-creative-insights-and-the-brain-kounios-johnbeeman-mark">The Eureka Factor: Creative Insights and the Brain (Kounios, John;Beeman, Mark)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>The ultimate goal of Zen is “satori,” which Japanese scholar D. T. Suzuki explained as “acquiring a new viewpoint for looking into the essence of things.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Flynn effect”—startled the world: Average raw scores have been increasing. The worldwide “new normal” has been getting better and better. We don’t yet know for sure why this is happening, but the numbers don’t lie. People are getting smarter. Aren’t they?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Fire wasn’t just the problem—it was also the solution. He fought fire with fire. The conceptual restructuring that produces an insight can be relatively simple—in Dodge’s case, a straightforward inversion—or it can be a lens for viewing subtler relationships.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Analogical thinking solves a problem by revealing a deep relationship between two things that appear very different from each other on the surface. Insights aren’t the only way to experience an analogy. You can deliberately try to construct one. But when you spontaneously realize that one situation is similar to another, you’ve had an analogical insight.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The answer appeared when he took a break from work to enjoy a baseball game.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The difficulty lies, not in the new ideas, but in escaping from the old ones, which ramify, for those brought up as most of us have been, into every corner of our minds. —John Maynard Keynes, preface to The General Theory of Employment, Interest, and Money (1935)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Everything you do has the potential to limit what you do next.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Everything you do has the potential to limit what you do next. Everything you think has the potential to limit what you think next. And you won’t even know that this is happening.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The fact is that you are the sum total of your experiences, even fleeting ones. Your past informs your assumptions, beliefs, and expectations but also limits your ability to think and act flexibly.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This is how experts get better results while thinking less, not more.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That’s why you shouldn’t even attempt to consider all your options and possibilities. You can’t. If you tried to, then you’d never get anything done. So don’t knock the box. Ironically, although it limits your thinking, it also makes you smart. It helps you to stay one step ahead of reality. But also remember that your box isn’t perfect. It can’t enable you to anticipate everything, because doing so would mean that your brain would have to be as complex as the world around you. For those occasions when your box is insufficient, you have insight as a way to break out of an old box and swap it for a new and improved one.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Einstein’s razor”: “Everything should be made as simple as possible, but no simpler.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The notes I handle no better than many pianists. But the pauses between the notes—ah, that is where the art resides. —Artur Schnabel, pianist</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Just as your ability to use language requires two intact hemispheres, so does effective, practical, creative performance. But the right hemisphere provides the spark that ignites the creative fire.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Aspects of sleep stages can persist for a while. Descartes’s insight may have been the product of a conscious mind still under the partial influence of the last phase of the previous night’s sleep.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One way that sleep can incubate ideas and promote insight is by removing blocks that prevent a weakly activated idea from becoming conscious. Cognitive psychologists call this liberation of thought “fixation forgetting.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Zeigarnik effect”: An interruption improves memory for the unfinished task; but once completed, the odds of forgetting the task suddenly increase.10</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The universe tends toward disorder. Objects fall because falling is the most disorderly and likely outcome to emerge in this complex system.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To get the maximum benefit from a break, it helps if you “change your mind”—the greater the change, the better.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Context is the key. Your memories are associated with the contexts in which you originally acquired them. If you learn something in one place, type of situation, or frame of mind, then you’ll remember that information better if you recall it later in the same context. That’s why you sometimes can’t remember the name of a person you know only from your office when you encounter that person at the shopping mall. (Cognitive psychologists call this the “butcher-on-the-bus phenomenon.”) So when you’re stuck in a rut and take a break to resolve the impasse, you’ll shed the misleading ideas more quickly and thoroughly if you think about things that transport your mind far from your current situation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Of course, actually getting away and taking a walk, especially on an unfamiliar route, would be an even better way to change context (as long as you aren’t thinking about the problem during your walk). But if you can’t get away, try thinking about getting away, to another town, another country, or, even better, another planet. Thinking about a situation far removed from your current one might have additional benefits beyond those afforded by a mental reset. When you do this, you are also exercising your ability to change perspective, which seems to be the same sort of ability that you use when you reinterpret a situation to achieve insight. Later, we’ll tell you about research that suggests that exercising this mental flexibility can, at least temporarily, boost your insightfulness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, “When I am, as it were, completely myself, entirely alone, and of good cheer—say, traveling in a carriage or walking after a good meal … it is on such occasions that my ideas flow best and most abundantly,” and other such anecdotes would seem to suggest that a positive mood enhances creative insight.3</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But the fact is that cognition and emotion are closely intertwined, even blended, in the brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“mood congruency”: If you’re sad, then you’ll tend to think of sad things, even to the point of interpreting ambiguous situations negatively. Likewise, happy people tend to have positive thoughts and interpretations. Just as our unconscious associations are filters through which we view the world and ourselves, so, too, are our moods.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This suggests that being put in a good mood enhanced his creative thinking but not his analytic thinking.8</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One is the “winner-take-all” strategy (aka “the rich get richer”). Squash or ignore the weaker, less obvious tendencies and let the strongest, most obvious one dominate. This enables a person to focus on the most straightforward path to solving a problem without detours or distractions. Just twist the jar top harder! This is the analytic mind-set. The other approach is the “Robin Hood” strategy of taking from the rich and giving to the poor—let a weaker, less-obvious tendency dominate over a stronger, more obvious one. Forget brute force—use a can opener. This is the insight mind-set.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>remote associative thinking and positive mood can’t reinforce each other indefinitely. Otherwise, a person’s positive mood and insightfulness would amplify each other in an infinite chain reaction. We know that this doesn’t happen. Every once in a while, the cycle is broken, and this can have practical benefits.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To help you achieve a creative breakthrough, do things that make you happy. Take a walk in the park. Listen to music. But after you’ve had your aha moment, fun time is over. You’ll need to analyze and refine your new idea, and a state of bliss won’t help you to be at your critical best. In this case, a mild dose of anxiety may do the trick. To regain your critical edge, go see a scary movie, ride a roller coaster, or just watch the news—whatever makes you a little nervous. A positive mood may be the best kindling for a creative spark. But once that kindling starts burning, it takes careful work to turn that spark into a useful bonfire.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Try this: Open your mouth a little and then hold a pen in place horizontally with your lips for a few seconds without clenching your teeth. How do you feel? That exercise forces you to tighten the same muscles that you use to smile, causing a tiny, easy-to-miss wave of positive emotion. The researchers used that technique to induce a subtle good mood in their participants (who were tricked by a cover story).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A positive mood energizes a person’s unconscious associations so that when she views a coherent problem, the problem’s parts prime the solution and one another more strongly, making them easier to perceive. This triggers a little burst of pleasure that she interprets as an intuition that a solution is present. It also encourages her to continue working on the problem until the solution proclaims itself in the form of an insight.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>intuitions can be caused either by bursts of positive emotion from fluency or by bursts of negative emotion from disfluency. Either way, emotional surges, whether positive or negative, seem to have their strongest influence on intuition when they occur against the backdrop of an ongoing positive mood because that’s when a person’s associations are most energized.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So mood influences intuition, but not equally for everyone.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you have an intuition, don’t make an impulsive decision to either follow or reject it. Ask yourself why you are having that hunch, at that time, and at that place. The answers to these questions will help you to decide whether to trust a particular intuition. Remember, your brain knows more than you do, but it doesn’t know everything.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“bottom-up” processing is a grassroots movement. It occurs when something in the environment grabs control of the brain, as when you reflexively attend to a loud, unexpected sound, such as a door slamming. Bottom-up processing is dominated by what’s happening in the world around you; top-down control is an expression of your goals, plans, and values.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is reason to think that creativity and mental illness are related and that they are both expressions of something that is relatively stable—one’s genes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you purposely ignore something, even briefly, it’s difficult to immediately shift mental gears and pay full attention to it, a phenomenon called “negative priming.” This can sometimes be a minor inconvenience, but it occurs for a reason. When you ignore something, it’s because you deemed it to be unimportant. By inhibiting something that you’ve already labeled as irrelevant, you don’t have to waste time or energy reconsidering it. More generally, inhibition protects you from unimportant, distracting stimuli. Without it, your thoughts would wander all over the place, even retracing previous mental steps.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>However, all things being equal, you are at your inhibitory best during your peak time. This means that you are most analytical at your peak time and most insightful at your off-peak time. For creativity, your finest hour is literally the low point of your day.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>People can voluntarily broaden or narrow their attention. This isn’t news. Wegbreit’s innovation was to show that these adjustments can influence one’s cognitive style. After the participants’ attention was either broadened or narrowed, they tackled a set of remote associates problems. Narrowing increased the number of analytic solutions; broadening increased insights.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Once your attention has been broadened or narrowed, it stays that way for a while. It doesn’t immediately snap back to its previous focus. Your attention and cognitive style are flexible, but only within limits.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Experience and the environment are important, to a point.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Innovation has nothing to do with how many R&amp;D dollars you have…. It’s not about money. It’s about the people you have, how you’re led, and how much you get it. —Steve Jobs, co-founder of Apple, Inc., quoted in Fortune magazine, November 9, 1998</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when confronted with a deadline an Insightful tends to make “errors of omission” by drawing a blank, while an Analyst’s errors are more likely to be incorrect solutions (“errors of commission”).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Since creativity flows from a promotion orientation, not prevention, creative insight will be enhanced after a prize is won, not in anticipation of one. So make your way through the maze and eat your cheese in safety. Then your mind will expand.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Thinking, as well as feeling, can energize the mental machinery that produces creative insights.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Considering long-term consequences enhances creativity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>imagining a new world by adding something enhances creative thought; taking something away improves analytic problem solving.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To entertain an additive counterfactual, you have to expand your awareness beyond your current situation to include extra things in the mix. It’s the here and now plus something. This should broaden conceptual attention and enhance insight. But when you consider a subtractive counterfactual, you have to think about the here and now minus something. This isn’t as simple as pushing the banished thing out of your mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Like love, adapting to another culture demands the cognitive flexibility to consider situations from another perspective. It involves learning to think about alternate, even opposite, interpretations of events and circumstances. (If you haven’t ever lived abroad and don’t believe this, just watch a foreign news channel or read some foreign newspapers to prove this to yourself.) It</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We’ve seen that thinking about the distant future, faraway places, different cultures, and imaginary worlds can prime you for insightfulness. This is not a laundry list of unrelated techniques for enhancing creativity. These factors are all manifestations of a single psychological principle.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>to empower creative thought, you should imagine unusual people, alternate realities, and the distant future. Think about a loved one. Take in the view—and broaden it. Visit or envision faraway places and cultures. Ponder “what spring is like on Jupiter and Mars.”6</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The key point: The right kind of training and experience may help you learn how to solve specific kinds of problems, but it won’t help you solve other types of problems, and it won’t teach you how to have insights. Real-life problems aren’t circumscribed. For an Insightful, there is no boundary between the problem and the rest of the world or the rest of one’s experience.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes, insight is the specific tool that you need. Unfortunately, it can’t be pulled out of your mental toolbox at will.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You are more likely to have creative insights and valid intuitions when your brain is in a general state characterized by remote associations, broad flexible attention, abstract thought, positive mood, a sense of psychological distance, and a promotion orientation.7</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Quick reference that help you retrieve the main concepts of the book.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>MAKING IT HAPPEN</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To put a twist on Pasteur’s famous saying, chance favors the happy mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The truly essence of the book: how to achive more insights from change your habits to choose the good environ and what should do for start it NOW.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The music is like a mask; I don’t hear it.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You can tap these same principles to design your own personal technique to maximize your own creative potential. Just be sure to test its effectiveness on yourself so that you can optimize it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You could make your dream enviroment but test it if it really works best. TEST OFTEN</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In these common situations is better train your insight mode instead focus only in be more productive.. perfect time to improve crativity without too much effort!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What time can you repurpose for creativity? Any time in which you are engaged in no task, such as when you are waiting in line, or are doing a task that demands minimal attention, like housework or gardening, can be commandeered for creative work in this way. The classic example is the isolation of the shower. Meal times are another possibility. (After all, you have to eat.) Try taking your breakfast or lunch alone in a quiet, isolated environment. Start by priming yourself for a positive mood, psychological distance, and a promotion orientation, for example, by thinking of what long-range goals would make you happy. Then let the ideas flow while you unhurriedly nibble on your meal. Thinking about a problem while doing an easy task may not be particularly convenient. However, incubating a problem while doing a simple, unrelated task can help more than incubation during either a demanding task or no task.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>thoughts about our always connected world</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>constant attention to the environment. There is continuous pressure to produce, especially during economically uncertain times. Meanwhile, many people strive to be attentive parents, spouses, partners, relatives, or friends. Leisure time is hard to come by, and it’s difficult to resist expending what there is of it on the alluring social media platforms, games, videos, gadgets, podcasts, and television channels that are constantly clamoring for our attention. Our thoughts can be interrupted by a cellphone or text message anywhere and anytime. And when the cellphone isn’t ringing and there aren’t any new text or email messages, we think about when the next call or message will arrive. The twenty-first century is all about staying connected, staying on top of things, not missing anything. This is exciting and often productive, but we need to be aware of all of its effects on us. The truth is, we live in an environment on steroids, far removed from the more relaxed pace of life just one generation ago. We are slaves to the present moment, with little opportunity for quiet introspection and mental travel. The inner world</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>default brain state, the brain space ON when you rest</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All 24/7. All enemies of the (default brain) state.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Modern life can stimulate, as well as sap, one’s insightfulness. We’ve seen that alternating between the inner and outer worlds is the best way to enhance your creativity. The impediment to achieving this balance is that the outer world keeps its thumb on the scale. The only way to compensate is by giving extra weight to the inner world and by periodically banishing its enemies.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Create the state. It’s the empire of the future.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-06-25-the-eureka-factor.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A Mind For Numbers (Oakley, Barbara)</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-04-29-mind-for-numbers.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#a-mind-for-numbers-how-to-excel-at-math-and-science-even-if-you-flunked-algebra">A Mind For Numbers: How to Excel at Math and Science (Even If You Flunked Algebra)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1575009552l/18693655._SY475_.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="a-mind-for-numbers-how-to-excel-at-math-and-science-even-if-you-flunked-algebra">A Mind For Numbers: How to Excel at Math and Science (Even If You Flunked Algebra)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>This relaxation can allow different areas of the brain to hook up and return valuable insights. Unlike the focused mode, the diffuse mode seems less affiliated with any one area of the brain—you can think of it as being “diffused” throughout the brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“What surprises me is that we all know that mathematical equations are encrypted messages, for which you need to know the key if you want to crack the code and know what is represented. Nevertheless, we wonder why higher math is difficult to teach, and often blame the educational system or bad teachers. I think that it is similarly a bit misplaced to blame evolution</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Einstellung effect (pronounced EYE-nshtellung). In this phenomenon, an idea you already have in mind, or your simple initial thought, prevents a better idea or solution from being found.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You have to unlearn your erroneous older ideas even while you’re learning new ones.10</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>For example, a little research, self-awareness, and even self-experimentation can prevent you from being parted with your money—or even your good health—on products that come with bogus “scientific” claims.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The harder you push your brain to come up with something creative, the less creative your ideas will be.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But be wary of the idea that some people are “left-brain” or “right-brain” dominant—research indicates that is simply not true.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Befuddlement is a healthy part of the learning process. When students approach a problem and don’t know how to do it, they’ll often decide they’re no good at the subject. Brighter students, in particular, can have difficulty in this way—their breezing through high school leaves them no reason to think that being confused is normal and necessary. But the learning process is all about working your way out of confusion. Articulating your question is 80 percent of the battle. By the time you’ve figured out what’s confusing, you’re likely to have answered the question yourself!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>there are more than three hundred different known proofs of the Pythagorean theorem. As we will soon learn, technical problems and their solutions may be considered a form of poetry.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Understanding how your mind works helps you better understand the creative nature of some of your thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We learn a great deal from our failures in math and science.9 Know that you are making progress with each mistake you catch when trying to solve a problem—finding errors should give you a sense of satisfaction. Edison himself is said to have noted “I have not failed. I’ve just found 10,000 ways that won’t work.”10</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Consistency over time is key!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>blinking is a vital activity that provides another means of reevaluating a situation. Closing our eyes seems to provide a micropause that momentarily deactivates our attention and allows us, for the briefest of moments, to refresh and renew our consciousness and perspective.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“sleeping on it” before making major decisions is generally a good idea,18 and why taking vacations is important.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Learning is often paradoxical. The very thing we need in order to learn impedes our ability to learn. We need to focus intently to be able to solve problems—yet that focus can also block us from accessing the fresh approach we may need. Success is important, but critically, so is failure. Persistence is key—but misplaced persistence causes needless frustration.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It takes time to move information from working memory to long-term memory. To help with this process, use a technique called spaced repetition. As you may have guessed, this technique involves repeating what you are trying to retain, like a new vocabulary word or a new problem-solving technique, but spacing this repetition out over a number of days.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you go even further and set it in mind that you want to dream about the material, it seems to improve your chances of dreaming about it still further.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Going without sleep the night before an examination can mean that even if you are perfectly prepared, your mind is simply unable to function properly, so you do poorly on the test.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Chunking the information you deal with helps your brain run more efficiently. Once you chunk an idea or concept, you don’t need to remember all the little underlying details; you’ve got the main idea—the chunk—and that’s enough.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a bottom-up chunking process where practice and repetition can help you both build and strengthen each chunk, so you can easily gain access to it when needed. And there is a top-down “big picture” process that allows you to see where what you are learning fits in.9 Both processes are vital in gaining mastery over the material. Context is where bottom-up and top-down learning meet.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Intention to learn is helpful only if it leads to the use of good learning strategies.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When marking up the text, train yourself to look for main ideas before making any marks, and keep your text markings to a minimum—one sentence or less per paragraph.13 Words or notes in a margin that synthesize key concepts are a good idea.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Underline Marking Sottolineare if so,how!?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You don’t want to wait too long for the recall practice, so that you have to start the reinforcement of the concept from scratch every time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Merely glancing at the solution to a problem and thinking you truly know it yourself is one of the most common illusions of competence in learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A student is unlikely to make creative discoveries in any subject without a comprehensive set of facts and concepts at his or her command. There is no necessary conflict in learning concepts and facts and in thinking creatively; the two are symbiotic.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Law of Serendipity comes to play: Lady Luck favors the one who tries.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What to Do If You Can’t Grasp It If you don’t understand a method presented in a course you are taking, stop and work backward. Go to the Internet and discover who first figured out the method or some of the earliest people to use it. Try to understand how the creative inventor arrived at the idea and why the idea is used—you can often find a simple explanation that gives a basic sense of why a method is being taught and why you would want to use it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In the same amount of time, by simply practicing and recalling the material, students learned far more and at a much deeper level than they did using any other approach,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the retrieval process itself enhances deep learning and helps us begin forming chunks</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when learning any new skill or discipline, you need plenty of varied practice with different contexts. This helps build the neural patterns you need to make the new skill a comfortable part of your way of thinking.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>recalling material when you are outside your usual place of study helps you strengthen your grasp of the material by viewing it from a different perspective.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Interleaving means practice by doing a mixture of different kinds of problems requiring different strategies.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You want your brain to become used to the idea that just knowing how to use a particular problem-solving technique isn’t enough—you also need to know when to use it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There’s evidence that writing by hand helps get the ideas into mind more easily than if you type the answer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The dread of doing a task uses up more time and energy than doing the task itself.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the better you get at something, the more you’ll find you enjoy it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Procrastination is like addiction. It offers temporary excitement and relief from boring reality. It’s easy to delude yourself that the most profitable use of any given moment is surfing the web for information instead of reading the textbook or doing the assigned problems. You start to tell yourself stories.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I often find that when I cannot bring myself to start something, if I go for a quick run or do something active first, when I come back to it, it is much easier to start.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>remember that the better you get at something, the more enjoyable it can become.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You can change your reality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you find yourself avoiding certain tasks because they make you uncomfortable, there is a great way to reframe things: Learn to focus on process, not product.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Multitasking is like constantly pulling up a plant. This kind of constant shifting of your attention means that new ideas and concepts have no chance to take root and flourish. When you multitask while doing schoolwork, you get tired more quickly. Each tiny shift back and forth of attention siphons off energy. Although each attention switch itself seems tiny, the cumulative result is that you accomplish far less for your effort. You also don’t remember as well, you make more mistakes, and you are less able to transfer what little you do learn into other contexts.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you feel muzzy or featherbrained as you’re trying to look away and recall a key idea, or you find yourself rereading the same paragraphs over and over again, try doing a few situps, pushups, or jumping jacks. A little physical exertion can have a surprisingly positive effect on your ability to understand and recall. Try doing something active now, before recalling the ideas of this chapter.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Generating (that is, recalling) the material helps you learn it much more effectively than simply rereading it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>THE LAW OF SERENDIPITY Remember, Lady Luck favors the one who tries. So don’t feel overwhelmed with everything you need to learn about a new subject. Instead, focus on nailing down a few key ideas. You’ll be surprised at how much that simple framework can help.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Highlighting should be avoided because, at least in my experience, it provides only an illusion of competence. Retrieval practice is far more powerful. Try to get the main ideas of each page you are reading cemented in your mind before you turn the page.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s normal to sit down with a few negative feelings about beginning your work. It’s how you handle those feelings that matters.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Writing the list before you go to sleep enlists your zombies to help you accomplish the items on the list the next day.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Eat your frogs first thing in the morning.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>like pulling weeds or sweeping the kitchen. These aren’t generally my favorite kinds of tasks, but somehow, because I’m using them as diffuse-mode breaks, I often look forward to them. Mixing other tasks up with your learning seems to make everything more enjoyable and keeps you from prolonged and unhealthy bouts of sitting.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Planning your quitting time is as important as planning your working time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s important to transform distant deadlines into daily ones. Attack them bit by bit. Big tasks need to be translated into smaller ones that show up on your daily task list. The only way to walk a journey of a thousand miles is to take one step at a time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“When I was younger, I thought that if I didn’t get something immediately, it meant I would never be able to get it, or I wasn’t smart. That isn’t true at all, of course. Now I understand that it’s really important to get started on something early, leaving time for it to digest. This leads to stress-free understanding that makes learning a lot more enjoyable.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We develop a passion for what we are good at. The mistake is thinking that if we aren’t good at something, we do not have and can never develop a passion for it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>(I’m not kidding about the “close your eyes” part—remember, that can help disengage you from your previous thought patterns.9</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s worth reemphasizing that world-class experts in a variety of disciplines reveal that their path to expertise wasn’t easy. They slogged through some tedious, difficult times to get to their current level of expertise where they can glide by and make it all look easy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But memorization of key facts is essential since it is these facts that form the seeds for the creative process of chunking! The important lesson is that we must continue jiggling and playing mentally with things we have memorized in order to form chunks.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>See Joshua Foer’s masterful TED talk for a demonstration of the memory palace technique for remembering speeches.6</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>They help remind you that meaning is important for remembering, even if the initial meaning is wacky. In short, memorization techniques remind you to make what you learn in your life meaningful, memorable, and fun.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Theories describe and deal with the world on its own terms and must stand on their own two feet. Models stand on someone else’s feet. They are metaphors that compare the object of their attention to something else that it resembles. Resemblance is always partial, and so models necessarily simplify things and reduce the dimensions of the world. . . . In a nutshell, theories tell you what something is; models tell you merely what something is like”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Metaphors are never perfect. But then, all scientific models are just metaphors, which means they also break down at some point.2 But never mind that—metaphors (and models!) are vitally important in giving a physical understanding of the central idea behind the mathematical or scientific process or concept that you are trying to understand. Interestingly, metaphors and analogies are useful for getting people out of Einstellung—being blocked by thinking about a problem in the wrong way. For</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The more you memorize using these innovative techniques, the more creative you become.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Just before you to go sleep, review something mentally that you are trying to learn. To boost this process, review it yet again when you first wake up.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Remember—people learn by trying to make sense out of information they perceive. They rarely learn anything complex simply by having someone else tell it to them. (As math teachers say, “Math is not a spectator sport.”)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As Albert Einstein noted, “There are only two ways to live your life. One is as though nothing is a miracle. The other is as if everything is.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we can make significant changes in our brain by changing how we think.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A synthesis—an abstraction, chunk, or gist idea—is a neural pattern. Good chunks form neural patterns that resonate, not only within the subject we’re working in, but with other subjects and areas of our lives. The abstraction helps you transfer ideas from one area to another.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>sometimes, things that look rough and messy—like clouds and shorelines—have a degree of order to them. Visual complexity can be created from simple rules,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>physicist Jeffrey Prentis compares how a brand-new student of physics and a mature physicist look at equations.6 The equation is seen by the novice as just one more thing to memorize in a vast collection of unrelated equations. More advanced students and physicists, however, see with their mind’s eye the meaning beneath the equation, including how it fits into the big picture, and even a sense of how the parts of the equation feel.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Symbols and equations, in other words, have a hidden text that lies beneath them—a meaning that becomes clear once you are more familiar with the ideas.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Einstein’s theories of relativity arose not from his mathematical skills (he often needed to collaborate with mathematicians to make progress) but from his ability to pretend. He imagined himself as a photon moving at the speed of light, then imagined how a second photon might perceive him. What would that second photon see and feel?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It may seem silly to stage a play in your mind’s eye and imagine the elements and mechanisms you are studying as living creatures, with their own feelings and thoughts. But it is a method that works—it brings them to life and helps you see and understand phenomena that you couldn’t intuit when looking at dry numbers and formulas.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Multitasking during the learning process means you don’t learn as deeply—this can inhibit your ability to transfer what you are learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Persistence is often more important than intelligence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>no matter how good your teacher and textbook are, it’s only when you sneak off and look at other books or videos that you begin to see that what you learn through a single teacher or book is a partial version of the full, three-dimensional reality of the subject, which has links to still other fascinating topics that are of your choosing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>students learn best when they themselves are actively engaged in the subject instead of simply listening to someone else speak.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Failures are better teachers than successes because they cause you to rethink your approach.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Take pride in who you are, especially in the qualities that make you “different,” and use them as a secret talisman for success. Use your natural contrariness to defy the always-present prejudices from others about what you can do.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“the left hemisphere maintains our current beliefs while the right hemisphere evaluates and updates those beliefs when appropriate. Belief evaluation is thus dependent on interhemispheric interaction.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you whiz through a homework or test problem and don’t go back to check your work, you are acting a little like a person who is refusing to use parts of your brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Good learners vet their work to ensure that it makes sense. They ask themselves what the equations mean and where they come from.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The first principle is that you must not fool yourself—and you are the easiest person to fool.”8 —Physicist Richard Feynman, advising how to avoid pseudo-science that masquerades as science</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As Alan Baddeley and colleagues (2009, pp. 148–149) note: “We are not lacking in ways of defending ourselves against challenges to our self-esteem. We readily accept praise but tend to be skeptical of criticism, often attributing criticism to prejudice on the part of the critic. We are inclined to take credit for success when it occurs but deny responsibility for failure. If this stratagem fails, we are rather good at selectively forgetting failure and remembering success and praise.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Friends and teammates can serve as a sort of ever-questioning, larger-scale diffuse mode, outside your own brain, that can catch what you missed, or what you just can’t see. And of course, as mentioned earlier, explaining to friends helps build your own understanding.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Feynman, you want to remember that criticism, whether you are giving or receiving it, isn’t really about you. It’s about what you are trying to understand. In a related vein, people often don’t realize that competition can be a good thing—competition is an intense form of collaboration that can help bring out people’s best.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Keep small talk to a minimum, get your group on track, and finish your work.14 If you find that your group meetings start five to fifteen minutes late, members haven’t read the material, and the conversation consistently veers off topic, find yourself another group.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>there are ways to work with others that require only minimal interaction if you don’t like working in groups.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>equations are NOT merely expressions you plug numbers into to get other numbers. Equations tell a story about how the physical world works. For me, the key to understanding an equation in physics is to see the underlying story. A qualitative understanding of an equation is more important than getting quantitatively correct numbers out of it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This approach works for some people, mostly because anything works for some people.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When the test is handed out to you, first take a quick look to get a sense of what it involves. (You should do this in any case.) Keep your eye out for what appears to be the hardest problem. Then when you start working problems, start first with what appears to be the hardest one. But steel yourself to pull away within the first minute or two if you get stuck or get a sense that you might not be on the right track.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“With my students, I talk about good worry and bad worry. Good worry helps provide motivation and focus while bad worry simply wastes energy.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you shift your thinking from “this test has made me afraid” to “this test has got me excited to do my best!” it can make a significant improvement in your performance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Don’t feel guilty if you can’t seem to get yourself to work too hard the day before a big examination. If you’ve prepared properly, this is a natural reaction: You are subconsciously pulling back to conserve mental energy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>While taking a test, you should also remember how your mind can trick you into thinking what you’ve done is correct, even if it isn’t. This means that, whenever possible, you should blink, shift your attention, and then double-check your answers using a big-picture perspective, asking yourself, “Does this really make sense?” There is often more than one way to solve a problem, and checking your answers from a different perspective provides a golden opportunity for verifying what you’ve done.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When you are checking your work, if you start more toward the back and work toward the front, it sometimes seems to give your brain a fresher perspective that can allow you to more easily catch errors.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>your desire to figure things out right now is what prevents you from being able to figure things out.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Reshaping your brain is under your control. The key is patient persistence—working knowledgeably with your brain’s strengths and weaknesses.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A central theme of this book is the paradoxical nature of learning. Focused attention is indispensable for problem solving—yet it can also block our ability to solve problems. Persistence is key—but it can also leave us unnecessarily pounding our heads. Memorization is a critical aspect of acquiring expertise—but it can also keep us focused on the trees instead of the forest. Metaphor allows us to acquire new concepts—but it can also keep us wedded to faulty conceptions. Study in groups or alone, start hard or start easy, learn concretely or in abstract, success or failure . . . In the end, integrating the many paradoxes of learning adds value and meaning to everything we do. Part of the magic long used by the world’s best thinkers has been to simplify—to put things into terms that even a kid brother or sister can understand. This, indeed, was Richard Feynman’s approach; he challenged some of the most esoteric theoretical mathematicians he knew to put their complicated theories in simple terms.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This work will pay off both for you and those you love!</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-04-29-mind-for-numbers.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Make It Stick (Brown, Peter C.)</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2014-10-30-make-it-stick.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#make-it-stick">Make It Stick</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1436742344l/18770267._SY475_.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="make-it-stick">Make It Stick</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>While the brain is not a muscle that gets stronger with exercise, the neural pathways that make up a body of learning do get stronger, when the memory is retrieved and the learning is practiced. Periodic practice arrests forgetting, strengthens retrieval routes, and is essential for hanging onto the knowledge you want to gain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Trying to solve a problem before being taught the solution leads to better learning, even when errors are made in the attempt.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>underlying principles or “rules” that differentiate types of problems, you’re more successful at picking the right solutions in unfamiliar situations.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Testing helps calibrate our judgments of what we’ve learned.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>limit of what you can keep in mind. However, if you practice elaboration, there’s no known limit to how much you can learn. Elaboration is the process of giving new material meaning by expressing it in your own words and connecting it with what you already know. The more you can explain about the way your new learning relates to your prior knowledge, the stronger your grasp of the new learning will be, and the</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>more connections you create that will help you remember it later.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>every time you learn something new, you change the brain—the</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Understanding that this is so enables you to see failure as a badge of effort and a source of useful information—the need to dig deeper or to try a different strategy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Making mistakes and correcting them builds the bridges to advanced learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Learning is stronger when it matters,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>rising familiarity with a text and fluency in reading it can create an illusion of mastery.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mastering the lecture or the text is not the same as mastering the ideas behind them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But if we stop thinking of testing as a dipstick to measure learning—if we think of it as practicing retrieval of learning from memory rather than “testing,” we open ourselves to another possibility: the use of testing as a tool for learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Pitting the learning of basic knowledge against the development of creative thinking is a false choice. Both need to be cultivated. The stronger one’s knowledge about the subject at hand, the more nuanced one’s creativity can be in addressing a new problem.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There was concern that if students tested better in the final exam on material that had been quizzed than on material not quizzed, it could be argued that the simple act of reexposing them to the material in the quizzes was responsible for the superior learning, not the retrieval practice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the act of retrieving a memory changes the memory, making it easier to retrieve again later.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Students who have been quizzed have a double advantage over those who have not: a more accurate sense of what they know and don’t know, and the strengthening of learning that accrues from retrieval practice.16</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when the mind has to work, learning sticks better. The greater the effort to retrieve learning, provided that you succeed, the more that learning is strengthened by retrieval.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Practice that’s spaced out, interleaved with other learning, and varied produces better mastery, longer retention, and more versatility.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Spacing out your practice feels less productive for the very reason that some forgetting has set in and you’ve got to work harder to recall the concepts. It doesn’t feel like you’re on top of it. What you don’t sense in the moment is that this added effort is making the learning stronger.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The mixing of problem types, which boosted final test performance by a remarkable 215 percent, actually impeded performance during initial learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But the research shows unequivocally that mastery and long-term retention are much better if you interleave practice than if you mass it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When you have learned under conditions of massed or blocked repetition, you have had no practice on that critical sorting process. But this is the way life usually unfolds: problems and opportunities come at us unpredictably, out of sequence. For our learning to have practical value, we must be adept at discerning “What kind of problem is this?” so we can select and apply an appropriate solution. Several studies have demonstrated the improved powers of discrimination to be gained through interleaved and varied practice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s not just what you know, but how you practice what you know that determines how well the learning serves you later.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>go to these conferences and they have no repeated exposure whatsoever to it. It’s just a matter of happenstance whether they end up finally seeing a patient in the future whose problem relates back to the conference topic. Otherwise, they don’t study the material, they are certainly not tested on the material, they just listen then they walk out.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Larsen would like to see something done to interrupt the forgetting: give a quiz at the end of a conference and follow it with spaced retrieval practice. “Make quizzing a standard part of the culture and the curriculum. You just know every week you’re going to get in your email your ten questions that you need to work through.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>How big an interval, you ask? The simple answer: enough so that practice doesn’t become a mindless repetition. At a minimum, enough time so that a little forgetting has set in. A little forgetting between practice sessions can be a good thing, if it leads to more effort in practice, but you do not want so much forgetting that retrieval essentially involves relearning the material.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sleep seems to play a large role in memory consolidation, so practice with at least a day in between sessions is good.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Interleaving two or more subjects during practice also provides a form of spacing. Interleaving can also help you develop your ability to discriminate later between different kinds of problems and select the right tool from your growing toolkit of solutions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Beware of the familiarity trap: the feeling that you know something and no longer need to practice it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Like interleaving, varied practice helps learners build a broad schema, an ability to assess changing conditions and adjust responses to fit.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You need to shuffle your flashcards. If you always practice the same skill in the same way, from the same place on the ice or field, in the same set of math problems, or during the same sequence in a flight simulator, you’re starving your learning on short rations of variety. Spacing, interleaving, and variability are natural features of how we conduct our lives.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Reflection is a form of retrieval practice (What happened? What did I do? How did it work out?), enhanced with elaboration (What would I do differently next time?).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Testing is not only a powerful learning strategy, it is a potent reality check on the accuracy of your own judgment of what you know how to do. When confidence is based on repeated performance, demonstrated through testing that simulates real-world conditions, you can lean into it. Facing the jump door may always reawaken feelings of terror, but the moment she’s out, Mia says, the fear evaporates.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the process of learning something often starts out feeling disorganized and unwieldy; the most important aspects are not always salient. Consolidation helps organize and solidify learning, and, notably, so does retrieval after a lapse of some time, because the act of retrieving a memory from long-term storage can both strengthen the memory traces and at the same time make them modifiable again, enabling them, for example, to connect to more recent learning. This process is called reconsolidation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you let the memory recede a little, for example by spacing or interleaving the</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>practice, retrieval is harder, your performance is less accomplished, and you feel let down, but your learning is deeper and you will retrieve it more easily in the future.4</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Knowledge, skills, and experiences that are vivid and hold significance, and those that are periodically practiced, stay with us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The mental rehearsal you conduct while lying in your bunk too tired to sleep and wishing the next day was already over and well-jumped is a form of spaced practice, and that helps you, too.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There’s virtually no limit to how much learning we can remember as long as we relate it to what we already know. In fact, because new learning depends on prior learning, the more we learn,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the more possible connections we create for further learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This limitation on retrieval is helpful to us: if every memory were always readily to hand, you would have a hard time sorting through the sheer volume of material to put your finger on the knowledge you need at the moment: where did I put my hat, how do I sync my electronic devices, what goes into a perfect brandy Manhattan?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when a sight or sound or smell brings back a memory in full force, even some episode you have not thought about in years.8</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Context can unleash memories, as when the right key works to open an old lock. In Marcel Proust’s Remembrance of Things Past,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the more effort required to retrieve (or, in effect, relearn) something, the better you learn it. In other words, the more you’ve forgotten about a topic, the more effective relearning will be in shaping your permanent knowledge.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The more effort that is required to recall a memory or to execute a skill, provided that the effort succeeds, the more the act of recalling or executing benefits the learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s the effortful process of reconstructing the knowledge that triggers reconsolidation and deeper learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It turns out that when the outline of a lecture proceeds in a different order from the textbook passage, the effort to discern the main ideas and reconcile the discrepancy produces better recall of the content. In another surprise, when letters are omitted from words in a text, requiring the reader to supply them, reading is slowed, and retention improves.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Having to write a short essay makes them stronger still. Overcoming these mild difficulties is a form of active learning, where students engage in higher-order thinking tasks rather than passively receiving knowledge</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s better to solve a problem than to memorize a solution. It’s better to attempt a solution and supply the incorrect answer than not to make the attempt.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>(retrieval, elaboration, generation)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>students who have a high fear of making errors when taking tests may actually do worse on the test because of their anxiety.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>of their working memory capacity is expended to monitor their performance</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>leaving less working memory capacity available to solve the problems posed by the test.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>thousands of hours of dedicated practice in which one strives to surpass one’s current level of ability, a process in which failure becomes an essential experience on the path to mastery.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s trusting that trying to solve a puzzle serves us better than being spoon-fed the solution, even if we fall short in our first attempts at an answer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Look, blundering’s really not a bad thing. It’s a good thing in that you get stuff done. A lot of people, when they contemplate the enormity of the task and they see all that’s entailed, they’re stopped in their tracks.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Of course, in some settings—like learning to jump out of airplanes</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>is not the optimal learning strategy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To be desirable, a difficulty must be something learners can overcome through increased effort.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>definition of desiderable difficulties</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Trying to come up with an answer rather than having it presented to you, or trying to solve a problem before being shown the solution, leads to better learning and longer retention of the correct answer or solution, even when your attempted response is wrong, so long as corrective feedback is provided.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Good judgment is a skill one must acquire, becoming an astute observer of one’s own thinking and performance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>One is that when we’re incompetent, we tend to overestimate our competence and see little reason to change.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To become more competent, or even expert, we must learn to recognize competence when we see it in others, become more accurate judges of what we ourselves know and don’t know, adopt learning strategies that get results, and find objective ways to track our progress.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Memory has some similarities to a Google search algorithm, in the sense that the more you connect what you learn to what you already know, and the more associations you make to a memory (for example, linking it with a visual image, a place, or a larger story), then the more mental cues you have through which to find and retrieve the memory again later.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Memory is a reconstruction. We cannot remember every aspect of an event, so we remember those elements that have greatest emotional significance for us, and we fill in the gaps with details of our own that are consistent with our narrative but may be wrong.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“the big lie” technique—even a big lie told repeatedly can come to be accepted as truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the feeling of knowing and be mistaken for true.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>social influence and tend to align with the memories of the people around us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Their research showed that incompetent people overestimate their own competence and, failing to sense a mismatch between their performance and what is desirable, see no need to try to improve. (The title of their initial paper on the topic was “Unskilled and Unaware of It.”)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it’s easy to blame the tool for what the hand cannot do.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The paradox is that those students who employ the least effective study strategies overestimate their learning the most and, as a consequence of their misplaced confidence, they are not inclined to change their habits.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Don’t make the mistake of dropping material from your testing regime once you’ve gotten it correct a couple of times. If it’s important, it needs to be practiced, and practiced again. And don’t put stock in momentary gains that result from massed practice. Space your testing, vary your practice, keep the long view.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>How ably you can explain a text is an excellent cue for judging comprehension, because you must recall the salient points from memory, put them into your own words, and explain why they are significant—how they relate to the larger subject.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Action beats reaction every time. That’s one mantra that’s drilled into our minds.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>because you will play like you practice. Sometimes the most powerful feedback for calibrating your sense of what you do and don’t know are the mistakes you make in the field, assuming you survive them and are receptive to the lesson.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>go where the competition isn’t, dig deep, ask the right questions, see the big picture, take risks, be honest.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Whether you think you can or you think you can’t, you’re right.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The stories we create to understand ourselves become the narratives of our lives, explaining the accidents and choices that have brought us where we are: what I’m good at, what I care about most, and where I’m headed. If you’re among the last kids standing on the sidelines as the softball teams are chosen up, the way you understand your place in the world likely changes a little, shaping your sense of ability and the subsequent paths you take.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Fluid intelligence is the ability to reason, see relationships, think abstractly, and hold information in mind while working on a problem; crystallized intelligence is one’s accumulated knowledge of the world and the procedures or mental models one has developed from past learning and experience.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Together, these two kinds of intelligence enable us to learn, reason, and solve problems.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Analytical intelligence is our ability to complete problem-solving tasks such as those typically contained in tests; creative intelligence is our ability to synthesize and apply existing knowledge and skills to deal with new and unusual situations; practical intelligence is our ability to adapt to everyday life—to understand what needs to be done in a specific setting and then do it; what we call street smarts. Different cultures and learning situations draw on these intelligences differently, and much of what’s required to succeed in a particular situation is not measured by standard IQ or aptitude tests, which can miss critical competencies.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Dynamic testing has three steps. Step 1: a test of some kind—perhaps an experience or a paper exam—shows me where I come up short in knowledge or a skill. Step 2: I dedicate myself to becoming more competent, using reflection, practice, spacing, and the other techniques of effective learning. Step 3: I test myself again, paying attention to what works better now but also, and especially, to where I still need more work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>cultivating the habit of reflecting on one’s experiences, of making them into a story, strengthens learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Knowledge is not knowhow until you understand the underlying principles at work and can fit them together into a structure larger than the sum of its parts. Knowhow is learning that enables you to go do.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Describe what you want to know, do, or accomplish. Then list the competencies required, what you need to learn, and where you can find the knowledge or skill. Then go get it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you go for more than knowledge. You go for knowhow. And that kind of mastery will put you ahead.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The marshmallow study is sublime in its simplicity and as a metaphor for life. We are born with the gift of our genes, but to a surprising degree our success is also determined by focus and self-discipline, which are the offspring of motivation and one’s sense of personal empowerment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>world endowed with the raw material of our genes, but we become capable through the learning and development of mental models and neural pathways that enable us to reason, solve, and create.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We’re born with about 100 billion nerve cells, called neurons. A synapse is a connection between neurons, enabling them to pass signals. For a period shortly before and after birth, we undergo “an exuberant burst of synapse formation,” in which the brain wires itself: the neurons sprout microscopic branches, called axons, that reach out in search of tiny nubs on other neurons, called dendrites. When axon meets dendrite, a synapse is formed. In order for some axons to find their target dendrites they must travel vast distances to complete the connections that make up our neural circuitry (a journey of such daunting scale and precision that Bruer likens it to finding one’s way clear across the United States to a waiting partner on the opposite coast, not unlike Kit Carson’s mission to President Polk for General Fremont). It’s this circuitry that enables our senses, cognition, and motor skills, including learning and memory, and it is this circuitry that forms the possibilities and the limits of one’s intellectual capacity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the eyes are not what sees, the brain is. The eyes sense, and the brain interprets. The success of this device relies on the brain learning to interpret signals from the tongue as sight.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>hippocampus, where we consolidate learning and memory, is able to generate new neurons throughout life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The fact that retrieval practice, spacing, rehearsal, rule learning, and the construction of mental models improve learning and memory is evidence of neuroplasticity and is consistent with scientists’ understanding of memory consolidation as an agent for increasing and strengthening the neural pathways by which one is later able to retrieve and apply learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nutrition affects IQ. Providing dietary supplements of fatty acids to pregnant women, breast-feeding women, and infants had the effect of increasing IQ by anywhere from 3.5 to 6.5 points.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>educational tools, books, and puzzles and trained how to help their children learn to speak and identify objects in the home, the children showed IQ gains.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When mothers of three-year-olds in low-income families were trained to talk to their children frequently and at length and to draw out the children with many open-ended questions, the children’s IQs rose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The brain is not a muscle, so strengthening one skill does not automatically strengthen others.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Study skills and learning skills are inert until they’re powered by an active ingredient,” Dweck says. The active ingredient is the simple but nonetheless profound realization that the power to increase your abilities lies largely within your own control.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>success. “Study skills and learning skills are inert until they’re powered by an active ingredient,” Dweck says. The active ingredient is the simple but nonetheless profound realization that the power to increase your abilities lies largely within your own control.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If people knew how hard I worked to get my mastery, it wouldn’t seem so wonderful after all.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Humans remember pictures more easily than words.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Despite being well grounded in their material, the stakes at play can make their minds go blank the moment they confront the empty exam booklet and the proctor’s ticking clock. That’s where having taken the time to construct a memory palace proves as good as gold. It’s not important that you understand the intricacies of British A-levels, just that they are difficult and highly consequential, which is why mnemonic devices are such a welcome tool at exam time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mnemonic devices are sometimes discounted as tricks of memory, not tools that fundamentally add to learning, and in a sense this is correct. The value of mnemonics to raise intellectual abilities comes after mastery of new material, as the students at Bellerbys are using them: as handy mental pockets for filing what they’ve learned, and linking the main ideas in each pocket to vivid memory cues so that they can readily bring them to mind and retrieve the associated concepts and details, in depth, at the unexpected moments that the need arises.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The more we do, the more we can do. To embrace this principle and reap its benefits is to be sustained through life by a growth mindset.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What are the key ideas? What terms or ideas are new to me? How would I define them? How do the ideas relate to what I already know?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Periodically practicing new knowledge and skills through self-quizzing strengthens your learning of it and your ability to connect it to prior knowledge.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you’re struggling to retrieve new learning is the fact that every time you work hard to recall a memory, you actually strengthen it. If you restudy something after failing to recall it, you actually learn it better than if you had not tried to recall it. The effort of retrieving knowledge or skills strengthens its staying power and your ability to recall it in the future.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>as you quiz yourself on new material, also reach back to retrieve prior material and ask yourself how that knowledge relates to what you have subsequently learned.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Establish a schedule of self-quizzing that allows time to elapse between study sessions. How much time? It depends on the material.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Another way of spacing retrieval practice is to interleave the study of two or more topics, so that alternating between them requires that you continually refresh your mind on each topic as you return to it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As you reconstruct learning from long-term memory, as awkward as it feels, you are strengthening your mastery as well as the memory.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>alternately quizzing yourself on various problem types and retrieving the appropriate solutions for each.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Even when learners achieve superior mastery from interleaved practice, they persist in feeling that blocked practice serves them better. You may also experience this feeling, but you now have the advantage of knowing that studies show that this feeling is illusory.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>ELABORATION improves your mastery of new material and multiplies the mental cues available to you for later recall and application of it</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>is the process of finding additional layers of meaning in new material.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>relating the material to what you already know, explaining it to somebody else in your own words, or explaining how it relates to your life outside of class.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The more that you can elaborate on how new learning relates to what you already know, the stronger your grasp of the new learning will be, and the more connections you create to remember it later.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>GENERATION has the effect of making the mind more receptive to new learning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Generation is an attempt to answer a question or solve a problem before being shown the answer or the solution.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You can practice generation when reading new class material by trying to explain beforehand the key ideas you expect to find in the material and how you expect they will relate to your prior knowledge. Then read the material to see if you were correct. As a result of having made the initial effort, you will be more astute at gleaning the substance and relevance of the reading material, even if it differs from your expectation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>REFLECTION is a combination of retrieval practice and elaboration that adds layers to learning and strengthens skills.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Reflection is the act of taking a few minutes to review what has been learned in a recent class or experience and asking yourself questions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>CALIBRATION is the act of aligning your judgments of what you know and don’t know with objective feedback so as to avoid being carried off by the illusions of mastery that catch many learners by surprise at test time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>MNEMONIC DEVICES help you to retrieve what you have learned and to hold arbitrary information in memory</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>They give you handy ways to store information and find it again when you need it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mnemonics are not tools for learning per se but for creating mental structures that make it easier to retrieve what you have learned.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>He says there’s not enough time to learn everything about everything, but pausing to make it meaningful helps it stick.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But once you engage the mind in trying to make sense of something new, the mind begins to “knit” at the problem on its own.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>your mind, in one way or another, is working on it twenty-four hours a day—yes, while you sleep—but only if some sort of draft or earlier version exists.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You engage it by making the effort to explain the material yourself, in your own words—connecting the facts, making it vivid, relating it to what you already know. Learning, like writing, is an act of engagement. Struggling with the puzzle stirs your creative juices, sets the mind to looking for parallels and metaphors from elsewhere in your experience, knowledge that can be transferred and applied here. It makes you hungry for the solution. And the solution, when you arrive at it, becomes more deeply embedded with your prior knowledge and abilities than anything pasted onto the surface of your brain by PowerPoint. So take a page from McPhee: when you want to master something new, delete the whimpering and go wrestle the bear.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In particular, students must be helped to understand such fundamental ideas as these:</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I can see them start to look through their notes. I say, “Stop. Do not look at your notes. Just take a minute to think about it yourself.” I tell them our brains are like a forest, and your memory is in there somewhere. You’re here, and the memory is over there. The more times you make a path to that memory, the better the path is, so that the next time you need the memory, it’s going to be easier to find it. But as soon as you get your notes out, you have short-circuited the path. You are not exploring for the path anymore, someone has told you the way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If you’ve read every word of this chapter, you’re not being very efficient.” The point is not to “slide your eyes over the words.” You start with questions, and you read for answers.8</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>how to shoot an azimuth. It’s a skill used for keeping your bearings in unfamiliar territory.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>high-structure classes help students who lack a history of using effective learning techniques and habits to develop them and succeed in rigorous settings.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>few things you might consider doing. One, get a copy of the presentation materials and use them to quiz yourself on the key ideas, much as Nathaniel Fuller quizzes himself</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>commercial training platform called Qstream that helps trainers send learners periodic quizzes via their mobile devices to strengthen learning through spaced retrieval practice. Similarly, an emerging platform called Osmosis uses mobile and Web based software to provide learners access to thousands of crowdsourced practice questions and explanations. Osmosis combines the testing effect, spacing, and social networking to facilitate what its developers call “student-driven social learning.” Qstream (qstream.com) and Osmosis (osmose-it.com) suggest interesting possibilities for redesigning in-service training for professionals. Many other companies are developing similar programs.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kaizen is a Japanese term for improvement.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The idea is not to let words just “slide through your brain.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2014-10-30-make-it-stick.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
