<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>condensō [en]</title>
        <link>https://jak3.github.io</link>
        <description><![CDATA[GM's e-notecard system]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2017 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Sleep</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-08-16-sleep.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#sleep">Sleep</a><ul>
<li><a href="#pre-sleep-routine">Pre Sleep Routine</a></li>
<li><a href="#post-sleep-routine">Post Sleep Routine</a></li>
<li><a href="#nap">NAP</a></li>
<li><a href="#quotes">Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="sleep">Sleep</h1>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1471745675l/31566948.jpg" />

</div>
<ul>
<li>It is better to think about quality rather than quantity when dealing with sleep. Quality can be determined not only when your are asleep, your routine while you are awake is important too.</li>
<li>Try to improve one step at a time. Little progresses make big differences.</li>
<li>Our biological clocks are regulated by external stimuli such as:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>sunlight</li>
<li>temperature</li>
<li>meal time</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Circadian rhythms work also without external stimuli</li>
<li>Homeostatic pressure determine our need to sleep. This need start when we wake up and keep increase while we are awake.</li>
<li>During night we attain the more efficient sleeping time near 2-3am (twelve hours later there is a compensation time span, it is really common for most of us to feel drowsy.</li>
<li>Light stimulate seratonin production, a neurotransmitter that increase well being and which melatonin is a derivative.</li>
<li>Blue light, dring the day as beneficial effects such as increase performance and reflexes. It is also reduce melatonin levels. It is a bad habit use blue light during the night as you might expect. Professor Idzikowsky define consequences of that bad habit (blue light from monitors before going to sleep) “junk sleep”. It is self explanatory.</li>
<li><p>In literature exist <code>3</code> chronotypes:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>He who go to sleep and get up early (<strong>AM</strong>)</li>
<li>He who go to sleep and get up late (<strong>PM</strong>)</li>
<li>He who stay between <strong>1</strong> and <strong>2</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>Check out the online quiz and <a href="https://www.bioinfo.mpg.de/mctq/core_work_life/core/introduction.jsp">find what is your chronotype</a> (thanks to University of Monaco).</p></li>
<li>Melatonina is a hormone that is produced by the pineal gland. It regulate your need to go to sleep.</li>
<li>Caffeine is a central nervous system stimulant. It is the world’s most widely consumed psychoactive drug. Unlike many other psychoactive substances, it is legal and unregulated in nearly all parts of the world. It reversibly blocks the action of adenosine on its receptor and consequently prevents the onset of drowsiness induced by adenosine. Caffeine also stimulates certain portions of the autonomic nervous system. Optimal dose for athletes is <code>3-6</code> milligrams per kilograms of body mass. It is a half-life that can be arrive up to six hours. <em>Use caffeine as a power boost, not as a substance that you need in order to do the minimum.</em></li>
<li>Stop waking up late during the weekend, try to keep your morning routine as much as possible.</li>
<li>Is is proven that <code>90</code> minutes is the range needed to pass through each sleep phases. The more important are:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><strong>light sleep</strong>: in which information are consolidated and motor skills performance increase.</li>
<li><p><strong>deep sleep</strong>: brain produce delta wave, the least frequency wave emitted (where we are awake brain produce beta waves that have an higher frequency). More deep sleep the better. We have the most beneficial effects and one of them is the production of growth hormone.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>born new cells, fix tissue and leave a feeling of renewal.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><strong>REM (Rapid Eye Movement)</strong>: dreaming phase, here the mind trick us with dreams while the body is paralyzed. Studies report that <strong>REM sleep increase creativity</strong>.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>It is not possible to get back lost sleep. Try to go to bed early or sleep for too long is time wasted. Our body is able to adapt, if you want to recover something, focus on keep your routine without too much worrying.</li>
<li>Keep a fix time to wake up is the best method we have to increase our sleeping quality.</li>
<li>Focus on <strong>cycles</strong> per night. A cycle is <strong>90 minutes of sleep</strong>.</li>
<li>Try to find out how many cycles are best suite for us. If for example we have seen that we need <code>5</code> cycles per night, we must try to not have three consecutive nights with less cycles. It is really important to find out <strong>How many cycles we need to feel restful and increase our daily routine performance</strong>. We must be ready to feel our body and mind responses while change cycles per night. Try at least for a week before switch.</li>
<li>Do not think that sleep can only be done only monophasically. In a time window of 24 hours there are other opportunities to compensate a poor night sleep.</li>
<li>Our biggest problem is psychological. Common bias that we need <code>8</code> hours of sleep per night is a real beast. It is difficult now think that <code>4.30</code> is enough.</li>
<li>When we get older, our sleep habit shift one bit at a time from a monophasic to a polyphasic sleep.</li>
<li>Sleep on your side is the recommended position. Better if your slave side, because is the side least used so less sensible. In addition, the dominant side can be think as “the reactive” side that can help you defense against attacks while sleeping (in order to sleep well we need to feel secure).</li>
<li>Try to use your bedroom only for sleeping activities.</li>
<li>“<em>Mouth breathing increase the number of sleep apnoea as well as probability to snore.</em>” - Patrick McKeown <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26533127-the-oxygen-advantage">The Oxygen Advantage</a></li>
<li>You can find if you have a good mattress if while you are on your side, the distance between the mattress and your head is less than two fist.</li>
<li>Double bed, as the word say <strong>must</strong> be at least <code>180</code> centimeters (width). Lesser the space we have higher is the probability to disturb our or our partner sleep. Sleep with someone else have benefits <strong>pre</strong> and <strong>post</strong> sleep. In an ideal world, we only [pre/post]sleep together.</li>
<li>Duvet optimal values: <code>13,5</code> tog during winter, <code>4,5</code> tog during summer, <code>9,0</code> tog during autumn and spring. In hot summer obviously we can use only a duvet cover or nothing at all.</li>
<li>Bedroom best practices:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>minimal forniture, cleaned space and color neutral.</li>
<li>can be totally overshadowed (use a night mask can be bothersome, we must be as free as possible).</li>
<li>temperature should be between <code>16-18</code> celsius degree.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Use your bed only for sleeping.</li>
<li>Try to avoid a bottle of water near the bed. Think: why do you need it? If you wake up with a dry throat probably is because you are breathing with your mouth while sleeping. If you wake up in order to go to the bathroom, maybe you have drink too much before sleep. In addition keep a bottle of water near your bed, let your mind think about it during night, with higher probability to think you need a sip.</li>
<li>The best alarm clock is a sunrise simulator. A device useful not only for whom suffering SAD (Seasonal Affective Disorder) but for everyone that try to wake up with a “sunrise”. A sunrise simulator has beneficial brain and body effects in addition to emotional feelings and well being.</li>
<li>Benefits that come with <strong>R90 program</strong> (all tips mentioned above and below) become effective only in addition to good nutrition and body exercises. Tackle these three problems together and each one enhance benefits to the rest. Your life surely will be better.</li>
<li>Tryptophan is an α-amino acid that is used in the biosynthesis of proteins. It is essential in humans, meaning the body cannot synthesize it and thus it must be obtained from the diet (fish, banana, dried fruit). Tryptophan is also a precursor to the neurotransmitter serotonin and the hormone melatonin. Sport athletes use <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1082898/">Montmorency’s cherry</a> as bio-hacking supplement. Glyn Howatson professor of Northumbria University has lead numerous studies that prove his beneficial effects and his efficiency after an intensive physical activity. In addition Glyn proved that these black berry increase melatonin production.</li>
<li>Oregon State University stated that <code>150</code> minutes of physical training per week, enhance sleep quality by <code>65%</code>.</li>
<li>Sleeping pills can give addiction, memory loss and sleepwalking</li>
<li>Think about your sleep in a time window of <code>7</code> days. One night is not enough to draw conclusions</li>
<li><p>Usually it is more problematic to <strong>travel</strong> eastward rather than westward. Good tips are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Go to bed and get up early some days before your departure.</li>
<li>Expose to sunlight early each day and avoid it during the evening</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sunlights</strong> is a lot of more effective rather than caffeine to keep you awake and sleeping pills to make you sleep.</p></li>
<li>An unbalanced sleep, typical to shift workers can lead to different problems such as depression, immune system imbalance, increase risk for cancer, cronic cardiopathy and metabolism disorders (type 2 diabetes). It is proven that being under these changes has severe health consequences. A study done to a sample of <code>70.000</code> nurses with a time window of 22 years has proven that after 5 years of shift work, probabilities to early death increase. Play with our internal clock has consequences. Always.</li>
<li><strong>winter blues</strong>: winter tendency to slow down mood and wants. You can try to avoid winter blues trying to go out and get direct sunlight between 11am to 16pm</li>
<li>National Sleep Foundation recommend for newborns from 14 to 17 sleep hours per day. A quantity that decrease while children grow. 9 to 11 when they start to go to school and 8 to 10 at the age of fourteen.</li>
<li>Help your children to sleep well using pre and post routines and avoid/banish stimulant substances such as sugars.</li>
<li>Teenagers sleep more because is your body that need more sleep.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="pre-sleep-routine">Pre Sleep Routine</h2>
<ul>
<li>A pre-sleep routine enhance your sleeping quality. Sometimes is better to reduce sleeping time in order to do your routine. Remember that it is a way much better <strong>quality</strong> rather than <strong>quantity</strong> in sleep.</li>
<li>Keep your bedroom with fresh air (not cold) is really important.</li>
<li>Have a warm shower rise your body temperature. When you get into bed, a little colder than you, works as naturally thermal excursion. In addition a lot of people feel comfortable getting into bed clean. It is not indispensable having a full shower, a rinse is enough.</li>
<li>Intensive training during afternoon or even evening increase bloody pressure (already at his maximum levels at that time) and for that reason it is not recommended before sleep, above all for the erderly. However going for a walk, yoga, stretching or low intensive exercises are recommended because as we said earlier rising your body temperature before sleeping can help.</li>
<li>Soften all surroundings is another tip. Switch off lights or keep them low, if possible choose lights with a warm color temperature.</li>
<li><p>Recommended activities:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Have a shower</li>
<li>Tidy up</li>
<li>Writing (thoughts, appointments, TODOs for the next day, stoic diary, …)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote></li>
<li>You might eat at least <code>3</code> hours before going to sleep. It is possible to have a snack but only before your pre-sleep routine (that is around <code>90</code> minutes).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="post-sleep-routine">Post Sleep Routine</h2>
<ul>
<li>Post sleep routine enhance our efficiency during the day.</li>
<li>If you wake up and your mouth is dry probably you breath throughout your mouth while asleep. Conversely if your mouth is wet, you are using your nose to breathe.</li>
<li>Cortisol (steroid hormone released in response to stress and low blood-glucose concentration) has his maximal level soon after your wake up time. It is useful start your day with relaxing activities, such as meditation, yoga, daily journal, reading…</li>
<li>When you wake up, get direct sunlight, it enhance our clarity of mind, it balance our biological clock and it prepare our body to switch from melatonin production to serotonin production.</li>
<li>Avoid un-healthy snacks (with too much sugar or difficult to digest).</li>
<li>If it is possible, have breakfast outdoor or at least in a room with a lot of sunlight. If outside the sun is not rise yet, switch on an artificial natural light.</li>
<li>It is a good habit doing some exercises, both high or low intensive. Having a walk, yoga, Taiji..</li>
<li>Easy mental activities such as listen to the radio, iron some clothes, tidy up, read and fix something are welcome.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="nap">NAP</h2>
<ul>
<li><em>Nap with steroids</em>: assume caffeine before having your nap boost results. <strong>NB</strong> (the desired effects arise approximately <code>30</code> minutes after consumption).</li>
<li>It is not necessary to have perfect conditions. You can make a nap while you are in a sitting position.</li>
<li>It is not important if you fall asleep or not. It is important that you take advantage of this resting time, <em>“switching off”</em> your brain.</li>
<li>Find a way to rest. Rest improve your efficiency and concentration, it is scientifically proven.</li>
<li>In addition, switching off your brain reduce stress and keep your productivity high during all day.</li>
<li>If you sleep (<code>1</code> cycle, <code>90</code> minutes, or more) during the day, it is preferred to choose between (<code>13-15</code>, <code>1pm-3pm</code>) and (<code>17-19</code>, <code>5pm-7pm</code>). The first one is better because is like the night period between <code>2am</code> and <code>3am</code> where the circadian stimulus is at his higher rate.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>We do not really know what sleep is. This may be upsetting for outsiders. - <a href="https://profiles.stanford.edu/philippe-mourrain?tab=bio">Philippe Mourrain</a></p>
<p>Breakfast is the most important meal. Period.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://sleepspecialist.co.uk/site-info-old/chris-idzikowski-1">Chris Idzikowski</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26533127-the-oxygen-advantage">The Oxygen Advantage</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1082898/">Montmorency’s cherry</a></li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-08-16-sleep.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>La Grande Via</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-05-29-grandevia.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#la-grande-via">La Grande Via</a><ul>
<li><a href="#diet">Diet</a></li>
<li><a href="#exercise">Exercise</a></li>
<li><a href="#meditation">Meditation</a></li>
<li><a href="#other-hints">Other hints</a></li>
<li><a href="#quotes">Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="la-grande-via">La Grande Via</h1>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://www.lagrandevia.it/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/lagrandevia-berrino-fontana.jpg" style="width:50.0%" />

</div>
<h2 id="diet">Diet</h2>
<ul>
<li>Stop eat before being full.</li>
<li>Fasting is a good habit. Do not eat few and often. Stomach needs to rest.</li>
<li>Eat until 3/4 full.</li>
<li>People can live eating 1/4, with other 3/4 live doctors.</li>
<li>TRF (Time Restricted Feeding) is lowering by 30% Kcal income per meal.</li>
<li><p>Fast 2 or 3 times a week. It is considered fasting:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Eat raw/cooked vegetables (avoid potatoes) with dressing such as olive oil (1 tbs per meal a day), lemon or vinegar No cereals, fruits or proteins.</li>
<li>Keep your stomach at rest at least 14 to 16 hours a day.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Have a bit of hungry is good, our body produces an hormone called Ghrelin. Ghrelin gene products have several actions on acute and chronic inflammation and autoimmunity.</li>
<li>Best breakfast time slot is between 7am to 9am</li>
<li>Buckwheat can be used to make cornmeal mush</li>
<li>Rye has lower glycemic load</li>
<li>Soybean has more proteins than parmigiano</li>
<li>Legumes raise HDL levels, you must eat them at least 2 or 4 times a week</li>
<li>Raw rice and lentils is a balance dish</li>
<li>Use malts and almond/hazelnut/sesame cremes together. Malts have high glycemia index but do not have fructose. Eat them with healthy fat as almon/hazelnut/sesame cremes decrease glucose absorption time. It useful eat them with legumes also.</li>
<li>Daily salt upper bound: 2,4g</li>
<li>Do not give sugar (in every form) to babies until 2 years old. White sugar if possible NEVER.</li>
<li>Mother feeding during pregnancy will be liked to her baby too</li>
<li>Eat fish 1 or 2 times a week</li>
<li>Eat fruits or jasmine Tea as dessert</li>
<li>Cultivate enhance health, Okinawa people are a living example</li>
<li><em>Nan kuru nai sa</em> - Everything will be OK</li>
<li>Pesco-vegetarians have much higher health levels (stats)</li>
<li>Calcium, tea, coffee, cocoa inhibits iron and zinc assimilation. Food with high levels of iron and zinc are grain cream, tahin, soy, azuki beans. Fermentation, sprouting and long leavening are practices that keep nutrients more assimilable</li>
<li>Vitamin D help calcium absorption. Calcium can be found in high quantities into turnip greens, cabbage (40-60% in comparison to only 30% in cow milk), legumes (eg: soy), figs.</li>
<li>In order to assimilate as much as possible nutrients from lettuce, use olive oil as dressing and add wild herbs such as lemon balm, mint, marjoram.</li>
<li>Pan-fry (with olive oil) vegetables in order to better assimilate carotenoids. Carotenoids:
<ul>
<li>alpha e beta carotene: green leaf or yellow vegetables</li>
<li>lycopene: tomatoes, peanuts</li>
<li>beta criptoxantina: pumpkin</li>
<li>lutein: cabbage</li>
<li>capsanthin: chili pepper, red pepper, paprika</li>
<li>crocin: saffron</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Vegetables must be eaten both raw and cooked (pan-fry or in hot water or steamed) Pan-fry cabbage enhance his nutrients, same with onion.</li>
<li>Garlic is better squashed. It releases chemical nutrients as defense mechanism.</li>
<li>Olive oil is useful to prevent thrombosis</li>
<li><p>Almonds and hazelnuts both raw or toasted reduce LDL</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="exercise">Exercise</h2>
<ul>
<li>Aerobic exercises for heart and lungs are walking, jogging, running, cycling, dancing, swimming and skiing</li>
<li>Doing exercises increase mitochondria levels (power and speed)</li>
<li>Benefits from exercises shade after 24-48 hours, keep your training session inside this time slot</li>
<li>Exercises and weight loss increase HDL levels</li>
<li>Exercises produce catepsina B useful in cognitive functions and memory</li>
<li>Heart rate upper bound is: 220 - age</li>
<li>HIT(High Interval Training) = switch between high intensive exercises (60s 90/85% max heart rate) with resting periods (60s). Do it 10 times per row Do not exceed 5/10 minutes of work. Metabolic effects are the same as long training sessions of aerobic exercises (100 minutes)</li>
<li>Exertion, feeding, alcohol, sleep and sex need caution</li>
<li>Exhale while lifting</li>
<li>Do not stay too much seated, change your posture often</li>
<li>Stretching! After some time passed seated and before exercises. It increase muscle grow, oxygenation and movement awareness</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="meditation">Meditation</h2>
<ul>
<li>“OM” vibes inhibit limbic system, it is responsible in controlling emotions</li>
<li>You don’t need to be in a temple or have particular things, nothing will follow you up</li>
<li><p>Yoga stages (by Patañjali):</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>External
<ul>
<li>Yama (passions)</li>
<li>Niyama (emotions)</li>
<li>Asana (know and keep healthy your body)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Breathing
<ul>
<li>Pranayama</li>
<li>Pratyahara</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Meditation (dharana, dhyana, samadhi)</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>Yoga and martial arts are good for kids:</p>
<ul>
<li>enhance ideas and planning</li>
<li>inhibit irrelevant informations and suppress their impulses</li>
<li>change and adapts behaviours</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Ataraxia = imperturbable spirit</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="other-hints">Other hints</h2>
<ul>
<li>Vitamin D is really important. During summer 5-15 minutes of direct sunlight are enough. For a much longer exposure sunscreen is needed. During winter before 10am and after 4pm UVB ray can’t go beyond ozone layer. It is useful sunbathing between 10am and 4pm. A dietary supplement of 800-1000 UI per day can be helpful (in winter).</li>
<li>Amory Lovins, expert in energy efficiency. He also wrote an interesting book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/12742309-reinventing-fire">Reinventing Fire</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Eat breakfast like a king, lunch like a prince, and dinner like a pauper.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Breakfast is for you, lunch to be shared and dinner gifted.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Fasting is the best cure, our doctor inside- Filippo Paracelso</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Meditation must start with the body. The body is the vehicle of himself, you need to control it in order to really meditate - Iyengar</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>A life without research is a life wasted</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Sky roads can be seen without looking out the windows</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Only in finite is expressed infinite and in time the eternal.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Watch your thoughts, they become words; watch your words, they become actions; watch your actions, they become habits; watch your habits, they become character; watch your character, for it becomes your destiny. - Frank Outlaw</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Happiness is also a way of interpreting the world, since while it may be difficult to change the world, it is always possible to change the way we look at it. - Matthieu Ricard</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>If something make you angry, think about what is more important: that thing or your health? In a moment, if you are wise enough, angry vanished. - Cao Tingdong</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>In cultivating body, mind and spirit it is necessary to keep in mind: be friendly, loyal and with broadminded. Not too much happy for praises nor too much angry for blames.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.lagrandevia.it/la-grande-via/">La grande via</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52036.Siddhartha">Siddharta</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/67896.Tao_Te_Ching">Tao te chin - Lao Tzu</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2340397.The_Philosophy_of_Spinoza">The philosophy of spinoza - Ratner J</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Longevity-Life-Preservation-Chinese-MING/dp/753772606X">Gong Ting Xian - Longevità e preservazione della vita</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun_Simiao">Sun Simiao</a></li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-05-29-grandevia.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
