<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>condensō [en]</title>
        <link>https://jak3.github.io</link>
        <description><![CDATA[GM's e-notecard system]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://jak3.github.io/gen/en/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Davening (Schachter-Shalomi, Rabbi Zalman)</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2021-02-18-davening.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#davening">Davening</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1355843320l/15893573.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="davening">Davening</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>We need that skepticism for quality assurance, because fooling oneself is easy. This is why I so love the statement in Psalm 34:9, “Taste and see that God is good.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if an insight emerges for you, take a few quiet moments to daven it in. And may you, too, as so many holy ones have before, experience the vision of prayer in your mind’s eye, the living taste of prayer in your heart, and the deep and gentle glow of prayer in your soul.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Deuteronomy 26:17–18, which speak of a reciprocal relationship between us and God. The verb used to capture this relationship is aleph-mem-resh. In the simple form this means “to say,” but here—uniquely in Torah—it is used in a transitive form: he’emarta and he’emirkha. God “says” us, and we “say” God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Just as I heard it said to me in a whisper, so I told it to you in a whisper” (Genesis Rabbah 3:4).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The imaginal world is a real world. Real things happen in the imaginal world that affect this world in turn.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>prayer begins with kavanah. To daven with kavanah means to pray with focus, intention, meaning. It means praying from the heart, rather than prayer centered solely in the mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kavanah is not attained in a day. We start small and build patiently on every small success. But if we aim our actions and our davening toward a godly place, we will get there.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I can’t do this without Your help.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Dear God, please help me to let this thought go.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>), wisdom to yield ko’ach mah (), the power of “What?”—the wisdom of getting to know what a thing is. Wise Mind seeks to understand the mitzvah lifnai ve-lifnim, inside and out. He wants to do the mitzvah in a completely integrated and organic way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“duties of the heart,” in Bachya ibn Pakuda’s famous phrase,3 cannot be fulfilled without conscious and deliberate intention.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Saying the words without intent is clearly unsatisfactory; on the other hand, saying every word and syllable with full and true kavanah is close to impossible.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My entire life and everything I do are nothing but God Godding Godself as Zalman. The best thing I can do, then, is to make my life a good ride for God, to consciously devote my actions to that purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The awareness that we stand in the presence of the Living God is one of the most important realizations we can install in our operative consciousness. God is always present. The question is, how present are we? We want to stand in that Presence without opacity. Our work is to penetrate, in meditation and in action, to the very heart of being nokhach penei ha-Shem (Lamentations 2:19), of being truly present before God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Meister Eckhart was trying to express when he wrote, “The eye with which I see God is the same eye with which God sees me. My eye and God’s eye are one eye, one sight, one knowledge, and one love.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>meditating on the Tetragrammaton, the letters of God’s mysterious name, can open a channel to bring down the holy. As in Vipassana or pranayama, we can use our breathing to help us get there. Your lungs without breath are like the yud, the smallest letter, the vanishing point. Our inhalation forms the hey, letter of breath: hhhhhhh. At the top of the breath we form the vav, straight as an erect backbone. Then we breathe out—hhhhhhh—another hey. So we invite YHVH to come down and dwell within us. As Jews we are concerned about living in this world. Ours is not primarily an Ein Sof focus, a preoccupation with the world beyond the beyond, but a Gaia focus. Our fundamental kavanah is not to leave the world behind but to bring God into this world, to create the “Kingdom of heaven” in the life we live, right here and now.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Yir’ah, awe, is sometimes translated as fear, but neither completely captures the idea. The Hebrew root of yir’ah is yud-resh-aleph . The root of words meaning sight or to see is resh-aleph-hey . Yir’ah arises from the state of being seen for what we really are.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The awareness that we are being seen, that we do everything we do in the presence of that Witness—that is the true path to and meaning of yir’ah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The disciple says, “Master, I couldn’t find a place where no One can see me.” The awareness that we are being seen, that we do everything we do in the presence of that Witness—that is the true path to and meaning of yir’ah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If I ascend to heaven, there You are; if I make my bed in hell, You are there” (Psalm 139:8).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Proverbs 3:6, “Be-khol derakhekha da’eihu, Know God in all your ways.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>important forms of consciousness maintenance, of kavanah watching kavanah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If I knew it, I would be it; if I were it, I would know it.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>le-khaven el ha-matarah, to aim at the bull’s-eye. (Le-khaven is from the same root as kavanah, kaf-vav-nun.) This is a useful metaphor. When I finally embrace a matarah—a bull’s-eye, a target for my existence—and I say, “Yes, I will go with that, I will collaborate with that, I will invest myself in that,” then my embracing becomes a kavanah.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>olam ha-ba—not “the world to come,” as the phrase is usually translated, but a world that is, at this very moment, becoming in us and around us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I come with a scroll-book on me,” says the psalmist, “in which there is one thing written”—like a journal, in which you declare its purpose on page one. This is what the scroll says: “My only desire is to do Your will. I want Your teaching in my very kishkes” (Psalm 40:8–9). This is my intent. This is what I want to do. I’m not there yet, but I’m on my way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>At the heart of kavanah lies the question: Why? Hebrew has two different words for why, madu’a and lamah, and each has a slightly different emphasis. Madu’a asks, “Mah yadu’a? What is known to us?” Philosophers might call this the what of etiology. It wants to know about origins and causes. Lamah asks, “Le-mah? What for?” This is the why of teleology. It asks: Where are we going with this? What is the goal? The why at the heart of kavanah is not only the madu’a of origins but the lamah of ultimate purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Every locksmith has a master key with which he can open many doors. Neginah is such a key, for it can unlock all doors.” Why? Because a niggun sung in the proper way is like doing teshuvah, like a moment of true repentance and turning to God. The wellsprings of niggun and teshuvah are the simple yearnings of the heart that we all share.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The word nusach can mean both text and melody.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>nusach can also mean the melody or musical mode of a given time and place, which is what I mean here. Nusach conveys information.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nusach also conveys emotion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The ga’agu’im or longing niggunim that raise up these unspoken questions can create a sacred space that all can share.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes the heart wants to daven, and the mind starts arguing. But, as the great cantor and educator Max Helfman said once, “you can’t argue with a song or a dance!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Maybe “the work is not upon you to finish” (Pirkei Avot 2:21). Someone else may complete your tune someday.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>with the emotions that you hear behind the words.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>emotional landscapes—sometimes within a single paragraph.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A niggun is a path to God, a “song of ascension.” But we must set out along that path! We must travel with that intention in mind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>True prayer is like the iceberg: little that is visible on the surface, much that happens below.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the invitation to prayer says “come as you are.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>our souls accept only one outcome when it comes to prayer: transformation. We do not wish just to spin our mental wheels: We want to be changed. We want to be moved. We want to end in a better place than where we started. Our souls yearn for this. If we really mean the words we say, how can we help but be moved?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>prayers as a journey through four different landscapes, four distinct facets of human experience: physical, emotional, intellectual, and spiritual. Each facet has its own character; each communicates in its own language; each speaks to a different part of us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Asiyah is the realm of the practical and the sensible—the stuff we apprehend with our senses. We’re packing for our spiritual journey here, grounding ourselves in our physical bodies and in the here and now.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Yetzirah, on a human level, is the world of feelings, the world of passion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The language here is plural. In Yetzirah, the realm of emotions and love, the boundaries between ourselves and others begin to feel permeable</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“I’m attracted to you in Asiyah! I love you in Yetzirah!” She’s saying, “Meet me in Beriyah.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In Beriyah, the language is no longer immanent but transcendent. Beriyah is the place of Wow, the place of wonder. We praise and give thanks for the constant and miraculous regeneration by a Creator who “renews, each day and always, the work of creation.” This is not the big bang understanding, in which a single event set the rest of the universe in motion. It is a mystical vision of the entire world being created anew in every instant. A person who sees the universe with such eyes can welcome each and every moment as a new opportunity for praise. In Beriyah, we are still in the group, but what the group does at this stage is to give you a matrix in which to do your individual work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>An important part of davening is to just sit be-nachat ru’ach, in serenity of spirit, and to allow for that to come in.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The word Atzilut refers to something that is noble, high, beyond. The world of Atzilut transcends our level of understanding. Boundaries are gone, definitions are gone. Individual words and thoughts are gone. We ourselves do not exist. Being as we know it has ceased.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kabbalistic tradition imagines us davening the Amidah in the world of Atzilut.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>So never mind the achievements and attainments; just talk like a friend to God about what you are really concerned about. If a thought comes, turn it into a prayer. These heartfelt prayers are the ones that are really important; these are the prayers we save for Atzilut, sending them directly to the highest level. I start by saying the introductory verse: “Adonai sefatai tiftach u-fi yagid tehilatekha, Please God, open my lips and let my mouth declare Your praise.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When a concern comes up for anything, turn it into a bakashah, a request. Then set is aside and go back to stillness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Each dimension of ourselves—physical, emotional, intellectual, spiritual—has its own needs and speaks its own language. I don’t want to leave any part of me out. I want my davening, my spiritual life and practice, to integrate them all. How can this holy conversation be real unless my entire self is engaged?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We cannot think our way to God. We cannot reach God by a safe, step-by-step process.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we limit God to the ultimate abstraction, then whom are we praying to? But if instead we come at this from a Yetzirah heart space, that changes everything. If we attune ourselves to Yetzirah, the language of the davening makes sense, and all the stuff that we’re talking about here make sense. The feeling that we’re “doing the divine thing” makes sense—that’s why I like the term davening best, to describe what we’re doing at prayer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Where in this many-layered universe does compassion reside? Who is the You of God for you?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All we need are feelings that we want to share with the listening presence of the universe. If you are not yet used to praying, start by expressing yourself in your own words.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>how much time they had. I got some flak</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Voice arouses kavanah,”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Daven so your heart can feel what your lips are saying!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Every breath will praise Yah” (Psalm 150:6). We can use this as a meditation with the YHVH, the Tetragrammaton. First empty your lungs and contemplate the yud, the smallest Hebrew letter, closest to emptiness. Then you breathe in, making a hhhhh sound; that’s the first hey. You hold the breath for a moment, sending it to all six directions in your body—that’s the vav, the sixth letter of the alphabet. Then you breathe out, hhhhh, to make the other hey. So we can use this prayer to scan our lung capacity and check in with our breath.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Barukh ha-Shem—thank God. At last! Now I am free just to sit and enjoy. I don’t need to run; I don’t need to make, do, fix, or change. For one day, I can just be.” If we pause from running through our day to offer a prayer, we find that we have created a little piece of Shabbos</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Throughout the centuries, the payyetanim—Jewish writers of spiritual poetry (piyyut, piyyutim)—have sought new ways of declaring their love for God.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ashkenazi siddurim have “Ahavah rabbah ahavtanu” in the morning prayers and “Ahavat olam beit Yisrael amkha ahavtah” in the evening prayer. Chabad and some of the Sepharad siddurim, however, follow the Ari, who saw an important kavanah in the first letters of ahavat olam ahavtanu: aleph (1) + ayin (70) + aleph (1) add up to 72, a number the kabbalists saw as a permutation of YHVH: yud = 10; yud hey = 15; yud hey vav = 21; yud hey vav hey = 26. And 10 + 15 + 21 + 26 = 72.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we study Torah, may we see clearly what is meant for us to know. When we do Mitzvot, may all our feelings sit harmonious in our heart. Focus all our hearts’ longing on that moment, when we stand in Your Presence, in awe and adoration.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>harder to grasp than it sounds. The Tikkunei Zohar marvels, “You are One, but not in the sense of enumeration”—not “one” as an alternative to two, three, or four, but a Unity of infinite existence and infinite potential.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>asking for what we truly need is the hardest part of prayer. We throw up all sorts of obstacles.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whom am I praying to? I am praying to God, however I understand and experience that word right here and right now. I may not be praying to the God that is All, but simply sharing my tsuris with the face of God with which I am most intimate. Perhaps I am praying to whatever it is that listens in the universe. I don’t need to do any more than that. Who am I to ask for anything? I am a creation and manifestation of godliness. I am a wave in the ocean and a world unto myself. The infinite potential for creativity and love in the universe manifests in me and through me, as it does in every other creature. And will it help? We know some parents pray with all their hearts for a child to be cured of a life-threatening disease, and yet the little one dies. We pray daily for peace, yet we are still at war. Prayer is not a switch with which we can control the universe. But I do believe that we can, with our prayers, reach dimensions of existence that we do not otherwise have access to and that the openings in those higher worlds bring blessings down to us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A prayer truly prayed is the beginnings of its own answer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“O God, open up my lips, and let my mouth speak Your praise.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This first sentence reminds us that prayer begins with silence. Think back to the silence that follows the last, enlarged dalet of the Shema statement’s final ECHAD. This is not a silence of absence but a silence full of the presence of the One, a silence of infinite potential.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we want our prayers to be answered, we have to make sure not to hang up the phone too quickly.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>During the week, you can take a piece of notepaper and a pencil. Reflect for a few moments after your davening and see what comes down. “So what do I have to do today, Ribbono shel olam?” Write down what comes to you, and try to refer to it during the day or before you go to sleep at night.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I begin in Asiyah, putting on my tallis and tefillin first, creating the prayer space that I need. I check in with my body, and I say Asher Yatzar, acknowledging the miracle of the limbs and organs that sustain me. Then I look out of the window and see the world outside, the people and the buildings and the trees, the sun or the rain or the snow, and I say, “Thank You, Ribbono shel olam, all of these are wonderful, and I thank You.” I want to spend a little time in Yetzirah if I possibly can, giving my emotions a voice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I know that without help I’m not going to make it. I close with the Amidah’s final thought: “Oseh shalom, just as in the heavens everything works out as it should, so please, bring peace and tranquility upon us as well.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the first task before us is to empty ourselves of our expectations—to free ourselves of the hold they have over us. I always quote Swami Satchidananda, who would say, “Don’t make any appointments, you won’t have any dis-appointments!”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Dear God, whatever jealousies and resentments I might harbor in my heart, please remove this judgment from me.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Reb Pinchas of Koretz, the great Hasidic master, wondered how we can pray for other people to become better. Are we not depriving that person of their choice and free will? The answer, he says, is that we are all part of each other. You are in me, and I am in you. Praying for the “you in me” to be better—the “you” that resides in my heart—somehow helps the “me in you” to do something good for you, and the “you in you” to become better. This is not a moral vision but an organismic vision. On a prayerful level, we are all part of each other and of the greater whole.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“If I am not for myself, who will be? But if I am only for myself, what am I?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>aleph-mem-nun, meaning to be firm or trustworthy. Amen means “So be it. May your words come to pass.” It is prayer and affirmation in one.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2021-02-18-davening.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Sleep</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-08-16-sleep.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#sleep">Sleep</a><ul>
<li><a href="#pre-sleep-routine">Pre Sleep Routine</a></li>
<li><a href="#post-sleep-routine">Post Sleep Routine</a></li>
<li><a href="#nap">NAP</a></li>
<li><a href="#quotes">Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="sleep">Sleep</h1>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1471745675l/31566948.jpg" />

</div>
<ul>
<li>It is better to think about quality rather than quantity when dealing with sleep. Quality can be determined not only when your are asleep, your routine while you are awake is important too.</li>
<li>Try to improve one step at a time. Little progresses make big differences.</li>
<li>Our biological clocks are regulated by external stimuli such as:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>sunlight</li>
<li>temperature</li>
<li>meal time</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Circadian rhythms work also without external stimuli</li>
<li>Homeostatic pressure determine our need to sleep. This need start when we wake up and keep increase while we are awake.</li>
<li>During night we attain the more efficient sleeping time near 2-3am (twelve hours later there is a compensation time span, it is really common for most of us to feel drowsy.</li>
<li>Light stimulate seratonin production, a neurotransmitter that increase well being and which melatonin is a derivative.</li>
<li>Blue light, dring the day as beneficial effects such as increase performance and reflexes. It is also reduce melatonin levels. It is a bad habit use blue light during the night as you might expect. Professor Idzikowsky define consequences of that bad habit (blue light from monitors before going to sleep) “junk sleep”. It is self explanatory.</li>
<li><p>In literature exist <code>3</code> chronotypes:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>He who go to sleep and get up early (<strong>AM</strong>)</li>
<li>He who go to sleep and get up late (<strong>PM</strong>)</li>
<li>He who stay between <strong>1</strong> and <strong>2</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>Check out the online quiz and <a href="https://www.bioinfo.mpg.de/mctq/core_work_life/core/introduction.jsp">find what is your chronotype</a> (thanks to University of Monaco).</p></li>
<li>Melatonina is a hormone that is produced by the pineal gland. It regulate your need to go to sleep.</li>
<li>Caffeine is a central nervous system stimulant. It is the world’s most widely consumed psychoactive drug. Unlike many other psychoactive substances, it is legal and unregulated in nearly all parts of the world. It reversibly blocks the action of adenosine on its receptor and consequently prevents the onset of drowsiness induced by adenosine. Caffeine also stimulates certain portions of the autonomic nervous system. Optimal dose for athletes is <code>3-6</code> milligrams per kilograms of body mass. It is a half-life that can be arrive up to six hours. <em>Use caffeine as a power boost, not as a substance that you need in order to do the minimum.</em></li>
<li>Stop waking up late during the weekend, try to keep your morning routine as much as possible.</li>
<li>Is is proven that <code>90</code> minutes is the range needed to pass through each sleep phases. The more important are:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><strong>light sleep</strong>: in which information are consolidated and motor skills performance increase.</li>
<li><p><strong>deep sleep</strong>: brain produce delta wave, the least frequency wave emitted (where we are awake brain produce beta waves that have an higher frequency). More deep sleep the better. We have the most beneficial effects and one of them is the production of growth hormone.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>born new cells, fix tissue and leave a feeling of renewal.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><strong>REM (Rapid Eye Movement)</strong>: dreaming phase, here the mind trick us with dreams while the body is paralyzed. Studies report that <strong>REM sleep increase creativity</strong>.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>It is not possible to get back lost sleep. Try to go to bed early or sleep for too long is time wasted. Our body is able to adapt, if you want to recover something, focus on keep your routine without too much worrying.</li>
<li>Keep a fix time to wake up is the best method we have to increase our sleeping quality.</li>
<li>Focus on <strong>cycles</strong> per night. A cycle is <strong>90 minutes of sleep</strong>.</li>
<li>Try to find out how many cycles are best suite for us. If for example we have seen that we need <code>5</code> cycles per night, we must try to not have three consecutive nights with less cycles. It is really important to find out <strong>How many cycles we need to feel restful and increase our daily routine performance</strong>. We must be ready to feel our body and mind responses while change cycles per night. Try at least for a week before switch.</li>
<li>Do not think that sleep can only be done only monophasically. In a time window of 24 hours there are other opportunities to compensate a poor night sleep.</li>
<li>Our biggest problem is psychological. Common bias that we need <code>8</code> hours of sleep per night is a real beast. It is difficult now think that <code>4.30</code> is enough.</li>
<li>When we get older, our sleep habit shift one bit at a time from a monophasic to a polyphasic sleep.</li>
<li>Sleep on your side is the recommended position. Better if your slave side, because is the side least used so less sensible. In addition, the dominant side can be think as “the reactive” side that can help you defense against attacks while sleeping (in order to sleep well we need to feel secure).</li>
<li>Try to use your bedroom only for sleeping activities.</li>
<li>“<em>Mouth breathing increase the number of sleep apnoea as well as probability to snore.</em>” - Patrick McKeown <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26533127-the-oxygen-advantage">The Oxygen Advantage</a></li>
<li>You can find if you have a good mattress if while you are on your side, the distance between the mattress and your head is less than two fist.</li>
<li>Double bed, as the word say <strong>must</strong> be at least <code>180</code> centimeters (width). Lesser the space we have higher is the probability to disturb our or our partner sleep. Sleep with someone else have benefits <strong>pre</strong> and <strong>post</strong> sleep. In an ideal world, we only [pre/post]sleep together.</li>
<li>Duvet optimal values: <code>13,5</code> tog during winter, <code>4,5</code> tog during summer, <code>9,0</code> tog during autumn and spring. In hot summer obviously we can use only a duvet cover or nothing at all.</li>
<li>Bedroom best practices:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>minimal forniture, cleaned space and color neutral.</li>
<li>can be totally overshadowed (use a night mask can be bothersome, we must be as free as possible).</li>
<li>temperature should be between <code>16-18</code> celsius degree.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Use your bed only for sleeping.</li>
<li>Try to avoid a bottle of water near the bed. Think: why do you need it? If you wake up with a dry throat probably is because you are breathing with your mouth while sleeping. If you wake up in order to go to the bathroom, maybe you have drink too much before sleep. In addition keep a bottle of water near your bed, let your mind think about it during night, with higher probability to think you need a sip.</li>
<li>The best alarm clock is a sunrise simulator. A device useful not only for whom suffering SAD (Seasonal Affective Disorder) but for everyone that try to wake up with a “sunrise”. A sunrise simulator has beneficial brain and body effects in addition to emotional feelings and well being.</li>
<li>Benefits that come with <strong>R90 program</strong> (all tips mentioned above and below) become effective only in addition to good nutrition and body exercises. Tackle these three problems together and each one enhance benefits to the rest. Your life surely will be better.</li>
<li>Tryptophan is an α-amino acid that is used in the biosynthesis of proteins. It is essential in humans, meaning the body cannot synthesize it and thus it must be obtained from the diet (fish, banana, dried fruit). Tryptophan is also a precursor to the neurotransmitter serotonin and the hormone melatonin. Sport athletes use <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1082898/">Montmorency’s cherry</a> as bio-hacking supplement. Glyn Howatson professor of Northumbria University has lead numerous studies that prove his beneficial effects and his efficiency after an intensive physical activity. In addition Glyn proved that these black berry increase melatonin production.</li>
<li>Oregon State University stated that <code>150</code> minutes of physical training per week, enhance sleep quality by <code>65%</code>.</li>
<li>Sleeping pills can give addiction, memory loss and sleepwalking</li>
<li>Think about your sleep in a time window of <code>7</code> days. One night is not enough to draw conclusions</li>
<li><p>Usually it is more problematic to <strong>travel</strong> eastward rather than westward. Good tips are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Go to bed and get up early some days before your departure.</li>
<li>Expose to sunlight early each day and avoid it during the evening</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sunlights</strong> is a lot of more effective rather than caffeine to keep you awake and sleeping pills to make you sleep.</p></li>
<li>An unbalanced sleep, typical to shift workers can lead to different problems such as depression, immune system imbalance, increase risk for cancer, cronic cardiopathy and metabolism disorders (type 2 diabetes). It is proven that being under these changes has severe health consequences. A study done to a sample of <code>70.000</code> nurses with a time window of 22 years has proven that after 5 years of shift work, probabilities to early death increase. Play with our internal clock has consequences. Always.</li>
<li><strong>winter blues</strong>: winter tendency to slow down mood and wants. You can try to avoid winter blues trying to go out and get direct sunlight between 11am to 16pm</li>
<li>National Sleep Foundation recommend for newborns from 14 to 17 sleep hours per day. A quantity that decrease while children grow. 9 to 11 when they start to go to school and 8 to 10 at the age of fourteen.</li>
<li>Help your children to sleep well using pre and post routines and avoid/banish stimulant substances such as sugars.</li>
<li>Teenagers sleep more because is your body that need more sleep.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="pre-sleep-routine">Pre Sleep Routine</h2>
<ul>
<li>A pre-sleep routine enhance your sleeping quality. Sometimes is better to reduce sleeping time in order to do your routine. Remember that it is a way much better <strong>quality</strong> rather than <strong>quantity</strong> in sleep.</li>
<li>Keep your bedroom with fresh air (not cold) is really important.</li>
<li>Have a warm shower rise your body temperature. When you get into bed, a little colder than you, works as naturally thermal excursion. In addition a lot of people feel comfortable getting into bed clean. It is not indispensable having a full shower, a rinse is enough.</li>
<li>Intensive training during afternoon or even evening increase bloody pressure (already at his maximum levels at that time) and for that reason it is not recommended before sleep, above all for the erderly. However going for a walk, yoga, stretching or low intensive exercises are recommended because as we said earlier rising your body temperature before sleeping can help.</li>
<li>Soften all surroundings is another tip. Switch off lights or keep them low, if possible choose lights with a warm color temperature.</li>
<li><p>Recommended activities:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Have a shower</li>
<li>Tidy up</li>
<li>Writing (thoughts, appointments, TODOs for the next day, stoic diary, …)</li>
</ol>
</blockquote></li>
<li>You might eat at least <code>3</code> hours before going to sleep. It is possible to have a snack but only before your pre-sleep routine (that is around <code>90</code> minutes).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="post-sleep-routine">Post Sleep Routine</h2>
<ul>
<li>Post sleep routine enhance our efficiency during the day.</li>
<li>If you wake up and your mouth is dry probably you breath throughout your mouth while asleep. Conversely if your mouth is wet, you are using your nose to breathe.</li>
<li>Cortisol (steroid hormone released in response to stress and low blood-glucose concentration) has his maximal level soon after your wake up time. It is useful start your day with relaxing activities, such as meditation, yoga, daily journal, reading…</li>
<li>When you wake up, get direct sunlight, it enhance our clarity of mind, it balance our biological clock and it prepare our body to switch from melatonin production to serotonin production.</li>
<li>Avoid un-healthy snacks (with too much sugar or difficult to digest).</li>
<li>If it is possible, have breakfast outdoor or at least in a room with a lot of sunlight. If outside the sun is not rise yet, switch on an artificial natural light.</li>
<li>It is a good habit doing some exercises, both high or low intensive. Having a walk, yoga, Taiji..</li>
<li>Easy mental activities such as listen to the radio, iron some clothes, tidy up, read and fix something are welcome.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="nap">NAP</h2>
<ul>
<li><em>Nap with steroids</em>: assume caffeine before having your nap boost results. <strong>NB</strong> (the desired effects arise approximately <code>30</code> minutes after consumption).</li>
<li>It is not necessary to have perfect conditions. You can make a nap while you are in a sitting position.</li>
<li>It is not important if you fall asleep or not. It is important that you take advantage of this resting time, <em>“switching off”</em> your brain.</li>
<li>Find a way to rest. Rest improve your efficiency and concentration, it is scientifically proven.</li>
<li>In addition, switching off your brain reduce stress and keep your productivity high during all day.</li>
<li>If you sleep (<code>1</code> cycle, <code>90</code> minutes, or more) during the day, it is preferred to choose between (<code>13-15</code>, <code>1pm-3pm</code>) and (<code>17-19</code>, <code>5pm-7pm</code>). The first one is better because is like the night period between <code>2am</code> and <code>3am</code> where the circadian stimulus is at his higher rate.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>We do not really know what sleep is. This may be upsetting for outsiders. - <a href="https://profiles.stanford.edu/philippe-mourrain?tab=bio">Philippe Mourrain</a></p>
<p>Breakfast is the most important meal. Period.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://sleepspecialist.co.uk/site-info-old/chris-idzikowski-1">Chris Idzikowski</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26533127-the-oxygen-advantage">The Oxygen Advantage</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1082898/">Montmorency’s cherry</a></li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-08-16-sleep.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>La Grande Via</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-05-29-grandevia.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#la-grande-via">La Grande Via</a><ul>
<li><a href="#diet">Diet</a></li>
<li><a href="#exercise">Exercise</a></li>
<li><a href="#meditation">Meditation</a></li>
<li><a href="#other-hints">Other hints</a></li>
<li><a href="#quotes">Quotes</a></li>
<li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="la-grande-via">La Grande Via</h1>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://www.lagrandevia.it/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/lagrandevia-berrino-fontana.jpg" style="width:50.0%" />

</div>
<h2 id="diet">Diet</h2>
<ul>
<li>Stop eat before being full.</li>
<li>Fasting is a good habit. Do not eat few and often. Stomach needs to rest.</li>
<li>Eat until 3/4 full.</li>
<li>People can live eating 1/4, with other 3/4 live doctors.</li>
<li>TRF (Time Restricted Feeding) is lowering by 30% Kcal income per meal.</li>
<li><p>Fast 2 or 3 times a week. It is considered fasting:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Eat raw/cooked vegetables (avoid potatoes) with dressing such as olive oil (1 tbs per meal a day), lemon or vinegar No cereals, fruits or proteins.</li>
<li>Keep your stomach at rest at least 14 to 16 hours a day.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Have a bit of hungry is good, our body produces an hormone called Ghrelin. Ghrelin gene products have several actions on acute and chronic inflammation and autoimmunity.</li>
<li>Best breakfast time slot is between 7am to 9am</li>
<li>Buckwheat can be used to make cornmeal mush</li>
<li>Rye has lower glycemic load</li>
<li>Soybean has more proteins than parmigiano</li>
<li>Legumes raise HDL levels, you must eat them at least 2 or 4 times a week</li>
<li>Raw rice and lentils is a balance dish</li>
<li>Use malts and almond/hazelnut/sesame cremes together. Malts have high glycemia index but do not have fructose. Eat them with healthy fat as almon/hazelnut/sesame cremes decrease glucose absorption time. It useful eat them with legumes also.</li>
<li>Daily salt upper bound: 2,4g</li>
<li>Do not give sugar (in every form) to babies until 2 years old. White sugar if possible NEVER.</li>
<li>Mother feeding during pregnancy will be liked to her baby too</li>
<li>Eat fish 1 or 2 times a week</li>
<li>Eat fruits or jasmine Tea as dessert</li>
<li>Cultivate enhance health, Okinawa people are a living example</li>
<li><em>Nan kuru nai sa</em> - Everything will be OK</li>
<li>Pesco-vegetarians have much higher health levels (stats)</li>
<li>Calcium, tea, coffee, cocoa inhibits iron and zinc assimilation. Food with high levels of iron and zinc are grain cream, tahin, soy, azuki beans. Fermentation, sprouting and long leavening are practices that keep nutrients more assimilable</li>
<li>Vitamin D help calcium absorption. Calcium can be found in high quantities into turnip greens, cabbage (40-60% in comparison to only 30% in cow milk), legumes (eg: soy), figs.</li>
<li>In order to assimilate as much as possible nutrients from lettuce, use olive oil as dressing and add wild herbs such as lemon balm, mint, marjoram.</li>
<li>Pan-fry (with olive oil) vegetables in order to better assimilate carotenoids. Carotenoids:
<ul>
<li>alpha e beta carotene: green leaf or yellow vegetables</li>
<li>lycopene: tomatoes, peanuts</li>
<li>beta criptoxantina: pumpkin</li>
<li>lutein: cabbage</li>
<li>capsanthin: chili pepper, red pepper, paprika</li>
<li>crocin: saffron</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Vegetables must be eaten both raw and cooked (pan-fry or in hot water or steamed) Pan-fry cabbage enhance his nutrients, same with onion.</li>
<li>Garlic is better squashed. It releases chemical nutrients as defense mechanism.</li>
<li>Olive oil is useful to prevent thrombosis</li>
<li><p>Almonds and hazelnuts both raw or toasted reduce LDL</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="exercise">Exercise</h2>
<ul>
<li>Aerobic exercises for heart and lungs are walking, jogging, running, cycling, dancing, swimming and skiing</li>
<li>Doing exercises increase mitochondria levels (power and speed)</li>
<li>Benefits from exercises shade after 24-48 hours, keep your training session inside this time slot</li>
<li>Exercises and weight loss increase HDL levels</li>
<li>Exercises produce catepsina B useful in cognitive functions and memory</li>
<li>Heart rate upper bound is: 220 - age</li>
<li>HIT(High Interval Training) = switch between high intensive exercises (60s 90/85% max heart rate) with resting periods (60s). Do it 10 times per row Do not exceed 5/10 minutes of work. Metabolic effects are the same as long training sessions of aerobic exercises (100 minutes)</li>
<li>Exertion, feeding, alcohol, sleep and sex need caution</li>
<li>Exhale while lifting</li>
<li>Do not stay too much seated, change your posture often</li>
<li>Stretching! After some time passed seated and before exercises. It increase muscle grow, oxygenation and movement awareness</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="meditation">Meditation</h2>
<ul>
<li>“OM” vibes inhibit limbic system, it is responsible in controlling emotions</li>
<li>You don’t need to be in a temple or have particular things, nothing will follow you up</li>
<li><p>Yoga stages (by Patañjali):</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>External
<ul>
<li>Yama (passions)</li>
<li>Niyama (emotions)</li>
<li>Asana (know and keep healthy your body)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Breathing
<ul>
<li>Pranayama</li>
<li>Pratyahara</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Meditation (dharana, dhyana, samadhi)</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>Yoga and martial arts are good for kids:</p>
<ul>
<li>enhance ideas and planning</li>
<li>inhibit irrelevant informations and suppress their impulses</li>
<li>change and adapts behaviours</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Ataraxia = imperturbable spirit</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="other-hints">Other hints</h2>
<ul>
<li>Vitamin D is really important. During summer 5-15 minutes of direct sunlight are enough. For a much longer exposure sunscreen is needed. During winter before 10am and after 4pm UVB ray can’t go beyond ozone layer. It is useful sunbathing between 10am and 4pm. A dietary supplement of 800-1000 UI per day can be helpful (in winter).</li>
<li>Amory Lovins, expert in energy efficiency. He also wrote an interesting book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/12742309-reinventing-fire">Reinventing Fire</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quotes">Quotes</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Eat breakfast like a king, lunch like a prince, and dinner like a pauper.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Breakfast is for you, lunch to be shared and dinner gifted.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Fasting is the best cure, our doctor inside- Filippo Paracelso</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Meditation must start with the body. The body is the vehicle of himself, you need to control it in order to really meditate - Iyengar</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>A life without research is a life wasted</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Sky roads can be seen without looking out the windows</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Only in finite is expressed infinite and in time the eternal.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Watch your thoughts, they become words; watch your words, they become actions; watch your actions, they become habits; watch your habits, they become character; watch your character, for it becomes your destiny. - Frank Outlaw</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>Happiness is also a way of interpreting the world, since while it may be difficult to change the world, it is always possible to change the way we look at it. - Matthieu Ricard</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>If something make you angry, think about what is more important: that thing or your health? In a moment, if you are wise enough, angry vanished. - Cao Tingdong</p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>In cultivating body, mind and spirit it is necessary to keep in mind: be friendly, loyal and with broadminded. Not too much happy for praises nor too much angry for blames.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.lagrandevia.it/la-grande-via/">La grande via</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52036.Siddhartha">Siddharta</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/67896.Tao_Te_Ching">Tao te chin - Lao Tzu</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2340397.The_Philosophy_of_Spinoza">The philosophy of spinoza - Ratner J</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Longevity-Life-Preservation-Chinese-MING/dp/753772606X">Gong Ting Xian - Longevità e preservazione della vita</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun_Simiao">Sun Simiao</a></li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-05-29-grandevia.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Predictably Irrational</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-04-14-predictably-irrational.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#predictably-irrational-the-hidden-forces-that-shape-our-decisions-ariely-dan">Predictably Irrational: The Hidden Forces that Shape Our Decisions (Ariely, Dan)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1255573980l/1713426.jpg" />

</div>
<h3 id="predictably-irrational-the-hidden-forces-that-shape-our-decisions-ariely-dan">Predictably Irrational: The Hidden Forces that Shape Our Decisions (Ariely, Dan)</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>creating an expensive dish, a restaurateur can lure customers into ordering the second most expensive choice (which can be cleverly engineered to deliver a higher profit margin</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we are always looking at the things around us in relation to others.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we not only tend to compare things with one another but also tend to focus on comparing things that are easily comparable—and avoid comparing things that cannot be compared easily.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we are wired to compare.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That’s a lesson we can all learn: the more we have, the more we want. And the only cure is to break the cycle of relativity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>decoy effect</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Tom had discovered a great law of human action, namely, that in order to make a man covet a thing, it is only necessary to make the thing difficult to attain.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That our first decisions resonate over a long sequence of decisions. First impressions are important,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We call this type of behavior herding. It happens when we assume that something is good (or bad) on the basis of other people’s previous behavior, and our own actions follow suit.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You might begin by questioning that habit. How did it begin? Second, ask yourself what amount of pleasure you will be getting out of it. Is the pleasure as much as you thought you would get? Could you cut back a little and better spend the remaining money on something else? With everything you do, in fact, you should train yourself to question your repeated behaviors.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We should also pay particular attention to the first decision we make in what is going to be a long stream of decisions (about clothing, food, etc.). When we face such a decision, it might seem to us that this is just one decision, without large consequences; but in fact the power of the first decision can have such a long-lasting effect that it will percolate into our future decisions for years to come. Given this effect, the first decision is crucial, and we should give it an appropriate amount of attention.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>what consumers are willing to pay can easily be manipulated, and this means that consumers don’t in fact have a good handle on their own preferences and the prices they are willing to pay for different goods and experiences.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the sensitivity we show to price changes might in fact be largely a result of our memory for the prices we have paid in the past and our desire for coherence with our past decisions—not at all a reflection of our true preferences or our level of demand.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>humans are intrinsically afraid of loss. The real allure of FREE! is tied to this fear. There’s no visible possibility of loss when we choose a FREE! item (it’s free). But suppose we choose the item that’s not free. Uh-oh, now there’s a risk of having made a poor decision—the possibility of a loss. And so, given the choice, we go for what is free.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Zero is not just another discount. Zero is a different place. The difference between two cents and one cent is small. But the difference between one cent and zero is huge! If you are in business, and understand that, you can do some marvelous things. Want to draw a crowd? Make something FREE! Want to sell more</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>products? Make part of the purchase FREE!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There are many examples to show that people will work more for a cause than for cash.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The conclusion: no one is offended by a small gift, because even small gifts keep us in the social exchange world and away from market norms.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>for heaven’s sake don’t mention the price of the selections.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>SO WE LIVE in two worlds: one characterized by social exchanges and the other characterized by market exchanges. And we apply different norms to these two kinds of relationships. Moreover, introducing market norms into social exchanges, as we have seen, violates the social norms and hurts the relationships. Once this type of mistake has been committed, recovering a social relationship is difficult.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There are social rewards that strongly motivate behavior—and one of the least used in corporate life is the encouragement of social rewards and reputation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>to be flexible, concerned, and willing to pitch in. That’s what a social relationship delivers.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But money has also taken on a life of its own. As we have seen, it can remove the best in human interactions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We should probably first rethink school curricula, and link them in more obvious ways to social goals (elimination of poverty and crime, elevation of human rights, etc.), technological goals (boosting energy conservation, space exploration, nanotechnology, etc.), and medical goals (cures for cancer, diabetes, obesity, etc.) that we care about as a society.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>MONEY, AS IT turns out, is very often the most expensive way to motivate people. Social norms are not only cheaper, but often more effective as well.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Money is not accepted at Burning Man. Rather, the whole place works as a gift exchange economy—you give things to other people, with the understanding that they will give something back to you (or to someone else) at some point in the future</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>life with fewer market norms and more social norms would be more satisfying, creative, fulfilling, and fun.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Even so, we all systematically underpredict the degree to which arousal completely negates our superego, and the way emotions can take control of our behavior.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>LOOKING FROM ONE emotional state to another is difficult. It’s not always possible; and as Sumi learned it can be painful. But to make informed decisions we need to somehow experience and understand the emotional state we will be in at the other side of the experience. Learning how to bridge this gap is essential to making some of the important decisions of our lives.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>that tightly restricting their freedom (equally spaced deadlines, imposed from above) is the best cure for procrastination</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>simply offering the students a tool by which they could precommit to deadlines helped them achieve better grades.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Because without precommitments, we keep on falling for temptation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the best course might be to give people an opportunity to commit up front to their preferred path of action. This approach might not be as effective as the dictatorial treatment, but it can help push us in the right direction (perhaps even more so if we train people to do it, and give them experience in setting their own deadlines). What’s the bottom line? We have problems with self-control, related to immediate and delayed gratification—no doubt there. But each of the problems we face has potential self-control mechanisms, as well. If we can’t save from our paycheck, we can take advantage of our employer’s automatic deduction option; if we don’t have the will to exercise regularly alone, we can make an appointment to exercise in the company of our friends. These are the tools that we can commit to in advance, and they may help us be the kind of people we want to be.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>simplification is one mark of real genius.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>OWNERSHIP PERVADES OUR lives and, in a strange way, shapes many of the things we do. Adam Smith wrote, “Every man [and woman] … lives by exchanging, or becomes in some measure a merchant, and the society itself grows to be what is properly a commercial society.” That’s an awesome thought. Much of our life story can be told by describing the ebb and flow of our particular possessions—what we get and what we give up. We buy clothes and food, automobiles and homes, for instance. And we sell things as well—homes and cars, and in the course of our careers, our time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first quirk, as we saw in the case of the basketball tickets, is that we fall in love with what we already have.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The second quirk is that we focus on what we may lose, rather than what we may gain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our aversion to loss is a strong emotion, and as I will explain later in the book, one that sometimes causes us to make bad decisions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The third quirk is that we assume other people will see the transaction from the same perspective as we do.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Another peculiarity is that we can begin to feel ownership even before we own something.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>OWNERSHIP IS NOT limited to material things. It can also apply to points of view.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My own approach is to try to view all transactions (particularly large ones) as if I were a nonowner, putting some distance between myself and the item of interest. In this attempt, I’m not certain if I have achieved the uninterest in material things that is espoused by the Hindu sannyasi, but at least I try to be as Zen as I can about it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The truth is that they could have made more money by picking a room—any room—and merely staying there for the whole experiment! (Think about that in terms of your life or career.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Erich Fromm wrote a book called Escape from Freedom. In a modern democracy, he said, people are beset not by a lack of opportunity, but by a dizzying abundance of it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We may work more hours at our jobs, for instance, without realizing that the childhood of our sons and daughters is slipping away. Sometimes these doors close too slowly for us to see them vanishing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What we need is to consciously start closing some of our doors. Small doors, of course, are rather easy to close. We can easily strike names off our holiday card lists or omit the tae kwon do from our daughter’s string of activities.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We have an irrational compulsion to keep doors open. It’s just the way we’re wired. But that doesn’t mean we shouldn’t try to close them.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>focusing on the similarities and minor differences between two things was to take into account the consequences of not deciding.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>WHEN WE BELIEVE beforehand that something will be good, therefore, it generally will be good—and when we think it will be bad, it will bad.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If we acknowledge that we are trapped within our perspective, which partially blinds us to the truth, we may be able to accept the idea that conflicts generally require a neutral third party—who has not been tainted with our expectations—to set down the rules and regulations. Of course, accepting the word of a third party is not easy and not always possible; but when it is possible, it can yield substantial benefits. And for that reason alone, we must continue to try. Di’ tutte queste cose agli altri, ma in modo da udire anche tu, nel dirle; scrivile, ma per leggerle mentre le scrivi; e rivolgi ogni tuo impegno a migliorare i costumi e a placare il furore delle passioni. Sia tua cura non di saper di più, ma di sapere meglio.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>GENERAL, TWO mechanisms shape the expectations that make placebos work. One is belief—our confidence or faith in the drug, the procedure, or the caregiver. Sometimes just the fact that a doctor or nurse is paying attention to us and reassuring us not only makes us feel better but also triggers our internal healing processes. Even a doctor’s enthusiasm for a particular treatment or procedure may predispose us toward a positive outcome. The second mechanism is conditioning. Like Pavlov’s famous dogs (that learned to salivate at the ring of a bell), the body builds up expectancy after repeated experiences and releases various chemicals to prepare us for the future.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>there is nothing “just” about the power of a placebo, and in reality it represents the amazing way our mind controls our body. How the mind achieves these amazing outcomes is not always very clear. Some of the effect, to be sure, has to do with reducing the level of stress, changing hormonal secretions, changing the immune system, etc. The more we understand the connection between brain and body, the more things that once seemed clear-cut become ambiguous. Nowhere is this as apparent as with the placebo.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Behavioral economists, on the other hand, believe that people are susceptible to irrelevant influences from their immediate environment (which we call context effects), irrelevant emotions, shortsightedness, and other forms of irrationality</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>why not develop new strategies, tools, and methods to help us make better decisions and improve our overall well-being? That’s exactly the meaning of free lunches from the perspective of behavioral economics—the idea that there are tools, methods, and policies that can help all of us make better decisions and as a consequence achieve what we desire.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>fact, research in behavioral economics points to many possible reasons why people are not saving enough for retirement. People procrastinate. People have a hard time understanding the real cost of not saving as well as the benefits of saving.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>IF I WERE to distill one main lesson from the research described in this book, it is that we are pawns in a game whose forces we largely fail to comprehend. We usually think of ourselves as sitting in the driver’s seat, with ultimate control over the decisions we make and the direction our life takes; but, alas, this perception has more to do with our desires—with how we want to view ourselves—than with reality.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2017-04-14-predictably-irrational.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Leisure - The Basis of Culture</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-11-01-leisure.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#leisure-the-basis-of-culture-pieper-joseph">Leisure: The Basis of Culture (Pieper, Joseph)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1389227160l/767958.jpg" />

</div>
<h2 id="leisure-the-basis-of-culture-pieper-joseph">Leisure: The Basis of Culture (Pieper, Joseph)</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>We shall see each other again.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Ratio is the power of discursive, logical thought, of searching and of examination, of abstraction, of definition and drawing conclusions. Intellectus, on the other hand, is the name for the understanding in so far as it is the capacity of simplex intuitus, of that simple vision to which truth offers itself like a landscape to the eye.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The tendency to overvalue hard work and the effort of doing something difficult is so deep-rooted that it even infects our notion of love. Why should it be that the average Christian regards loving one’s enemy as the most exalted form of love? Principally because it offers an example of a natural bent heroically curbed; the exceptional difficulty, the impossibility one might almost say, of loving one’s enemy constitutes the greatness of the love. And what does Aquinas say? “It is not the difficulty of loving one’s enemy that matters when the essence of the merit of doing so is concerned, excepting in so far as the perfection of love wipes out the difficulty. And therefore, if love were to be so perfect that the difficulty vanished altogether—it would be more meritorious still.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>And in the same way, the essence of knowledge does not consist in the effort for which it calls, but in grasping existing things and in unveiling reality. Moreover, just as the highest form of virtue knows nothing of “difficulty”, so too the highest form of knowledge comes to man like a gift—the sudden illumination, a stroke of genius, true contemplation; it comes effortlessly and without trouble. On one occasion St. Thomas speaks of contemplation and play in the same breath: “because of the leisure that goes with contemplation” the divine wisdom itself, Holy Scripture says, is “always at play, playing through the whole world”(</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>man seems to mistrust everything that is effortless; he can only enjoy, with a good conscience, what he has acquired with toil and trouble; he refuses to have anything as a gift.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The liberal arts, then, include all forms of human activity which are an end in themselves; the servile arts are those which have an end beyond themselves, and more precisely an end which consists in a utilitarian result attainable in practice, a practicable result.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Education concerns the whole man; an educated man is a man with a point of view from which he takes in the whole world.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Aquinas writes, “that there should be men who devote their lives to contemplation”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Compared with the exclusive ideal of work as activity, leisure implies (in the first place) an attitude of non-activity, of inward calm, of silence; it means not being “busy”, but letting things happen.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Silence, as it is used in this context, does not mean “dumbness” or “noiselessness”; it means more nearly that the soul’s power to “answer” to the reality of the world is left undisturbed. For leisure is a receptive attitude of mind, a contemplative attitude, and it is not only the occasion but also the capacity for steeping oneself in the whole of creation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Furthermore, there is also a certain serenity in leisure. That serenity springs precisely from our inability to understand, from our recognition of the mysterious nature of the universe; it springs from the courage of deep confidence, so that we are content to let things take their course; and there is something about it which Konrad Weiss, the poet, called “confidence in the fragmentariness of life and history.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>leisure appears (secondly) in its character as an attitude of contemplative “celebration”,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Leisure is possible only on the premise that man consents to his own true nature and abides in concord with the meaning of the universe</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Leisure draws its vitality from affirmation. It is not the same as non-activity, nor is it identical with tranquility; it is not even the same as inward tranquility. Rather, it is like the tranquil silence of lovers, which draws its strength from concord.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>A break in one’s work, whether of an hour, a day or a week, is still part of the world of work. It is a link in the chain of utilitarian functions. The pause is made for the sake of work and in order to work, and a man is not only refreshed from work but for work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The soul of leisure, it can be said, lies in “celebration”.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>its ultimate justification derive from its roots in divine worship.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Temple” means (as may be seen from the original sense of the word): that a particular piece of ground is specially reserved, and marked off from the remainder of the land which is used either for agriculture or for habitation. And this plot of land is transferred to the estate of the gods, it is neither lived on, nor cultivated. And similarly in divine worship a certain definite space of time is set aside from working hours and days, a limited time, specially marked off—and like the space allotted to the temple, is not used, is withdrawn from all merely utilitarian ends. Every seventh day is such a period of time. It is the “festival time”, and it arises in this way and no other.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is in fact no room in the world of “total labor” either for divine worship, or for a feast: because the “worker’s” world, the world of “labor” rests solely upon the principle of rational utilization.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>sacrifice mean? It means a voluntary offering freely given. It definitely does not involve utility; it is in fact absolutely antithetic to utility. Thus, the act of worship creates a store of real wealth that cannot be consumed by the workaday world.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The vacancy left by absence of worship is filled by mere killing of time and by boredom, which is directly related to inability to enjoy leisure; for one can only be bored if the spiritual power to be leisurely has been lost.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The opening question, What does philosophizing mean? is certainly philosophical.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But like all philosophical questions, it cannot be answered with complete finality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>because you think you are doing something when you are really doing nothing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>serves no purpose whatsoever beyond itself and its own end or that it can never be used apart from its own end. Philosophy is not functional knowledge but, as Newman said, “the knowledge of a gentleman”;9 not a useful knowledge, but a “free” knowledge. Freedom, here, means that philosophical knowledge is not legitimized by its usefulness or usableness, or by virtue of its social function, or with reference to the “common need”. This is the selfsame sense in which “freedom” was used in the phrase “artes liberales”, the liberal arts—in contradistinction to the “artes serviles”, the servile arts which, as Aquinas says, are “ordered to the satisfaction of a need through activity.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“freedom” being understood to mean “not being at the disposal of external aims and ends”. The different branches of science are “free” in this sense, provided only that they are pursued philosophically and in so far as they share the freedom of philosophy. “Knowledge is free”, writes Newman, “in the truest sense, as soon as and in so far as it is philosophical.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whenever we look at being philosophically, we discourse purely “theoretically” about it, in a manner, that is to say, untouched in any way whatsoever by practical considerations, by the desire to change it; and it is in this sense that philosophy is said to be above any and every “purpose”.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>transcends the world of work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“What do they not see, who see him who sees all things?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Aqhinas = San Tommaso d’Aquino, citazione presa da ‘commento alle sentenze di Pietro Lombardo’ o ‘Somma Teologica’</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That, then, is the first point: the world is a field of relations. To have a world is to be the center, the coordinator, of a field of relations. The second point is: the higher the order of a being, the more embracing and wider its power of establishing relations—the greater the field of relations within its power. This may also be expressed by saying that the higher a being stands in the order of reality, in the hierarchic order of being, the wider and deeper its world.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>And “surroundings”, even “surroundings” which could “in themselves” be apprehended, do not yet constitute a “world”. Though this view was far from generally held until Jacob von Uexküll, the</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>That would explain why so many insects feign death. If their motionless form simply does not exist in the field of vision of their enemies, then by shamming death they drop out of that world with absolute certainty and cannot be found even though searched for.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>human world “cannot claim to be any more real than the animal’s world”;4 man, then, is limited by his environment in exactly the same way as an animal, that is to say, he is limited to a selected environment assembled, as it were, by natural selection and biological necessity; he is incapable of apprehending anything and, even though searching for it, of finding anything outside his environment—like the crow that cannot find a motionless grasshopper. (The question does arise, however, as to how a creature limited to its own environment and imprisoned so effectively within it could study the theory of environment.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>anima est quodammodo omnia, the soul is in a certain sense all things, the all.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To the philosophers of the past—to Plato, Aristotle, Augustine, and Thomas Aquinas—the concepts of “spirit” and “world” (in the sense of the whole of reality) are not only interrelated; their correspondence is complete. These philosophers not only held that “spirit is relatedness to the totality of existing things”, but also that all existing things are essentially related to spirit. Moreover, they formulated that relation in such precise terms that at first we scarcely dare to take them at their word. Not only, they said, is it of the nature of the spirit for its frame of reference to be the totality of existing things; but it is also of the nature of existing things for them to lie within spirit’s frame of reference. Furthermore, in the philosophical tradition of which I am speaking, it comes to the same thing whether I say, “Things have being” or whether I say, “Things exist in the spirit’s frame of reference.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the world of a spiritual being is the totality of existing things; and their correspondence is so complete that it is both essential to spirit (spirit is the power of embracing the totality of being) and equally it is essential to things themselves (“to be” means “to be in relation to spirit”).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>that the greater the capacity for relations the greater the dimensions of the coordinated field, until that field becomes (for spirit) “the” world.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the same time it is one of the characteristics of man, a corporeal and spiritual being, that it should be his spiritual soul which informs the physical and sensitive realms—to such a degree that taking food in man and animal are two utterly different things (quite apart from the fact that in the human sphere a “meal” may have a spiritual or even a religious character). It is so true that the spiritual soul informs the whole of man’s nature that even when a man “vegetates” it is ultimately only possible because he is spiritual—a cabbage can’t vegetate. Equally, when man shuts himself up in his environment, in the sphere defined and limited by his immediate needs, the degeneration that follows is only possible because spiritual degeneration is possible. The really human thing is to see the stars above the roof, to preserve our apprehension of the universality of things in the midst of the habits of daily life, and to see “the world” above and beyond our immediate environment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Socrates and says that the teacher only induces the learner to remember “and to win knowledge from out of himself”; “there is no such thing as learning, one only remembers once again.”14 Yet another man comes along maintaining that we are all faced by or face the same reality: the teacher only points it out, the learner, the hearer, then sees it for himself.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The distinctive mark of a philosophical question is, then, that it brings out what constitutes the essence of spirit: convenire cum omni ente, in harmony with everything that is. One cannot ask a philosophical question or think philosophically without bringing the whole of being into play, the totality of existing things, “God and the world”.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>to philosophize means to step beyond the sectional, partial environment of the workaday world into a position vis-à-vis de l’univers: a step that takes one into the open, for the heavens are not a roof over a man’s head—though one ought always to leave the door open behind one, for a man cannot live like that continuously.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To philosophize means to withdraw—not from the things of everyday life—but from the currently accepted meaning attached to them, or to question the value placed upon them. This does not, of course, take place by virtue of some decision to differentiate our attitude from that of others and to see things “differently”, but because, quite suddenly, things themselves assume a different aspect.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the beginning of philosophy is wonder.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Theoria” is only possible in so far as man is not blind to the wonderful fact that things are. For our sense of wonder, in the philosophical meaning of the word, is not aroused by enormous, sensational things—though that is what a dulled sensibility requires to provoke it to a sort of ersatz experience of wonder. A man who needs the unusual to make him “wonder” shows that he has lost the capacity to find the true answer to the wonder of being.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>doubt is the beginning of philosophy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The innermost meaning of wonder is fulfilled in a deepened sense of mystery. It does not end in doubt, but is the awakening of the knowledge that being, qua being, is mysterious and inconceivable, and that it is a mystery in the full sense of the word: neither a dead end, nor a contradiction, nor even something impenetrable and dark. Rather, mystery means that a reality cannot be comprehended because its light is ever-flowing, unfathomable, and inexhaustible. And that is what the wonderer really experiences.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the Summa Theologica 7 wonder is defined as the desiderium sciendi, the longing for knowledge, an active desire for knowledge. Although to wonder means, as we have said, not to know, it does not mean that we are, in a kind of despair, resigned to ignorance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“the really damaging thing about stupidity is its self-satisfaction.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>to wonder, to philosophize, means to hope!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Philosophy never claimed to be a superior form of knowledge but, on the contrary, a form of humility, and restrained, and conscious of this restraint and humility in relation to knowledge. The words philosopher and philosophy were coined, according to legend—and the legend is of great antiquity—by Pythagoras in explicit contrast to the words sophia and sophos: no man is wise, and no man “knows”;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>is because of the ambivalent structure of philosophy, because “marveling” sets one on a road that never ends, because the structure of philosophy is that of hope, that to philosophize is so essentially human—and in a sense to philosophize means living a truly human life.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-11-01-leisure.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Peace Is Every Step</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-09-13-peace-every-step.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#peace-is-every-step-the-path-of-mindfulness-in-everyday-life-hanh-thich-nhat">Peace Is Every Step: The Path of Mindfulness in Everyday Life (Hanh, Thich Nhat)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1320544155l/14572.jpg" />

</div>
<h2 id="peace-is-every-step-the-path-of-mindfulness-in-everyday-life-hanh-thich-nhat">Peace Is Every Step: The Path of Mindfulness in Everyday Life (Hanh, Thich Nhat)</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Every time you do an activity, or have a thought, you are changing a piece of yourself into something slightly different than it was before. Every hour you spend with others, you become more like the people around you. Gradually, you become a different person. If there is a large gap between your daily conduct and your core commitment, you will become more like your daily activities and less attached to your original commitment.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if we can only quiet our distracted thinking long enough to come back to the present moment and notice the blue sky, the child’s smile, the beautiful sunrise. “If we are peaceful, if we are happy, we can smile, and everyone in our family, our entire society, will benefit from our peace.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are very good at preparing to live, but not very good at living.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>mind and body are not unified. By concentrating on our breathing, “In” and “Out,” we bring body and mind back together, and become whole again. Conscious breathing is an important bridge.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are what we feel and perceive. If we are angry, we are the anger. If we are in love, we are love. If we look at a snow-covered mountain peak, we are the mountain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Whether we are in the city, the countryside, or the wilderness, we need to sustain ourselves by choosing our surroundings carefully and nourishing our awareness in each moment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We need to practice meditation gently, but steadily, throughout daily life, not wasting a single opportunity or event to see deeply into the true nature of life, including our everyday problems. Practicing in this way, we dwell in profound communion with life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We have to learn to really enjoy our church bells and our school bells. Bells are beautiful, and they can wake us up.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Everything is still there, and if you really want it, you can find it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Eating mindfully is a most important practice of meditation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You become a bodhisattva, helping a living being become enlightened. Children, in particular, are very capable of practicing mindfulness and reminding others to do the same.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mindfulness can penetrate the activities of everyday life, each minute, each hour of our daily life, and not just be a description of something far away.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>By taking good care of the present moment, we take good care of the future. Working for peace in the future is to work for peace in the present moment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>has become a kind of habit to look at things with the intention of getting something. We call it “pragmatism,” and we say that the truth is something that pays. If we meditate in order to get to the truth, it seems we will be well paid. In meditation, we stop, and we look deeply. We stop just to be there, to be with ourselves and with the world. When we are capable of stopping, we begin to see and, if we can see, we understand. Peace and happiness are the fruit of this process.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we just act in each moment with composure and mindfulness, each minute of our life is a work of art. Even when we are not painting or writing, we are still creating. We are pregnant with beauty, joy, and peace, and we are making life more beautiful for many people. Sometimes it is better not to talk about art by using the word “art.” If we just act with awareness and integrity, our art will flower, and we don’t have to talk about it at all. When we know how to be peace, we find that art is a wonderful way to share our peacefulness. Artistic expression will take place in one way or another, but the being is essential. So we must go back to ourselves, and when we have joy and peace in ourselves, our creations of art will be quite natural, and they will serve the world in a positive way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When I think deeply about the nature of hope, I see something tragic. Since we cling to our hope in the future, we do not focus our energies and capabilities on the present moment. We use hope to believe something better will happen in the future, that we will arrive at peace, or the Kingdom of God. Hope becomes a kind of obstacle. If you can refrain from hoping, you can bring yourself entirely into the present moment and discover the joy that is already here.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I do not mean that you should not have hope, but that hope is not enough. Hope can create an obstacle for you, and if you dwell in the energy of hope, you will not bring yourself back entirely into the present moment. If you re-channel those energies into being aware of what is going on in the present moment, you will be able to make a breakthrough and discover joy and peace right in the present moment, inside of yourself and all around you.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When someone holds up a flower and shows it to you, he wants you to see it. If you keep thinking, you miss the flower. The person who was not thinking, who was just himself, was able to encounter the flower in depth, and he smiled. That is the problem of life. If we are not fully ourselves, truly in the present moment, we miss everything</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mindful observation is based on the principle of “non-duality”: our feeling is not separate from us or caused merely by something outside us; our feeling is us, and for the moment we are that feeling. We are neither drowned in nor terrorized by the feeling, nor do we reject it. Our attitude of not clinging to or rejecting our feelings is the attitude of letting go, an important part of meditation practice. If we face our unpleasant feelings with care, affection, and nonviolence, we can transform them into the kind of energy that is healthy and has the capacity to nourish us. By the work of mindful observation, our unpleasant feelings can illuminate so much for us, offering us insight and understanding into ourselves and society.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Instead of acting as if we can dispose of parts of ourselves, we should learn the art of transformation.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we become angry at our anger, we will have two angers at the same time. We only have to observe it with love and attention. If we take care of our anger in this way, without trying to run away from it, it will transform itself.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first step in dealing with feelings is to recognize each feeling as it arises.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You calm your feeling just by being with it, like a mother tenderly holding her crying baby.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The second step is to become one with the feeling.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The third step is to calm the feeling.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The fourth step is to release the feeling, to let it go.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The fifth step is to look deeply.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you will know what to do and what not to do to transform the feeling and be free.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>After recognizing the feeling, becoming one with it, calming it down, and releasing it, we can look deeply into its causes, which are often based on inaccurate perceptions. As soon as we understand the causes and nature of our feelings, they begin to transform themselves</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is best if we do not listen to or look at the person whom we consider to be the cause of our anger.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We need the insight and non-dual vision of the organic gardener with regard to our anger. We need not be afraid of it or reject it. We know that anger can be a kind of compost, and that it is within its power to give birth to something beautiful. We need anger in the way the organic gardener needs compost. If we know how to accept our anger, we already have some peace and joy. Gradually we can transform anger completely into peace, love, and understanding.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>our anger will subside and we will feel stronger. Then we can begin to observe the anger directly and try to understand it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Thanks to the illuminating light of awareness, after practicing mindful observation for a while, we begin to see the primary causes of our anger. Meditation helps us look deeply into things in order to see their nature. If we look into our anger, we can see its roots, such as misunderstanding, clumsiness, injustice, resentment, or conditioning. These roots can be present in ourselves and in the person who played the principal role in precipitating our anger. We observe mindfully in order to be able to see and to understand. Seeing and understanding are the elements of liberation that bring about love and compassion. The method of mindful observation in order to see and understand the roots of the anger is a method that has lasting effectiveness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The absence of clear understanding is the basis for every knot.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>There is a term in Buddhist psychology that can be translated as “internal formations,” “fetters,” or “knots.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Internal formations need our full attention as soon as they manifest, while they are still weak, so that the work of transformation is easy. If we do not untie our knots when they form, they will grow tighter and stronger.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In psychology, this is called resistance. We are afraid to bring into our conscious mind the feelings of pain that are buried in us, because they will make us suffer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>they are not considered in relation to our real problems, our meditation is not really very valuable or helpful. If we know how to live every moment in an awakened way, we will be aware of what is going on in our feelings and perceptions in the present moment, and we will not let knots form or become tighter in our consciousness. And if we know how to observe our feelings, we can find the roots of long-standing internal formations and transform them, even those that have become quite strong.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“suchness” is used to mean “the essence or particular characteristics of a thing or a person, its true nature.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We do not expect a person always to be a flower. We have to understand his or her garbage as well.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>realized that if I didn’t do something about the anger in me, I would transmit it to my children.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>three components: the giver, the gift, and the one who receives the gift. The giver is our parents; we are the continuation of our parents and our ancestors. The gift is our body itself. The one who receives the gift is us. As we continue to meditate on this, we see clearly that the giver, the gift, and the receiver are one. All three are present in our body. When we are deeply in touch with the present moment, we can see that all our ancestors and all future generations are present in us. Seeing this, we will know what to do and what not to do—for ourselves, our ancestors, our children, and their children.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Consciousness exists on two levels: as seeds and as manifestations of these seeds.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Each of us needs a reserve of seeds that are beautiful, healthy, and strong enough to help us during difficult moments.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Awareness of the precious elements of happiness is itself the practice of right mindfulness. Elements like these are within us and all around us. In each second of our lives we can enjoy them. If we do so, seeds of peace, joy, and happiness will be planted in us, and they will become strong. The secret to happiness is happiness itself. Wherever we are, any time, we have the capacity to enjoy the sunshine, the presence of each other, the wonder of our breathing. We don’t have to travel anywhere else to do so. We can be in touch with these things right now.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Blaming has no positive effect at all, nor does trying to persuade using reason and arguments. That is my experience. No blame, no reasoning, no argument, just understanding. If you understand, and you show that you understand, you can love, and the situation will change.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when you love, you naturally act in a way that can relieve the suffering of people.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we know only our own needs and ignore the needs of the other person, we cannot love. We must look deeply in order to see and understand the needs, aspirations, and suffering of the person we love. This is the ground of real love. You cannot resist loving another person when you really understand him or her.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>True love needs understanding.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Compassion means, literally, “to suffer with.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To look deeply is to understand. Once we understand the reasons he has acted badly, our bitterness towards him will vanish, and we will long for him to suffer less. We will feel cool and light, and we can smile. We do not need the other person to be present in order to bring about reconciliation. When we look deeply, we become reconciled with ourselves, and, for us, the problem no longer exists.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We can get in touch with the refreshing, healing elements within and around us thanks to the loving support of other people. If we have a good community of friends, we are very fortunate. To create a good community, we first have to transform ourselves into a good element of the community. After that, we can go to another person and help him or her become an element of the community. We build our network of friends that way. We have to think of friends and community as investments, as our most important asset. They can comfort us and help us in difficult times, and they can share our joy and happiness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mindfulness must be engaged. Once there is seeing, there must be acting. Otherwise, what is the use of seeing?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Wealth is made of non-wealth elements, and poverty is made by non-poverty elements. It is exactly the same as with the sheet of paper. So we must be careful not to imprison ourselves in concepts. The truth is that everything contains everything else. We cannot just be, we can only inter-be. We are responsible for everything that happens around us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Real strength is not in power, money, or weapons, but in deep, inner peace.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>If you are a mountain climber or someone who enjoys the countryside, or the green forest, you know that the forests are our lungs outside of our bodies, just as the sun is our heart outside of our bodies. Yet we have been acting in a way that has allowed two million square miles of forest land to be destroyed by acid rain, and we have destroyed parts of the ozone layer that regulate how much direct sunlight we receive. We are imprisoned in our small selves, thinking only of the comfortable conditions for this small self, while we destroy our large self. We should be able to be our true self. That means we should be able to be the river, we should be able to be the forest, the sun, and the ozone layer. We must do this to understand and to have hope for the future.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Awareness of this fact alone can help us overcome many of our own psychological pains. Eventually our contemplations can help us see how to assist those who need our help so much.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We need harmony, we need peace. Peace is based on respect for life, the spirit of reverence for life. Not only do we have to respect the lives of human beings, but we have to respect the lives of animals, vegetables, and minerals. Rocks can be alive. A rock can be destroyed. The Earth also. The destruction of our health by pollution of the air and water is linked to the destruction of the minerals. The way we farm, the way we deal with our garbage, all these things are related to each other.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We cannot just blame one side or the other. We have to transcend the tendency to take sides.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I asked the leaf whether it was frightened because it was autumn and the other leaves were falling. The leaf told me, “No. During the whole spring and summer I was completely alive. I worked hard to help nourish the tree, and now much of me is in the tree. I am not limited by this form. I am also the whole tree, and when I go back to the soil, I will continue to nourish the tree. So I don’t worry at all. As I leave this branch and float to the ground, I will wave to the tree and tell her, ‘I will see you again very soon.’”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What we need are people who are capable of loving, of not taking sides so that they can embrace the whole of reality.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I asked the question, how could people live like this when things are like that? But if you stay in Paris for ten years without being in touch, you find it normal. Meditation is a point of contact. Sometimes you do not have to go to the place of suffering. You just sit quietly on your cushion, and you can see everything. You can actualize everything, and you can be aware of what is going on in the world. Out of that kind of awareness, compassion and understanding arise naturally, and you can stay right in your own country and perform social action.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All systems of thought are guiding means; they are not absolute truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Avoid being narrow-minded and bound to present views. Learn and practice non-attachment from views in order to be open to receive others’ viewpoints. Truth is found in life and not merely in conceptual knowledge. Be ready to learn throughout your entire life and to observe reality in yourself and in the world at all times.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As soon as anger or hatred arises, turn your attention to your breathing in order to see and understand the nature of your anger or hatred and the nature of the persons who have caused your anger or hatred.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>9 Do not say untruthful things for the sake of personal interest or to impress people. Do not utter words that cause division and hatred. Do not spread news that you do not know to be certain. Do not criticize or condemn things that you are not sure of. Always speak truthfully and constructively. Have the courage to speak out about situations of injustice, even when doing so may threaten your own safety.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>14 Do not mistreat your body. Learn to handle it with respect. Do not look on your body as only an instrument. Preserve vital energies for the realization of the Way. Sexual expression should not happen without love and commitment. In sexual relationships, be aware of future suffering that may be caused. To preserve the happiness of others, respect the rights and commitments of others. Be fully aware of the responsibility of bringing new lives into the world. Meditate on the world into which you are bringing new beings.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The next morning when the sun was in the sky, she discovered something beautiful. She saw the blue sky for the first time. She had never noticed it before. She had only been interested in clouds, and she had missed seeing the sky, which is the home of all the clouds. Clouds are impermanent, but the sky is stable. She realized that the immense sky had been within her heart since the very beginning. This great insight brought her peace and happiness. As she saw the vast wonderful blue sky, she knew that her peace and stability would never be lost again.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Take the hand of your child and invite her to go out and sit with you on the grass. The two of you may want to contemplate the green grass, the little flowers that grow among the grasses, and the sky. Breathing and smiling together—that is peace education. If we know how to appreciate these beautiful things, we will not have to search for anything else. Peace is available in every moment, in every breath, in every step.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-09-13-peace-every-step.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Brain Maker, The Power of Gut Microbes to Heal and Protect Your Brain</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-01-25-brain-maker.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#brain-maker-the-power-of-gut-microbes-to-heal-and-protect-your-brain---for-life-perlmutter-david">Brain Maker: The Power of Gut Microbes to Heal and Protect Your Brain - for Life (Perlmutter, David)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1415588147l/22875118.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="brain-maker-the-power-of-gut-microbes-to-heal-and-protect-your-brain---for-life-perlmutter-david">Brain Maker: The Power of Gut Microbes to Heal and Protect Your Brain - for Life (Perlmutter, David)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>“Let food be thy medicine and medicine be thy food.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Foods such as garlic, Jerusalem artichoke, jicama, and even dandelion greens, as well as fermented foods such as sauerkraut, kombucha, and kimchi open the door for heightened levels of health in general, and brain function and protection in particular</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The vagus nerve, the longest of the twelve cranial nerves, is the primary channel of information between the hundreds of millions of nerve cells in our intestinal nervous system and our central nervous system. Also known as cranial nerve X, it extends from the brain stem to the abdomen, directing many bodily processes that we don’t consciously control. These include such important tasks as maintaining the heart rate and controlling digestion. And it turns out that the population of bacteria in the gut directly affects the stimulation and function of the cells along the vagus nerve.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>How does the microbiome come into play? It regulates or manages the immune response. So it, in turn, takes part in the story of inflammation in your body.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The reason most of your immune system is deployed in your gut is simple: the intestinal wall is the border with the outside world. Aside from skin, it’s where your body has the most chances of encountering foreign material and organisms. And it is in constant communication with every other immune system cell in the body. If it meets a problematic substance in the gut, it alerts the rest of the immune system to be on guard.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Elevated blood sugar stirs up inflammation in the bloodstream, as excess sugar can be toxic if it’s not swept up and used by cells. It also triggers a reaction called glycation — the biological process by which sugar binds to proteins and certain fats, resulting in deformed molecules that don’t function well. These sugar proteins are technically called advanced glycation end products (AGEs). The body does not recognize AGEs as normal, so they set off inflammatory reactions. In the brain, sugar molecules and brain proteins combine to produce lethal new structures that contribute to the degeneration of the brain and its functioning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>These studies together support the crucial role of microbiota in maintaining the intestinal barrier integrity, sustaining a normal metabolic homeostasis, protecting the host from infection by pathogens, enhancing host defense systems and even influencing the nervous system in type-2 diabetes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Chinese herbal components berberine and ginseng, as well as the compounds found in tea, coffee, wine, and chocolate have anti-diabetic qualities through their effects on gut bacteria.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Dr. Fasano’s recent discovery that not only is there increased gut permeability when the gut is exposed to gliadin, a protein found in gluten, but in fact the blood-brain barrier also becomes more permeable in response to gliadin exposure.24</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>they can even produce various vitamins that are essential to brain health, including B12. It’s well substantiated that low levels of B12 are a huge risk factor for dementia, not to mention other neurological challenges such as depression.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>An important byproduct of the work done by mitochondria is the production of chemicals, related to oxygen, called reactive oxygen species (ROS). ROS are more commonly known as free radicals.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>MS patients almost always were either born by C-section, not breast-fed, or treated with antibiotics for some illness early in life.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the idea that people will take a pill to treat symptoms, while the underlying disorder is ignored. So there’s never any real focus on actually curing or even improving the root cause of the illness, let alone getting people off the medication.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>High blood sugar, in fact, is one of the biggest risk factors for depression, just as it is for Alzheimer’s.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>fructose has been shown to increase circulating LPS by 40 percent.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>LPS make the gut more permeable, but it can cross the blood-brain barrier and allow pro-inflammatory chemicals to bombard the brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>cocoa, coffee, and curcumin (turmeric), for example — can have the opposite effect of lowering the risk of depression by helping balance the microbiome.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>obesity during pregnancy harms the developing fetus’s stem cells, which are responsible for creating and sustaining lifelong blood and immune-system function.5</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes; between them, these two groups make up more than 90 percent of the gut’s population. The ratio of these two groups to each other determines levels of inflammation and squarely relates to such conditions as obesity, diabetes, coronary artery disease, and inflammation in general.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>higher levels of Firmicutes changes our genetic expression, noting that this paves the way for obesity, diabetes, cardiovascular disease, and inflammation. But, as they also revealed in their study, you can change this. Just increasing dietary fiber can improve the ratio.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Our cells can accept glucose only with the help of insulin, which acts like a transporter and is produced by the pancreas. Insulin shuttles glucose from the bloodstream into cells, where it can then be used as fuel. When a cell is normal and healthy, it has abundant receptors for insulin, so it has no problem responding to it. But when a cell is mercilessly exposed to high levels of insulin through a never-ending presence of glucose — caused by consuming too many carbohydrates and refined sugars — the cell does something brilliant to adapt: It reduces the number of insulin-responsive receptors on its surfaces. It’s as if the cell closes a few doors so it can’t hear insulin knocking. This ultimately causes the cell to become desensitized or “resistant” to insulin. Once a cell is insulin resistant, it’s unable to take glucose from the blood, leaving glucose in the bloodstream. As with most biological processes, there’s a “fail-safe” backup system in place. The body wants to fix this problem, as it knows it can’t have glucose loitering in the blood. So it tells the pancreas to increase production of insulin to mop up that glucose, which the pancreas dutifully does. It will continue to pump out as much insulin as needed to push glucose into cells. And higher levels of insulin are needed because the cells aren’t as responsive to insulin</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>relationship between high carbohydrate consumption and diabetes is almost indisputable.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This same outcome — a lack of satiety — is also seen with artificial sweeteners. Although we used to think that sugar substitutes like saccharin, sucralose, and aspartame didn’t have a metabolic impact because they don’t raise insulin, it turns out that they can indeed wreak tremendous metabolic havoc and cause the same metabolic disorders as real sugar.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Obviously, B. fragilis, or any other single probiotic for that matter, is not a guaranteed treatment. But I have no doubt that future therapies for autism will include probiotics, some of which might work wonders on some symptoms of autism in some patients. I also have a hunch that in the future, we’ll begin to view brain disorders like autism as mitochondrial diseases that have strong ties to the gut’s tribes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>best of all, these new therapies won’t be pharmaceutical drugs that come with side effects. They will, for the most part, come from dietary choices and probiotic treatments to rebalance the microbiome. They will be lifestyle interventions that are highly accessible and economical for everyone.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What’s empowering about this is that we can change our health’s destiny, as well as the destiny of our children’s health, if we make the right choices. Now that we have evidence to suggest that food, stress, exercise, sleep — and the state of our microbiome — affect which of our genes are activated and which remain suppressed, we can take some degree of control in all of these realms. To be sure, we may never be able to totally eradicate the possibility of autism or another brain disorder, but we can most certainly do our best to reduce the chances. And now that we know that the gut bacteria factor in somewhere, harnessing the microbiome for the benefit of the brain becomes key. What also becomes key is knowing how a good microbiome can go bad. Hence the purpose of part II.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Knowledge, after all, is power.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>it has the lowest GI of all the natural sugars because the liver metabolizes most of the fructose, so it has no immediate effect on our blood-sugar and insulin levels.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I call gluten a “silent germ” because it can inflict lasting damage without your knowing it. While its effects might start with unexplained headaches and feeling anxious, or “wired and tired,” they can worsen to more dire disorders such as depression and dementia.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Gluten is made up of two main groups of proteins, the glutenins and the gliadins.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>exposure to the gliadin protein in particular increases gut permeability in all of us.5 That’s right, all humans have some degree of gluten sensitivity. Once you have a leaky gut, you’re highly susceptible to other food sensitivities in the future. You’re also vulnerable to the impact of LPS making its way into the bloodstream. Lipopolysaccharide, or LPS as you’ll recall, is a structural component of many microbial cells in the gut. If LPS gets past those tight junctions, it increases systemic inflammation and irritates the immune system — a double strike that puts you at risk for myriad brain ailments, autoimmune disease, and cancer.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Although there’s a huge market now for gluten-free products, the bottom line is they are just that — products, and they can be just as junky and nutrient-poor as processed products that don’t come with a “gluten-free” claim. Many are made with refined, gluten-free grains that are low in fiber, vitamins, and other nutrients. That’s why it’s crucial to pay attention to ingredients and choose gluten-free foods that are authentic in their nutrition and wholesomeness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Based on studies of chlorine’s effects on human cells, the EPA sets the safe level in drinking water at no more than four parts per million. Even that dilution can wipe out lots of organisms, as anyone knows who has killed a goldfish using tap water. in chapter 9, I’ll offer ideas on how to avoid chlorinated water. It’s easier than you think, and you won’t have to call a plumber or invest in a water delivery service.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>changes in the array of gut bacteria can take place in as little as six days after instituting a new dietary protocol,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>coconut yogurt</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>coconut kefir,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kombucha tea.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Tempeh.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>great source of vitamin B12, tempeh</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kimchi.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sauerkraut.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Pickles.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Even setting aside the gluten factor, one of the main reasons that consuming too many grains and carbs is so harmful is that they spike blood sugar in ways other foods, such as meat, fish, poultry, and vegetables, do not.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This particular diet supplies the ingredients to nourish not only healthy biology (and thus a healthy microbiome) but also a healthy brain. A diet that keeps blood sugar balanced keeps gut bacteria balanced. A diet high in rich sources of fiber, which you’ll get from whole fruits and vegetables, feeds the good gut bacteria and produces the right balance of those short-chain fatty acids to keep the gut lining in check. A diet devoid of injurious gluten will further tip the scales in favor of healthy gut ecology as well as healthy brain physiology. And a diet that’s intrinsically anti-inflammatory is good for the gut and brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>sizeable portion of vegetables (two-thirds of your plate) and about 75 to 115g of protein.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You’ll get your fats from those found naturally in protein, from ingredients used to prepare the protein dish and vegetables, such as butter and olive oil, and from nuts and seeds.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Coffee also stimulates a specific gene pathway called the Nrf2 pathway. When this is triggered, it causes the body to make higher levels of protective antioxidants, while reducing inflammation and enhancing detoxification. Other Nrf2 activators are chocolate (another bonus for cocoa), green tea, turmeric, and resveratrol, an ingredient in red wine.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Interestingly, the effect was the same even when the alcohol was removed. The researchers also analyzed the bacterial composition of the stool of such individuals and found a significant increase in bifidobacteria. Red wine is also a rich source of those gut-loving polyphenols. Just be sure that you don’t drink too much. A glass a day for women, two for men at the most.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Prebiotics occur naturally in a variety of foods, including chicory, Jerusalem artichoke, garlic, onions, leeks, and jicama or Mexican yam;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Researchers have determined that beta-HBA, which is easily obtainable just by adding coconut oil to your diet, improves antioxidant function, increases the number of mitochondria, and stimulates the growth of new brain cells.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>No food but lots of water (avoid caffeine) for a twenty-four-hour period.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My fasting protocol is simple: No food but lots of water (avoid caffeine) for a twenty-four-hour period.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I recommend fasting at least four times a year; fasting during the seasonal changes (for example, the last week of September, December, March, and June) is an excellent practice to keep.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Louis Pasteur famously said “Chance favors the prepared mind.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Consider and then act, don’t react.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2016-01-25-brain-maker.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Laws of Medicine</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-12-28-laws-medicine.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#the-laws-of-medicine-field-notes-from-an-uncertain-science-mukherjee-siddhartha">The Laws of Medicine: Field Notes from an Uncertain Science (Mukherjee, Siddhartha)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1439172237l/25409816.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="the-laws-of-medicine-field-notes-from-an-uncertain-science-mukherjee-siddhartha">The Laws of Medicine: Field Notes from an Uncertain Science (Mukherjee, Siddhartha)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>The only way to break the deadly monotony was to read. In the medieval story, a prisoner is sent to jail with just one book, but discovers a cosmos of a thousand books in that single volume.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if you had a hammer, as the saying goes, then everything looks like a nail.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sciences have laws—statements of truth based on repeated experimental observations that describe some universal or generalizable attributes of nature.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>law distills a relationship between observable phenomena that remains true across multiple circumstances and multiple conditions. Laws are rules that nature must live by. There are fewer laws in chemistry. Biology is the most lawless of the three basic sciences: there are few rules to begin with, and even fewer rules that are universal.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every diagnostic challenge in medicine can be imagined as a probability game.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a test can only be interpreted sanely in the context of prior probabilities.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This is the way we intuit the world, Bayes argued. There is no absolute knowledge; there is only conditional knowledge. History repeats itself—and so do statistical patterns. The past is the best guide to the future.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every outlier represents an opportunity to refine our understanding of illness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Inliers” allow us to create rules—but “outliers” act as portals to understand deeper laws.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Karl Popper proposed a crucial criterion for distinguishing a scientific system from an unscientific one. The fundamental feature of a scientific system, Popper argued, is not that its propositions are verifiable, but that its propositions are falsifiable—i.e., every theory carries an inherent possibility of proving it false. A theory or proposition can only be judged “scientific” if it carries within it a prediction or observation that will prove it false. Theories that fail to generate such “falsifiable” conjectures are not scientific</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The human genome has about twenty-four thousand genes in total.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every science suffers from human biases. Even as we train massive machines to collect, store, and manipulate data for us, humans are the final observers, interpreters, and arbiters of that data. In medicine, the biases are particularly acute for two reasons. The first is hope: we want our medicines to work.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“Doctors,” Voltaire wrote, “are men who prescribe medicines of which they know little, to cure diseases of which they know less, in human beings of whom they know nothing.” The pivotal word in this scathing description is know. The discipline of medicine concerns the manipulation of knowledge under uncertainty.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-12-28-laws-medicine.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Thinking, Fast and Slow</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-12-07-thinking-fast-slow.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#thinking-fast-and-slow-kahneman-daniel">Thinking, Fast and Slow (Kahneman, Daniel)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1317793965l/11468377.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="thinking-fast-and-slow-kahneman-daniel">Thinking, Fast and Slow (Kahneman, Daniel)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>“The situation has provided a cue; this cue has given the expert access to information stored in memory, and the information provides the answer. Intuition is nothing more and nothing less than recognition.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Overconfidence is fed by the illusory certainty of hindsight. My views on this topic have been influenced by Nassim Taleb, the author of The Black Swan. I hope for watercooler conversations that intelligently explore the lessons that can be learned from the past while resisting the lure of hindsight and the illusion of certainty.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The gorilla study illustrates two important facts about our minds: we can be blind to the obvious, and we are also blind to our blindness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you know that the lines are equally long. If asked about their length, you will say what you know. But you still see the bottom line as longer. You have chosen to believe the measurement, but you cannot prevent System 1 from doing its thing; you cannot decide to see the lines as equal, although you know they are.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Not all illusions are visual. There are illusions of thought, which we call cognitive illusions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As a way to live your life, however, continuous vigilance is not necessarily good, and it is certainly impractical. Constantly questioning our own thinking would be impossibly tedious, and System 2 is much too slow and inefficient to serve as a substitute for System 1 in making routine decisions. The best we can do is a compromise: learn to recognize situations in which mistakes are likely and try harder to avoid significant mistakes when the stakes are high. The premise of this book is that it is easier to recognize other people’s mistakes than our own.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the pupil was a good measure of the physical arousal that accompanies mental effort, and we could go ahead and use it to understand how the mind works. Much like the electricity meter outside your house or apartment, the pupils offer an index of the current rate at which mental energy is used.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Any task that requires you to keep several ideas in mind at the same time has the same hurried character. Unless you have the good fortune of a capacious working memory, you may be forced to work uncomfortably hard. The most effortful forms of slow thinking are those that require you to think fast.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The psychologist Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi (pronounced six-cent-mihaly) has done more than anyone else to study this state of effortless attending, and the name he proposed for it, flow, has become part of the language. People who experience flow describe it as “a state of effortless concentration so deep that they lose their sense of time, of themselves, of their problems,” and their descriptions of the joy of that state are so compelling that Csikszentmihalyi has called it an “optimal experience.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>People who are cognitively busy are also more likely to make selfish choices, use sexist language, and make superficial judgments in social situations.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The nervous system consumes more glucose than most other parts of the body, and effortful mental activity appears to be especially expensive in the currency of glucose. When you are actively involved in difficult cognitive reasoning or engaged in a task that requires self-control, your blood glucose level drops. The effect is analogous to a runner who draws down glucose stored in her muscles during a sprint. The bold implication of this idea is that the effects of ego depletion could be undone by ingesting glucose,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if you have had to force yourself to do something, you are less willing or less able to exert self-control when the next challenge comes around. The phenomenon has been named ego depletion.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when people believe a conclusion is true, they are also very likely to believe arguments that appear to support it, even when these arguments are unsound. If System 1 is involved, the conclusion comes first and the arguments follow.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Intelligence is not only the ability to reason; it is also the ability to find relevant material in memory and to deploy attention when needed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Those who avoid the sin of intellectual sloth could be called “engaged.” They are more alert, more intellectually active, less willing to be satisfied with superficially attractive answers, more skeptical about their intuitions. The psychologist Keith Stanovich would call them more rational.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As cognitive scientists have emphasized in recent years, cognition is embodied; you think with your body, not only with your brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>This remarkable priming phenomenon—the influencing of an action by the idea—is known as the ideomotor effect.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>being amused tends to make you smile, and smiling tends to make you feel amused.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“act calm and kind regardless of how you feel” is very good advice: you are likely to be rewarded by actually feeling calm and kind.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>reliable way to make people believe in falsehoods is frequent repetition, because familiarity is not easily distinguished from truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>All this is very good advice, but we should not get carried away. High-quality paper, bright colors, and rhyming or simple language will not be much help if your message is obviously nonsensical, or if it contradicts facts that your audience knows to be true.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>performance was better with the bad font.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Zajonc argued that the effect of repetition on liking is a profoundly important biological fact, and that it extends to all animals. To survive in a frequently dangerous world, an organism should react cautiously to a novel stimulus, with withdrawal and fear. Survival prospects are poor for an animal that is not suspicious of novelty. However, it is also adaptive for the initial caution to fade if the stimulus is actually safe. The mere exposure effect occurs, Zajonc claimed, because the repeated exposure of a stimulus is followed by nothing bad. Such a stimulus will eventually become a safety signal, and safety is good.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Mood evidently affects the operation of System 1: when we are uncomfortable and unhappy, we lose touch with our intuition.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the connection makes biological sense. A good mood is a signal that things are generally going well, the environment is safe, and it is all right to let one’s guard down. A bad mood indicates that things are not going very well, there may be a threat, and vigilance is required. Cognitive ease is both a cause and a consequence of a pleasant feeling.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We have norms for a vast number of categories, and these norms provide the background for the immediate detection of anomalies</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>a large event is supposed to have consequences, and consequences need causes to explain them. We have limited information about what happened on a day, and System 1 is adept at finding a coherent causal story that links the fragments of knowledge at its disposal.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we are born prepared to make intentional attributions: infants under one year old identify bullies and victims, and expect a pursuer to follow the most direct path in attempting to catch whatever it is chasing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when System 2 is otherwise engaged, we will believe almost anything. System 1 is gullible and biased to believe, System 2 is in charge of doubting and unbelieving, but System 2 is sometimes busy, and often lazy. Indeed, there is evidence that people are more likely to be influenced by empty persuasive messages, such as commercials, when they are tired and depleted.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The tendency to like (or dislike) everything about a person—including things you have not observed—is known as the halo effect.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Gilbert proposed that understanding a statement must begin with an attempt to believe it: you must first know what the idea would mean if it were true. Only then can you decide whether or not to unbelieve it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>simple rule can help: before an issue is discussed, all members of the committee should be asked to write a very brief summary of their position. This procedure makes good use of the value of the diversity of knowledge and opinion in the group.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Jumping to conclusions on the basis of limited evidence is so important to an understanding of intuitive thinking, and comes up so often in this book, that I will use a cumbersome abbreviation for it: WYSIATI, which stands for what you see is all there is. System 1 is radically insensitive to both the quality and the quantity of the information that gives rise to impressions and intuitions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>It is the consistency of the information that matters for a good story, not its completeness. Indeed, you will often find that knowing little makes it easier to fit everything you know into a coherent pattern.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Here we encounter a new aptitude of System 1. An underlying scale of intensity allows matching across diverse dimensions.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>assessment. You do that automatically whether or not you</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>you often have answers to questions that you do not completely understand, relying on evidence that you can neither explain nor defend.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>How to Solve It: “If you can’t solve a problem, then there is an easier problem you can solve: find it.” Pólya’s heuristics are strategic procedures that are deliberately implemented by System 2.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The dominance of conclusions over arguments is most pronounced where emotions are involved.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“people are not adequately sensitive to sample size.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we are prone to exaggerate the consistency and coherence of what we see. The exaggerated faith of researchers in what can be learned from a few observations is closely related to the halo effect, the sense we often get that we know and understand a person about whom we actually know very little.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>if you follow your intuition, you will more often than not err by misclassifying a random event as systematic. We are far too willing to reject the belief that much of what we see in life is random.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>anchoring effect. It occurs when people consider a particular value for an unknown quantity before estimating that quantity. What happens is one of the most reliable and robust results of experimental psychology: the estimates stay close to the number that people considered—hence the image of an anchor.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The conclusion is clear: anchors do not have their effects because people believe they are informative.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My advice to students when I taught negotiations was that if you think the other side has made an outrageous proposal, you should not come back with an equally outrageous counteroffer, creating a gap that will be difficult to bridge in further negotiations. Instead you should make a scene, storm out or threaten to do so, and make it clear—to yourself as well as to the other side—that you will not continue the negotiation with that number on the table.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>general, a strategy of deliberately “thinking the opposite” may be a good defense against anchoring effects, because it negates the biased recruitment of thoughts that produces these effects.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You are always aware of the anchor and even pay attention to it, but you do not know how it guides and constrains your thinking, because you cannot imagine how you would have thought if the anchor had been different (or absent). However, you should assume that any number that is on the table has had an anchoring effect on you, and if the stakes are high you should mobilize yourself (your System 2) to combat the effect.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Kunreuther also observed that protective actions, whether by individuals or governments, are usually designed to be adequate to the worst disaster actually experienced.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The world in our heads is not a precise replica of reality; our expectations about the frequency of events are distorted by the prevalence and emotional intensity of the messages to which we are exposed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Slovic has challenged the foundation of their expertise: the idea that risk is objective. “Risk” does not exist “out there,” independent of our minds and culture, waiting to be measured. Human beings have invented the concept of “risk” to help them understand and cope with the dangers and uncertainties of life. Although these dangers are real, there is no such thing as “real risk” or “objective risk.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Every parent who has stayed up waiting for a teenage daughter who is late from a party will recognize the feeling. You may know that there is really (almost) nothing to worry about, but you cannot help images of disaster from coming to mind. As Slovic has argued, the amount of concern is not adequately sensitive to the probability of harm; you are imagining the numerator—the tragic story you saw on the news—and not thinking about the denominator. Sunstein has coined the phrase “probability neglect” to describe the pattern. The combination of probability neglect with the social mechanisms of availability cascades inevitably leads to gross exaggeration of minor threats, sometimes with important consequences.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>mechanism through which biases flow into policy: the availability cascade.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Anchor your judgment of the probability of an outcome on a plausible base rate. Question the diagnosticity of your evidence.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>individuals feel relieved of responsibility when they know that others have heard the same request for help.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Changing one’s mind about human nature is hard work, and changing one’s mind for the worse about oneself is even harder.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Subjects’ unwillingness to deduce the particular from the general was matched only by their willingness to infer the general from the particular.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You are more likely to learn something by finding surprises in your own behavior than by hearing surprising facts about people in general.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>rewards for improved performance work better than punishment of mistakes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>correlation and regression are not two concepts—they are different perspectives on the same concept. The general rule is straightforward but has surprising consequences: whenever the correlation between two scores is imperfect, there will be regression to the mean. To</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In order to conclude that an energy drink—or any other treatment—is effective, you must compare a group of patients who receive this treatment to a “control group” that receives no treatment (or, better, receives a placebo).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>general limitation of the human mind is its imperfect ability to reconstruct past states of knowledge, or beliefs that have changed. Once you adopt a new view of the world (or of any part of it), you immediately lose much of your ability to recall what you used to believe before your mind changed.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In other words, people who spend their time, and earn their living, studying a particular topic produce poorer predictions than dart-throwing monkeys who would have distributed their choices evenly over the options. Even in the region they knew best, experts were not significantly better than nonspecialists. Those who know more forecast very slightly better than those who know less. But those with the most knowledge are often less reliable. The reason is that the person who acquires more knowledge develops an enhanced illusion of her skill and becomes unrealistically overconfident.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The first lesson is that errors of prediction are inevitable because the world is unpredictable. The second is that high subjective confidence is not to be trusted as an indicator of accuracy (low confidence could be more informative).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Several studies have shown that human decision makers are inferior to a prediction formula even when they are given the score suggested by the formula!</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The situation has provided a cue; this cue has given the expert access to information stored in memory, and the information provides the answer. Intuition is nothing more and nothing less than recognition.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>intuition cannot be trusted in the absence of stable regularities in the environment.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>when a project ends reasonably well: once you understand the main conclusion, it seems it was always obvious.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>how can we evaluate the probable validity of an intuitive judgment? When do judgments reflect true expertise? When do they display an illusion of validity? The answer comes from the two basic conditions for acquiring a skill: an environment that is sufficiently regular to be predictable an opportunity to learn these regularities through prolonged practice</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the likelihood that something will go wrong in a big project is high.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>people who have information about an individual case rarely feel the need to know the statistics of the class to which the case belongs. When we were eventually exposed to the outside view, we collectively ignored it. We can recognize what happened to us; it is similar to the experiment that suggested the futility of teaching psychology. When they made predictions about individual cases about which they had a little information (a brief and bland interview), Nisbett and Borgida’s students completely neglected the global results they had just learned. “Pallid” statistical information is routinely discarded when it is incompatible with one’s personal impressions of a case. In the competition with the inside view, the outside view doesn’t stand a chance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Bent Flyvbjerg, now at Oxford University, offered a forceful summary: The prevalent tendency to underweight or ignore distributional information is perhaps the major source of error in forecasting. Planners should therefore make every effort to frame the forecasting problem so as to facilitate utilizing all the distributional information that is available.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>for failing to allow for difficulties that they could not have anticipated—the unknown unknowns.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>call it theory-induced blindness: once you have accepted a theory and used it as a tool in your thinking, it is extraordinarily difficult to notice its flaws. If you come upon an observation that does not seem to fit the model, you assume that there must be a perfectly good explanation that you are somehow missing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You just like winning and dislike losing—and you almost certainly dislike losing more than you like winning.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The slope of the function is steeper in the negative domain; the response to a loss is stronger than the response to a corresponding gain. This was the explanation of the endowment effect that Thaler had been searching for. And the first application of prospect theory to an economic puzzle now appears to have been a significant milestone in the development of behavioral economics.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>paper titled “Bad Is Stronger Than Good,” summarized the evidence as follows: “Bad emotions, bad parents, and bad feedback have more impact than good ones, and bad information is processed more thoroughly than good. The self is more motivated to avoid bad self-definitions than to pursue good ones. Bad impressions and bad stereotypes are quicker to form and more resistant to disconfirmation than good ones.” They cite John Gottman, the well-known expert in marital relations, who observed that the long-term success of a relationship depends far more on avoiding the negative than on seeking the positive. Gottman estimated that a stable relationship requires that good interactions outnumber bad interactions by at least 5 to 1.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Loss aversion refers to the relative strength of two motives: we are driven more strongly to avoid losses than to achieve gains.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Animals, including people, fight harder to prevent losses than to achieve gains. In the world of territorial animals, this principle explains the success of defenders. A biologist observed that “when a territory holder is challenged by a rival, the owner almost always wins the contest—usually within a matter of seconds.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>von Neumann and Morgenstern introduced in 1944. They proved that any weighting of uncertain outcomes that is not strictly proportional to probability leads to inconsistencies and other disasters.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>My experience illustrates how terrorism works and why it is so effective: it induces an availability cascade.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The psychology of high-prize lotteries is similar to the psychology of terrorism. The thrilling possibility of winning the big prize is shared by the community and reinforced by conversations at work and at home. Buying a ticket is immediately rewarded by pleasant fantasies, just as avoiding a bus was immediately rewarded by relief from fear. In both cases, the actual probability is inconsequential; only possibility matters. The original formulation of prospect theory included the argument that “highly unlikely events are either ignored or overweighted,” but it did not specify the conditions under which one or the other will occur, nor did it propose a psychological interpretation of it. My current view of decision weights has been strongly influenced by recent research on the role of emotions and vividness in decision making. Overweighting of unlikely outcomes is rooted in System 1 features that are familiar by now. Emotion and vividness influence fluency, availability, and judgments of probability—and thus account for our excessive response to the few rare events that we do not ignore.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>People overestimate the probabilities of unlikely events. People overweight unlikely events in their decisions. Although overestimation and overweighting are distinct phenomena, the same psychological mechanisms are involved in both: focused attention, confirmation bias, and cognitive ease.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The common feature of these poignant stories is that they involve unusual events—and unusual events are easier than normal events to undo in imagination.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>An abnormal event attracts attention, and it also activates the idea of the event that would have been normal under the same circumstances.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Losses are weighted about twice as much as gains in several contexts: choice between gambles, the endowment effect, and reactions to price changes. The loss-aversion coefficient is much higher in some situations. In particular, you may be more loss averse for aspects of your life that are more important than money, such as health. Furthermore, your reluctance to “sell” important endowments increases dramatically when doing so might make you responsible for an awful outcome.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You can also take precautions that will inoculate you against regret. Perhaps the most useful is to be explicit about the anticipation of regret. If you can remember when things go badly that you considered the possibility of regret carefully before deciding, you are likely to experience less of it. You should also know that regret and hindsight bias will come together, so anything you can do to preclude hindsight is likely to be helpful. My personal hindsight-avoiding policy is to be either very thorough or completely casual when making a decision with long-term consequences. Hindsight is worse when you think a little, just enough to tell yourself later, “I almost made a better choice.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the emotion evoked by a word can “leak” into the final choice.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But the experience was not actually ruined, only the memory of it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>What we learn from the past is to maximize the qualities of our future memories, not necessarily of our future experience. This is the tyranny of the remembering self.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Tastes and decisions are shaped by memories, and the memories can be wrong.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>story is about significant events and memorable moments, not about time passing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Duration neglect is normal in a story, and the ending often defines its character. The same core features appear in the rules of narratives and in the memories of colonoscopies, vacations, and films. This is how the remembering self works: it composes stories and keeps them for future reference.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“You seem to be devoting your entire vacation to the construction of memories. Perhaps you should put away the camera and enjoy the moment, even if it is not very memorable?”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Csikszentmihalyi calls flow—a state that some artists experience in their creative moments and that many other people achieve when enthralled by a film, a book, or a crossword puzzle: interruptions are not welcome in any of these situations.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>focusing illusion, which can be described in a single sentence: Nothing in life is as important as you think it is when you are thinking about it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We believe that duration is important, but our memory tells us it is not.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Humans, unlike Econs, need help to make good decisions, and there are informed and unintrusive ways to provide that help.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The way to block errors that originate in System 1 is simple in principle: recognize the signs that you are in a cognitive minefield, slow down, and ask for reinforcement from System 2.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-12-07-thinking-fast-slow.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Power of Full Engagement</title>
    <link>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-08-15-fullengagement.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ul>
<li><a href="#the-power-of-full-engagement-managing-energy-not-time-is-the-key-to-high-performance-and-personal-renewal-loehr-jimschwartz-tony">The Power of Full Engagement: Managing Energy, Not Time, is the Key to High Performance and Personal Renewal (Loehr, Jim;Schwartz, Tony)</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1431760957l/68985._SY475_.jpg" />

</div>
<h1 id="the-power-of-full-engagement-managing-energy-not-time-is-the-key-to-high-performance-and-personal-renewal-loehr-jimschwartz-tony">The Power of Full Engagement: Managing Energy, Not Time, is the Key to High Performance and Personal Renewal (Loehr, Jim;Schwartz, Tony)</h1>
<blockquote>
<p>Human beings are complex energy systems, and full engagement is not simply one-dimensional. The energy that pulses through us is physical, emotional, mental, and spiritual.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We, too, must learn to live our own lives as a series of sprints—fully engaging for periods of time, and then fully disengaging and seeking renewal before jumping back into the fray to face whatever challenges confront us.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>As Nietzsche put it, “That which does not kill us makes us stronger.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The power of rituals is that they insure that we use as little conscious energy as possible where it is not absolutely necessary, leaving us free to strategically focus the energy available to us in creative, enriching ways.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Too much energy expenditure without sufficient recovery eventually leads to burnout and breakdown. (Overuse it and lose it.) Too much recovery without sufficient stress leads to atrophy and weakness. (Use it or lose it.)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Cultures that encourage people to seek intermittent renewal not only inspire greater commitment, but also more productivity.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We are oscillatory beings in an oscillatory universe. Rhythmicity is our inheritance.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Expanding capacity requires a willingness to endure short-term discomfort in the service of long-term reward.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“We can experience pleasure without any investment of psychic energy, whereas enjoyment happens only as a result of unusual investments of attention . . . ,” writes psychologist Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi, author of Flow. “The best moments [in our lives] usually occur when a person’s body or mind is stretched to its limits in a voluntary effort to accomplish something difficult and worthwhile.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>the key to expanding capacity is both to push beyond one’s ordinary limits and to regularly seek recovery, which is when growth actually occurs.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The most important rhythms in our lives are the ones we typically take for granted—most notably breathing and eating.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>simplest antidotes to anger and anxiety is to take deep abdominal breaths.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>researchers found that a series of short doses of intense aerobic activity—each one sixty seconds or less—followed by complete aerobic recovery, had a profound positive impact on participants. In a period of just eight weeks, the subjects exhibited significant improvements in cardiovascular fitness, heart-rate variability and mood.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Rigorous training improves a person’s ability to perform on the battlefield. . . . The concept of stress inoculation is very much like the concept of preventing a particular disease through vaccination. Like immunization, which occurs only when the vaccine is given in the proper dosage, stress inoculation occurs only when the stress intensity is at the optimal level—high enough to activate a person’s psychological and biological systems, but low enough so as not to overwhelm them. If the stress level is not high enough, inoculation will not occur; if the stress level is too high, stress sensitization will occur, and the individual will probably perform less effectively when he is stressed again.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Snowden discovered that those nuns whose writing expressed a preponderance of positive emotions (happiness, love, hope, gratitude and contentment) tended to live longer and more productive lives.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Researchers such as Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi have found that prolonged television watching is actually correlated with increased anxiety and low-level depression. Conversely, the richer and deeper the source of emotional recovery, the more we refill our reserves and the more resilient we become. Effective emotional renewal puts us in a position to perform more effectively, especially under pressure.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To be fully engaged emotionally requires celebrating what the Stoic philosophers called anacoluthia—the mutual entailment of the virtues. By this notion, no virtue is a virtue by itself. Rather, all virtues are entailed. Honesty without compassion, for example, becomes cruelty. We are, in effect, the sum of our complexities and contradictions. Practically, we must focus on building emotional capacity wherever it is that we are most out of balance. The ultimate goal is to move more freely and flexibly between our own opposites.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The brain represents just 2 percent of the body’s weight, but requires almost 25 percent of its oxygen.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The greatest geniuses,” da Vinci told his patron, “sometimes accomplish more when they work less.” In his Treatise on Painting, da Vinci wrote, “It is a very good plan every now and then to go away and have a little relaxation. . . . When you come back to the work your judgment will be surer, since to remain constantly at work will cause you to lose the power of judgment.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Five stages are now widely recognized: first insight, saturation, incubation, illumination and verification.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The quantity of energy we have to spend at any given moment is a reflection of our physical capacity. Our motivation to spend what we have is largely a spiritual issue.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Some activities generate considerable spiritual renewal without demanding significant energy expenditure. These include walking in nature, reading an inspirational book, listening to music, or hearing a great speaker. Spiritual practices, by contrast, can be renewing and demanding at the same time. Meditation, for example, requires mobilizing highly focused attention to quiet the mind, but may also prompt a rejuvenating experience of expansive openness, connectedness and even joy. Like yoga, meditation is a practice that can cut across all dimensions, building spiritual capacity while also providing mental and emotional recovery.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>all service to others, which involves considerable effort and even inconvenience, but may also provide a profound source of meaning and deep satisfaction.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The irony is that self-absorption ultimately drains energy and impedes performance. The more preoccupied we are with our own fears and concerns, the less energy we have available to take positive action. Subordinating our self-interest to something beyond ourselves may feel threatening at first, but as Gary discovered, it can also be immensely rewarding—a means by which to experience a deeper sense of meaning and greater self-worth. The commitment to live according to our deepest values not only creates a more stable center in our lives but also helps us to better navigate the challenges we face along the way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Nietzsche’s famous words, “He who has a why to live for can bear with almost any how.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we learned that visualizing a performance challenge in advance is a very effective way to allay anxiety and to perform without awkwardness or self-consciousness.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Wade Roofs has defined spirituality as “knowing our deepest selves and what is sacred to us.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Arthur Ashe once put it: “From what we get in life, we make a living. From what we give, we make a life.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>emotions such as fear, anger and even hatred can be a powerful source of energy. The problem is the cost. As we saw earlier, negative emotions drain energy and prompt the release of hormones that are toxic to our systems over time.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes it’s more important to stay connected with people than to be right.”</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>we feel more passion for and derive more pleasure from doing what we freely choose and most enjoy.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>capitolo <em>molto</em> bello. Deepest purpose.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Purpose becomes a more powerful and enduring source of energy when its source moves from negative to positive, external to internal and self to others.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>When we aren’t investing energy in protecting our turf, we have the potential to see more of the truth and to continue to learn and grow.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>We can derive as much value from studying and understanding our failures as we can from celebrating and reinforcing our successes.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“What amazes me most,” Roger told us, “is that once my values became clear and I got the hang of building rituals, most of the changes I made weren’t that hard. My life acquired a certain rhythm. I can feel how much my energy has rubbed off on the people in my life. My challenge now is just to feel the pulse and keep the beat.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://jak3.github.io/mica/enote/en/2015-08-15-fullengagement.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>Giacomo Mantani</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
